<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Ten introductions how to read, and in reading, how to vnderstand; and in vnderstanding, how to beare in mind all the bookes, chapters, and verses, contained in the holie Bible. With an answer for lawyers. Physitions. Ministers.</title>
            <author>Vaughan, Edward, preacher at St. Mary Woolnoth.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1594</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 214 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 111 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A14282</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 24599</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S119031</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99854238</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99854238</idno>
            <idno type="VID">19647</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A14282)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19647)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1368:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Ten introductions how to read, and in reading, how to vnderstand; and in vnderstanding, how to beare in mind all the bookes, chapters, and verses, contained in the holie Bible. With an answer for lawyers. Physitions. Ministers.</title>
                  <author>Vaughan, Edward, preacher at St. Mary Woolnoth.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[222] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by A. Islip,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1594.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: Edw. Vaughan.</note>
                  <note>The words "lawyers. Physitions. Ministers." are bracketed together on the title page.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A a B-N (-N8).</note>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
                  <note>Some print faded, considerable print show-through, and some pages stained.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible --  Study and teaching --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:19647:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19647:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>TEN Introductions: How to read, and in reading, how to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand; and in vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, how to beare in mind all the bookes, chapters, and verſes, contained in the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie Bible. <hi>With an Anſwer</hi> For
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Lawyers.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Phyſitions.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Miniſters.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON, <hi>Printed by A. Iſlip.</hi> 1594.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:19647:2"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>blazon or coat of arms of Tobias Wood(?), featuring three birds</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:19647:2"/>
            <head>To the right Worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipfull maiſter <hi>Tobie Wood,</hi> Eſquire, and Councellor at Law, dwelling neere her Maieſties Tower in London, the true and vndoubted Patrone of this booke.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S three ſpeciall occaſions mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued S. Peter to offer his la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour in buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of three Tabernacles;<note n="a" place="margin">Mat. 17, 3.4.</note> one for Chriſt one for Moſes, and one for Elias: euen ſo (right Worſhipfull) three ſpeciall occaſions moued me to offer this my la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor
<pb facs="tcp:19647:3"/> in the building of a ſpirituall Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle, one for meere<note n="b" place="margin">1 Cor. 12, 12.13.14. to 25. Phil. 2, 19.20.21. 1. Cor. 10, 24.</note> care and<note n="c" place="margin">Act. 24, 16. Rom. 9, 1.2.3.4.5.</note> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience to my<note n="d" place="margin">Leuit. 25.25.48.49. Rom. 9, 5.</note> contrimen in Wales, one to kindle my<note n="e" place="margin">1. Sam. 16.2.20, 2.4.9.12.13.17.12, 10.</note> faithfull affections to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards you, and one to ſatiſfie the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt<note n="f" place="margin">By his let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters dated, <hi>Ianuar.</hi> 20. <hi>Apr.</hi> 5. And one, <hi>May</hi> 2. 1592.</note> of a right worſhipfull gentleman, Sir <hi>William Herbert</hi> knight, who would ioyne with me in this worke. If the care of my countrimen might be vnſupplied; and if the worthineſſe of this learned and zealous knight might be (as he is in the graue) for euer ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenced; yet the heartie affections, the bond of thankefulneſse, and the chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian duety I owe you, can no way ſo effectually be diſcharged. Wherein alſo I ſhall make cleare my good conſcience towards the one, and my humble due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty towards the other: which if you ſhall pleaſe to patronize, whatſoeuer is found wanting by him which is dead, ſhall be ſupplied (I doubt not) to your contentment, by them which are aliue.
<pb facs="tcp:19647:3"/>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Exo. 37, 7.</note> As the two Cherubins which Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes made, tended to the preſeruation of Gods people,<note place="margin">The Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod and nine ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruations.</note> and therefore both were placed vpon the Arke as one: euen ſo (good worſhipfull Sir) the two former books which I made, tended to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of Gods people, in the holie Bible; and therefore I haue placed them both in one.<note n="h" place="margin">Pſal. 62, 11.12.13.</note> As God ſpake once and twice that power and mercie belongeth vnto him: ſo I will ſpeake once, twice, and euer to his maieſtie, that power may be giuen by his ſpirit, and mercie by his ſonne, to all that long with Zeale to the knowledge hereof. Theſe are to certifie<note n="i" place="margin">Ier. 9.17.18.19.</note> you, though not for news, there was great<note n="k" place="margin">Ezech. 32.1.2.3.</note> lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in Syon, becauſe of Gods iuſtice for their ſinnes, as there was great la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation for Pharao in Aegypt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he was a lion in the land, and a dragon in the ſea; and as there was great<note n="l" place="margin">Heſt. 4.3.</note> ſorrow, faſting, mourning, and
<pb facs="tcp:19647:4"/> weeping, among the Iewes, becauſe the king had decreed their deaths: euen ſo there is great cauſe of lamentation, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting, mourning, and weeping here in England, becauſe<note n="m" place="margin">Ier. 9, 21.</note> death is ſcaling our windowes, the<note n="n" place="margin">Eze. 32.4.</note> beaſts of the fields hungering to deuoure our bodies; our bloud readie to water the land;<note place="margin">Eze. 32, 6.</note> and our<note n="o" place="margin">Mat, 7, 19.13, 42.43.18.9. Iud. 9, Reu 19, 20.</note> ſoules as prepared for the fire of hell, by reaſon of ſinnes in the<note n="p" place="margin">Hoſ. 4, 1.2.</note> common ſort, of horrible crueltie in many of them that are<note n="q" place="margin">Eſa. 3, 12. Hoſ. 7, 3.4.5.</note> great, and of the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall ignorance of Chriſt, according to his goſpell, in euerie ſort. If it pleaſe you to compare the raigne of<note n="r" place="margin">Kin. 20, 21.</note> Manaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, ſometimes king of Iudah, with the raigne of Marie; ſometimes queene of England, you ſhall finde little oddes in the innocent blood that the one ſhed at Ieruſalem, and the innocent bloud that was ſhed at London, &amp;c. which God the righteous iudge hath not yet fully reuenged, becauſe that the vnifor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie
<pb facs="tcp:19647:4"/> in the profeſsio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Chriſt theſe <hi>36</hi> years, is not yet perfect, &amp; the perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of former times are not done away by repentance. For notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding the great<note n="s" place="margin">2. Kin. 22.23.</note> zeale of Ioſias, with the obedience of his people, yet the former ſinnes of Manaſses would not be forgotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God knowes, and moſt wiſe men ſees, we haue vrgent occaſions mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing vs to pray, yea, to pray heartely vnto Ieſus Chriſt the aeternall king, for Elizabeth our queene, and other hir ſubiects, that either be will vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly forgiue, or at the leaſt grant, that the penaltie deſerued doe not fall vpon vs, nor vpon our children. And albeit we cannot ſhake off the generall condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation threatned and knowne to hang ouer England, yet hir maiesty with vs, and we with hir, loathing our own ſins, and deteſting the abhomination of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, ſhall be ſingled and ſeuered to preſeruation, come the deſolation neuer
<pb facs="tcp:19647:5"/> ſo terrible and ſuddaine. Ieruſalem which was ſometimes the citie of the great king, the keeper of the diuine oracles, the receptacle of Angels, and the continual preſence of God himſelfe, is now become a place of ſulphir and helliſh flames, inhabited with Oules, Eſtriges, and ſuch like noiſome crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures euen ſo they that haue eyes to ſee, may yet ſee the tears and deſolation of the great and famous citie of London, &amp; they that haue ears to heare, may yet heare the cries of hir children, the piti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous lamentation of hir women, and the ſighs of hir men in euerie ſtreet: ſome for their parents, ſome for their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, ſome for their wiues, ſome for their husbands, ſome for mony, and ſome for meat, which the laſt years plague hath ruinated, depriued, and deſolated. Whether this were a reuenge of their ſinnes yet liuing, or a reuenge of their ſinnes alreadie dead, and yet
<pb facs="tcp:19647:5"/> vnrepented, it is not knowne; but ſure it is many woes are paſt, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more are to come, if the peruſing and the examinatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of our ſelues, worke not in vs the conſideration of that great zeale of Gods glorie, the deſire of building the Lords houſe, and the practiſing of ſuch an vpright life as was in the antient fathers of the church. Wherefore I humbly intreat you, and in Chriſt Ieſus I deſire you, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit your place be not to reforme theſe things, ſo generally out of frame, yet reforme and amend your ſelfe and your owne houſhold: ioyne with them, that they may ioyne with you. My good worſhipfull and Chriſtian friend, as I cannot charge you nor any of yours, for any diſorder, ſo I cannot leaue to intreat and deſire you to walke warily and wiſely in this crooked and froward generation, ground your own foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſure, take heed to your ſelfe, looke that
<pb facs="tcp:19647:6"/> noman<note n="t" place="margin">Reu. 3, 11.</note> take away your Crowne. The deuill offreth violence, hold therefore faſt that which you haue, watch and pray, O pray continually, powre out your ſupplications before God mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and euening, both you and your hoſhold.<note n="v" place="margin">Pſal. 5, 3.</note> Morning and euening (ſaid Dauid) will I direct my praiers vnto thee. As the morning and euening is a ſit and a conuenient time for ſutors to attend vpon great men, and as the morning was a ſit and a conuenient time to gather Manna:<note n="x" place="margin">Gen. 28, 18.</note> euen ſo (good ſir) the morning and euening is a ſitte and a conuenient time, for you and your houſhold to become ſutors vnto the great maieſty of God, for the ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall Manna, the food of your ſoules. As Moſes was commanded to come vp to Sinai, with the two tables of the law, early in the morning: euen ſo are we commanded to appeare before God in our chambers, early in the morning,
<pb facs="tcp:19647:6"/> before we goe abroad, hauing the two Teſtaments of God in our hands, lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning how to honor his maieſty in the one, and how to vſe our bretheren cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritably in the other, both which are the two principall dueties of euerie chriſtian. As the learning muſt needs goe before the practiſing, ſo the practiſing muſt needs follow after the learning. Learne (I beſeech you) there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and teach your houſhold the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Lord, morning and eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning; not in regard of him to whom all times are alike, but in regard of your ſelues, becauſe in the morning &amp; euening is the fitteſt and moſt conueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent time, by meditations and praiers to recommend your ſoules vnto his maieſty, and to contemplate of heauenly things. And thus hauing indeuored your eaſe and ſpeedy profit in theſe my introductions, by taking ſome thing away, and by adding other more need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full,
<pb facs="tcp:19647:7"/> with anſwers to three neceſsarie queſtions, I take my leaue, not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getting my humble commendations to your ſelfe and to the good Chriſtian Gentlewoman Ms. Barbara your wife, deſiring the maieſty of my aeternall God to finiſh your labors to the glorie of his name, to the good of his ſaints, and to the ſaluation of your and their ſoules. From Leonard Shorditch, the <hi>18</hi> of <hi>Octob. 1594.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Yours becauſe you be of Chriſt.</hi> Edw: <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>aughan.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:19647:7"/>
            <head>An admonition to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation for the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and eſpecially for my countriemen of Wales.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S among all other or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarie accidences that are incident to the proſperitie or aduerſitie of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde, there is nothing in earth that more fully proportioneth the ioys in heauen, than Muſicke, and Mariage: to heare the one, we leaue our meat and drinke; and to be ioyned in the other, w
<pb facs="tcp:19647:8"/> leaue father and mother; euen ſo among all ordinarie inſtructions incident to the earthly proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and aeternall felicitie of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde, there is nothing that more fully proportioneth our condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation to be iuſt, than the law; nor any thing that more fully propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioneth our ſaluation to be in Chriſt Ieſus, than the Goſpell. In the one we heare thu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dring, earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quakes, lamentations, mournings and woe: in the other nothing elſe but ſweet voices, pleaſaunt ſongs, and inſtruments of mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicke, all proportioning and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petually pointing our marriage with Chriſt Ieſus, in whom we are freed from the curſe &amp; threats of the law, &amp; all other inconueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences whatſoeuer; who ſaith vnto vs as vnto his bride, My Doue ſhew me thy ſelfe, let me heare
<pb facs="tcp:19647:8"/> thy voice, thy voice is ſweet,<note place="margin">Cant. 2, 14.4, 1. to 8.</note> and thy ſight comly. Behold thou art faire, behold thou art faire, thou art all faire my loue, &amp; there is no ſpot within thee. Now then (good chriſtian Reader) tell me, tell me, I pray you, tel me, who wil not leaue marrying with a noble Lady in Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael or in England, to be marryed with Chriſt Ieſus in heuen? &amp; who wil not leaue all the muſicke &amp; all the pleaſurs of this life, to obtaine the companie of Angels, the ioys of heauen, and the preſence of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt himſelfe? The ſtudie and the diligent apprehending of theſe exceeding great bleſſedneſſe, doe conſiſt in the apprehending of the true vſe and intent of the law and the Goſpell.</p>
            <p>Ceaſe not, ceaſe not, O my good contriemen and friends, whilſt you liue ceaſe not to cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brate
<pb facs="tcp:19647:9"/> the wonderfull wonders of <hi>Iehoua,</hi> of <hi>Iehoua,</hi> our aeternall God and ſauior <hi>Iehoua,</hi> O behold and contemplate who is ſo great a God as our God; is not the God of Iſrael the God of England? and is not the vniformitie of his truth among vs as it was among them who liued in tents and taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles? O Engliſh Iſrael, O people of England, the high Sacrificer, the perpetuall <hi>Aaron</hi> hath powred out vpon thee as out of a ful horn, the dew of Hermon,<note place="margin">Pſal. 133.1.2.</note> the ioy of the whole earth. O my loue, my ſpouſe (ſaith Chriſt) thou waſt in the rocks ſolitarie,<note place="margin">Cant. 2.14.</note> like a Doue that had loſt hir mate, thou waſt vpon the hils all bruſed and bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, like a bird ſcarred from hir young ones,<note place="margin">Pſal. 11.1.2.</note> and thou waſt in the wilderneſſe all weake and blo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, like a woman no rather deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered
<pb facs="tcp:19647:9"/> of hir child, forced to flee,<note place="margin">Reu. 12, 1.2.3.</note> for the ſafegard of hir owne life. Ariſe now my loue, my faire one, and come away,<note place="margin">Cant. 2, 11.12.13.</note> for behold win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is paſt, the rain is changed and gone away, the flowers appeare in the earth, the time of the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging of birds is come, and the voice of the Turtle is heard in our land. As though Chriſt had ſaid; True it is O my beloued bride, my wife, my dear one, yee were perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted too and fro, yee were hid here and there, yee were in places of ſmall comfort, as in a rocke, yee were in places of ſcarſitie, as in a hill or mountaine, and yee were in danger of your liues as among wild beaſts in the wilderneſſe: but take a good heart, feare not, caſt away euerie thing that preſſeth downe, and the ſinne that hangs on ſo faſt betraying the ſuccors
<pb facs="tcp:19647:10"/> which reaſon offreth. Winter, which is by relation, The time of deſolation, is paſt. Su<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mer which ſignifieth Peace and Plentie, is come, all arguments in the earth and in the elements inforceth the proofe thereof, for euerie thing in their order and kind doe bring forth a ioy innarrable, by the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction of frute. Well then (my good friends and countriemen) remember your ſelues, conſider wel what you are, where you liue, and the time you liue in, take time in time to repent, vſe the ſeaſon, obſerue the opportunity in which you may bequeath and dedicate your ſelues to God. Now is that acceptable time: You haue had many ioyfull iubilees, you haue now the preſence of the Ark, nay, ye haue the preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of Ieſus Chriſt himſelfe. <hi>Moſes</hi> rod hath eaten vp
<pb facs="tcp:19647:10"/> the rods of the Aegyptian force<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers;<note place="margin">Exod. 7.12. 1. Sam. 5, 4.</note> the Lords Arke hath thrown downe the Philiſtins Dagon, and the ſound of Gods ſiluer Trumpets haue broken the neck of poperie, for the voice of the Turtle is heard in our land. The church, the Sanctified Syon, is this Turtle; the preaching of the word is hir voice, which we haue heard this ſix and thirty ſummers, by the godly gouernment of a Turtle, in the ſame nature and kinde, who liues ſolely and ſolita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily, not meet to be matched with any but with Ieſus Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe.</p>
            <p>The ſon of <hi>Sirach</hi> ſaith; There be two manner of people that I abhorre, and the third are no peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: the firſt that ſit vpon the mountains of Samaria, the ſecond the Philiſtins that dwell in Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chimis.
<pb facs="tcp:19647:11"/> They that ſit vpon the mountaines of Samatia, repoſe themſelues vpon the authoritie of Rome, the Philiſtins repreſent the Turke, Sarazens, and other miſcreants; Theſe are the ſons of men (ſaid <hi>Dauid;</hi>) Theſe are the generation of vipers, (ſaid <hi>Iohn</hi> Baptiſt; Theſe are the children of darkeneſſe (ſaid S. <hi>Paule;</hi>) and theſe are they (ſay all men) that labor to ouer-run our countries, to ouerthrow our churches, to burne our houſes, to bereaue vs of our liues, and to depriue vs of our queene, and both hir and vs of the Goſpell. They conſpire againſt God like Hipocrites, againſt our quiet queen like traitors, &amp; againſt our common weale like ſpoilers. My good countriemen and kinſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, if you will adhibite any cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dite to my councell, if you haue
<pb facs="tcp:19647:11"/> any comfort in the mercifulneſſe of God, and if you haue any bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els of Chriſtian affection to your poſteritie, then now at the laſt get you Bibles; leaue off your beads, place learned preachers; diſplace Ieroboams Prieſts, walke in the light of the goſpell; extinguiſh the light of Tapers and Torches, the one brings you the high way to heauen, the other the ready way to hell.</p>
            <p>As <hi>Ioab</hi> tooke hold on the horns of the Alter for the ſafegard of his life: ſo now take you hold on Ieſus Chriſt for the ſafegard of your liues. All kind of creatures are in an vnitie praiſing God, they call you to ioyne and to vnite your ſelues with vs in one religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Strange ſights haue bin ſeen in the element and in the earth, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling you to repentance, fire hath
<pb facs="tcp:19647:12"/> come downe from heauen, fiſhes haue throwne the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues to land, and beaſts haue brought foorth vntimely monſters, calling you to repentance, the earth hath quaked vnder our feete, and our houſes haue ſhaken ouer our heads, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling you to repentance. O ioyne then with vs, &amp; we wil now ioyne with you, let vs goe togither into the houſe of God ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d in hand, &amp; heart in heart, let vs ſing one ſong as with one voice, to the praiſe of our one only God. Thus I haue boldly &amp; briefly admoniſhed you in the Lord; and that you may the better co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>template to your co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort, I haue here, as you ſee, compriſed and compoſed my two former labors into one, with ſome ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraction and with ſome ſuch ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition as may beſt further you to the ſpeech of his diuine maieſty, in your owne perſon, when occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
<pb facs="tcp:19647:12"/> ſhalbe offered for your ſelues &amp; for your houſhold. One quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of a years pains, as I haue poin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, will bring you 40 years pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit in earth, and at the expiration thereof, aeternall pleaſure in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. And when you haue obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned my promiſe, I deſire but your praiers and your meditations to God for me, &amp; for the poſteritie of the religious and magnanimious gentleman, Sir <hi>William Herberd</hi> knight, who for his owne part hath runne his race in the faith of Ieſus Chriſt, and finiſhed his courſe according to conſcience towards you, as may appeare; whoſe body is a ſleepe in the Lord, and whoſe ſoule is in ioy with Ieſus Chriſt. There are three ſorts of profeſſors that doe ſuffer great indignitie at the hands, and from the hearts of many picke-thanke
<pb facs="tcp:19647:13"/> Paraſites, ſtily Sicophants; too too hard, yea heatheniſh or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther helliſh cenſures are giuen in and granted out againſt them. I know their obiections vpon long experience, and I know that vpon ſmall skill and little reading their turneſicke ſpirite of giddi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe may eaſily be quailed, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though through ignorance and wilfull ſtubbernneſſe they will neuer be anſwered. Good Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian countriemen and courteous Readers, I am loath to offend you with tediouſneſſe about theſe matters, hauing a great ſhew of indeuour and purpoſe to draw you to other matters of greater importance. I haue therfore thought good and more conueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, to ſpeake of them in the latter end of this booke. The firſt doth partlie concerne this worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb facs="tcp:19647:13"/> gentleman, to whom I write for protection. The ſecond doth concerne partly mine owne bodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly health, and the third doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne the earthly proſperity, and the heauenly faelicity of all the elect, and therefore I may not paſſe it, neither may you in any caſe omit the learning of it, that with him and me and with the reſt of Gods inheritance you may be readie to defend it. And thus for this time I humbly take my leaue, and with ſuch conueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>encie as I may, do now betake my ſelfe in the feare of God to the matter. From <hi>Leonard</hi> Shor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dich, and county of Middleſex, nere London.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Yours if you be the Lords.</hi> Edw: Vaughan.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:19647:14"/>
            <head>A briefe recitall of the generall heads or places of inuention contained in this booke.</head>
            <p n="1">1 Away to know or to fetch, readilie and roundly, al the books in the booke of God, either backward or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, in the old and new Teſtament.</p>
            <p n="2">2 The Author, the originall, the occaſion, and the
<pb facs="tcp:19647:14"/> chiefe matter of euerie ſuch booke.</p>
            <p n="3">3 The books called Apocry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pha, how farre they are to be receiued, and their imperfectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, when, where, and by whom, found out among themſelues.</p>
            <p n="4">4 The principall ſtories chai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the whole ſcripture diſperſed here and there, in the old and new: where euerie ſuch ſtorie doth begin, and where it ends, with a recitall of the principall matters therin.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <pb facs="tcp:19647:15"/>5 Sir <hi>William Herberts</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count vpon the tenth ſtory, of the age and time from the birth of Chriſt, vnto the worlds end.</p>
            <p n="6">6 Certaine principall obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uations, or ſpeciall matter to be marked for the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and vnderſtanding of all ſuch books as are called Laegall.</p>
            <p n="7">7 Certaine principall obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uations, or ſpeciall matter to be marked, for the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and vnderſtanding of all ſuch books as are called Sapientall.</p>
            <p n="8">
               <pb facs="tcp:19647:15"/>8 Certaine principall obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uations or ſpeciall matter to be marked, for the reading and vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of all ſuch books as are called Propheticall.</p>
            <p n="9">9 Other fourteene places, and moſt direct rules, how to read and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand euery booke, chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and verſe.</p>
            <p n="10">10 Other foure and forty ſure titles or matter ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porting or agreeing with all the ſcriptures, to be
<pb facs="tcp:19647:16"/> digeſted or framed into common places.</p>
            <p n="11">11 The right vſe of poſitiue Laws.</p>
            <p n="12">12 The neceſsitie of Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicke.</p>
            <p n="13">13 The excellencie of the Miniſterie.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <div n="1" type="introduction">
               <pb facs="tcp:19647:16"/>
               <head>1 <hi>Introduction.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Earne perfectly all the names of the Canonicall bookes, as they are in order, from <hi>Geneſis</hi> to the <hi>Reuelation.</hi> You muſt be able readily to render an account what booke is next before or next after any ſuch booke taken in hand. Then returne back, and learne how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny chapters is in euerie booke.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="introduction">
               <head>2 <hi>Introduction.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>NOw you muſt go ouer theſe books old and new, by ſome proportion dayly, either morning or euening after this maner, wherein you ſhall ſee ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny profitable notes, and eſpecially the argument or ſumme of euerie booke; it will pleaſure you greatly, by the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port
<pb facs="tcp:19647:17"/> and iudgement of all antient au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thours.</p>
               <div type="argument">
                  <head>The Argument of Geneſis.</head>
                  <p>THis booke is called of the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brues <hi>Verescith,</hi> that is to ſay, <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, Generation,</hi> or <hi>Creation,</hi> gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing vs to vnderſtand, that it containes the <hi>creation</hi> of all things. <hi>Moſes</hi> the ſon of <hi>Amram</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Leui</hi> was borne 2430 yeares after the creation: when he was full 40 yeares old, he was called of God to be the leader of his people Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el; by a large meaſure of Gods ſpirit he ſpake of ſundrie things which were done 2414 yeares before he was borne, and alſo profoundly of manie other things that ſhould befall the people of Iſrael, euen vnto the birth of Chriſt. He wrote this booke neere about 850 yeares after the floud. At <hi>Ioſephs</hi> death it had a kind of ceaſing. This booke comprehends principally foure rhings.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1 <hi>Creation,</hi> by the word which was made fleſh.</item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:19647:17"/>
                     <item>2 <hi>Deſtruction,</hi> by the ouer-running of waters.</item>
                     <item>3 <hi>Multiplication</hi> of the world, by <hi>Noah.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>4 <hi>Election</hi> of ſome, as of <hi>Abraham, Iſaake, &amp;c.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </div>
               <div type="argument">
                  <head>The Argument of Exodus, the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond booke of Moſes.</head>
                  <p>IT is called of the Hebrues <hi>Shemoth,</hi> which is <hi>names,</hi> but of the Graecians &amp; later writers it is called <hi>Exodus,</hi> which ſignifieth a <hi>departing</hi> and <hi>going</hi> of Iſrael out of Aegypt: by co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>putation it amoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth neerly to a ſtorie of 405 yeres, from the death of <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> to the lifting vp of the tabernacle in <hi>Siloh;</hi> this booke com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehends principally three things.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1 The <hi>Deliuerance</hi> of Iſrael out of Aegypt.</item>
                     <item>2 Their <hi>Iourney</hi> towards Canaan.</item>
                     <item>3 An <hi>Order</hi> for the ſeruing of God.</item>
                  </list>
               </div>
               <div type="argument">
                  <head>The Argument of Leuiticus.</head>
                  <p>IT is called in Hebrue <hi>Vaicrah,</hi> but the Graecia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s &amp; later writers <hi>Leuiticus,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb facs="tcp:19647:18"/> it retaineth a memory of ſome no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table acts which were done fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the ſecond yere after the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſe from Aegypt, vnto the beginning of the eleuenth moneth of the 40 yeare, which is in ſome account thirty yeares: and partlie becauſe it debateth of cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies and ſuch like which were ended in their time.</p>
                  <list>
                     <head>This booke containes foure principall thinges.</head>
                     <item>1 Sundry ſorts of ofſrings concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Chriſt.</item>
                     <item>2 Ciuill orders for the practiſe of religion.</item>
                     <item>3 Ciuill orders concerning life and maners.</item>
                     <item>4 Diuerſe feaſts dedicated for reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</item>
                  </list>
               </div>
               <div type="argument">
                  <head>The Argument of Numbers.</head>
                  <p>THis booke is called of the Hebrues <hi>Vaied<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>bber,</hi> of the Latines <hi>Numeri,</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:19647:18" rendition="simple:additions"/> becauſe in the beginning of it <hi>Moſes</hi> numbred the people Iſrael by their tribes. It continueth the ſtorie from the beginning of the ſecond moneth of the ſecond yeare after the deliuerance of Iſrael out of Aegypt, vnto the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the eleuenth moneth of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teeth yeare of thirty eight yeares and odde.</p>
                  <list>
                     <head>It containeth foure things.</head>
                     <item>1 The muſtring of men, and orders for the preſeruation of the Arke.</item>
                     <item>2 Conſtitutions and lawes for reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</item>
                     <item>3 Conſtitutions and lawes for life and maners.</item>
                     <item>4 Particular lawes for reformation.</item>
                  </list>
               </div>
               <div type="argument">
                  <head>The Argument of Deutronomium.</head>
                  <p>THis booke is called in Hebrue <hi>Elle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haddebarim,</hi> in Greeke it is called <hi>Deut.</hi> ſignifying a Remembrance of things paſt, with an exhortation to the
<pb facs="tcp:19647:19" rendition="simple:additions"/> perfourmance of the law, from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the twelfth moneth of the fourteeth yeare, vnto the twelfth day of the ſame moneth, after their depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture from <hi>Pharaoes</hi> kingdome. This booke breefly repeats the greateſt mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters that were ſpoken and laid downe in the former bookes.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="argument">
                  <head>The Argument of Ioſhua.</head>
                  <p>HE was called Ieſus the Emperour of Iſrael; he ruled them victoriouſly ſeuenteene yeares, he was borne fiftie and three yeares before their going out of Aegypt, he died when he was one hundred and ten yeares old, 2570 of the world. <hi>He and Eleazar the high prieſt is thought to haue penned this booke.</hi> It approueth the performance of Gods promiſes, and that he neuer ſaileth by length of time, nor by diſtance of place, to remember his ellect: as is ſhewed vs by <hi>Ioſhua,</hi> who did conquer the land of Canaan, and deuided it among them, euen as the Lord had ſpoken. The land
<pb facs="tcp:19647:19"/> for the fertilitie thereof, farre beyond all other lands, did repreſent the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of <hi>heauen,</hi> and in regard of the power therof, it might well reſemble the kingdome of <hi>Antechriſt Ioſhua</hi> the <hi>conquerour</hi> was a figure of Ieſus, who ſubdued all things to himſelfe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="argument">
                  <head>The Argument of Iudges.</head>
                  <p>IT is called in Hebrue <hi>Sophetim,</hi> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Hebrue, Greeke, and La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine, it is called <hi>Iudicium,</hi> becauſe it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the <hi>gouernment</hi> and religion of Gods people, from the death of <hi>Ioſhua</hi> vnto <hi>Hely</hi> the prieſt, about 299 yeres: &amp; it is ſuppoſed that <hi>Samuel</hi> is the penner thereof: it ſheweth how God deteſteth <hi>ingratitude,</hi> by the great <hi>oppreſsions</hi> which was inflicted vpon the people for the ſame: they were of all people in the world moſt victoriouſly poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of all the ioyes in the world, and yet they were a people worſe than thoſe whoſe carcaſes fell in the wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: therefore God appointed ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants
<pb facs="tcp:19647:20"/> ouer them as their gouernours. Here is alſo a perfect preſident of <hi>par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> vpon <hi>repentance,</hi> for when they cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vnto the Lord, he deſtroyed thoſe tirants, and gaue them godly rulers.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="argument">
                  <head>The Argument of Ruth.</head>
                  <p>SHe is ſaid to liue when <hi>Deborah</hi> ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Iſrael, it is thought that the writer of <hi>Iudges</hi> is the author of this booke; becauſe that the Hebrues doe reckon it with the booke of <hi>Iudges:</hi> hir nation and kindred whence ſhe came doth well approue the calling of the Gentiles by Ieſus Chriſt, who was to come lineally euen from hir body. This booke doth arme all Chriſtians with <hi>patience,</hi> as with the whole armour of God, who in the end will get the fame and report of the world.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="argument">
                  <head>The Argument of the firſt and ſecond of Samuel.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">1. Chron. 29.29.</note>THe acts of <hi>Dauid,</hi> are they not written in the booke of <hi>Samuel</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:19647:20"/> the Seer, and in the booke of <hi>Nathan</hi> the prophet, and in the booke of <hi>Gad</hi> the Seer, by which wordes it is plaine, that <hi>Samuel, Nathan</hi> and <hi>Gad,</hi> did write theſe bookes.</p>
                  <p>In the firſt of <hi>Samuel</hi> is ſhewed the miſerie of the people vnder king <hi>Saul,</hi> which was a token of Gods wrath, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they were not content with their eſtate. <hi>Saul</hi> himſelfe is ſet foorth for an example of <hi>vnthankefulnes,</hi> he was ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of God, he was hated of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, &amp; he was poſſeſſed of a deuil. <hi>Dauid</hi> is made heire apparant to the crowne.</p>
                  <p>In the ſecond of <hi>Samuel,</hi> is declared the <hi>magnanimitie</hi> of <hi>Dauid,</hi> who ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came all the enemies of Gods people, wherin he was a figure of Chriſt.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="argument">
                  <head>The Argument of the firſt and ſecond of the kings.</head>
                  <p>BOth theſe are in the Hebrue as one. The Authours were theſe,<note place="margin">2. Chron. 19.29.</note> (ſeuerallie a part, or potion) <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>than,
<pb facs="tcp:19647:21"/> Ahiah</hi> the Silonite, <hi>Iddo</hi> the Seer <hi>Iohn,</hi> and <hi>Semeia.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The firſt Booke of <hi>Kings</hi> ſheweth vs the vncertaine ſtate of Gods people in this life, as by the example of the people vnder diuerſe kings, vnto the death of wicked <hi>Achab,</hi> who for a little ioy had great annoy; God alſo plagued them becauſe ſinne was fauoured, and vertue was diſcountenanced; their king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome was deuided into <hi>two parts,</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently vpon the death of <hi>Salamon,</hi> the one became open enimie to the other, for the ſpace of 350 yeares: one king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome was called the kingdome of <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah,</hi> whoſe ſeat was at Ieruſalem; the other was called the kingdome of <hi>Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el,</hi> whoſe ſeat was at <hi>Samaria:</hi> the one gaue themſelues to ſerue the true God; the other to idols. Here alſo is the perfect <hi>genealogie</hi> of Chriſt, lineally deſcending from <hi>Dauid.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The ſecond of <hi>Kings</hi> ſheweth vs of all famous acts, from <hi>Achab</hi> the king, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ranſacking of <hi>Samaria,</hi> the capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uating of the people, and <hi>Hoſea</hi> their laſt
<pb facs="tcp:19647:21"/> king; here is alſo the deſtruction of Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem, and the people carried to Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilon.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="argument">
                  <head>The Argument of the <hi>1</hi> and <hi>2</hi> of the Cronicles.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>PAralipomenon</hi> in Greeke. With the Hebrues both are one, it ſignifieth omitted, or things left; the Latines call it <hi>Verba Dierum,</hi> The words of daies; mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning a Catalogue of things done in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer ages: it was compoſed by <hi>Iddo,</hi> and <hi>Semeia.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1 <hi>Cron.</hi> comprehendeth briefly all that was excellently done from the <hi>cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation,</hi> vnto the reſtoring of the people from <hi>Babilon;</hi> it handleth exactly the <hi>genealogie</hi> of Chriſt.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 <hi>Cron.</hi> Comprehends chiefly all ſuch matters as were from the death of <hi>Salomon,</hi> vnto the captiuitie of <hi>Babi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon.</hi> Some things in theſe two books are more amplified than in the books of the <hi>Kings</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="argument">
                  <pb facs="tcp:19647:22"/>
                  <head>The Argument of Ezra.</head>
                  <p>HE was a prieſt, and towards the law, and the author of this booke. It containeth the deliuerance of Iſrael out of Babilon, with great fauour &amp; au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the king for the reedefying of the <hi>Temple</hi> at Ieruſalem; it was <hi>hinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red</hi> by the people of the land, yet it was <hi>finiſhed</hi> according to the time foretold by the angel to <hi>Daniel.</hi> This booke doth proue that God puniſheth not the godly according to iuſtice, but accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to mercie.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="argument">
                  <head>The argument of Nehemiah.</head>
                  <p>HE was cup-bearer to <hi>Artaxerxes,</hi> &amp; in ſuch credit, that he obtained in the twentith yeare of his raigne full au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority with licence &amp; letters, to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund to the finiſhing of the decaied places of Ieruſalem. This booke is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly called the 2 of <hi>Eſdras,</hi> becauſe he was thought to be the writer, and
<pb facs="tcp:19647:22"/> both were ioyned together the ſame time in the holy ſeruice of God. And in the Hebrue both books are one, both compriſe the ſtorie neare of 130 years, vnto the laſt <hi>Darius.</hi> There were three ſpecial men ſtirred vp by the Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, for the comfort of his people, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing long lain in exilement, the firſt was <hi>Zorobabel</hi> their captaine, the ſetter forward of <hi>chiualrie;</hi> the ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d was <hi>Ezra</hi> their prieſt, the ſetter forward of religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; &amp; the third was <hi>Nehemiah,</hi> the ſetter forward of their building. This booke ſets out many <hi>particulars,</hi> to weet, the builders, the manner of it, their hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derance, their religion, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>This booke containeth a ſingular fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour of God towards them that truſt for redemption by Chriſt, for that he openly writeth their names in his holy citie, that left Babel vpon <hi>Gabriels</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie, to build Ieruſalem the citie, for Chriſt the great king: and therefore the old Hebrues bound <hi>Ezra</hi> next <hi>Daniel,</hi> becauſe it dependeth all vpon <hi>Gabriels</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:19647:23"/> propheſie, <hi>Dan.</hi> 9. and all the nation ſtill thence talked of Chriſt to be their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="argument">
                  <head>The Argument of Eſther.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">2, 7.</note>SHe was named <hi>Hadaſſa,</hi> ſhe was maried to <hi>Darius</hi> the ſon of <hi>Hiſtaspis</hi> whoſe ſurname was <hi>Aſſuerus,</hi> vpon the diuorſe of queene <hi>Vaſthi:</hi> this booke was written by the chonicler of <hi>Aſſuerus,</hi> &amp; it was taken out of the records of the Medes and Perſians; <hi>Xerxes</hi> the great warrior was hir ſonne by the king, it is conſonant with the ſcriptures of God. Some hath added to the ſame ſix o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther chapters of <hi>Heſter,</hi> which are not ſound nor anſwerable to the reſt. This booke approueth the aſſurance of Gods mercies towards his elect, in time con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient, euen when all worldly helpes faileth, as by the example of <hi>Mardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheus</hi> and <hi>Heſter</hi> may appeare, who as inſtruments appointed of God, did de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer the Iewes from the decree and dedly ſentence of the king: moreouer
<pb facs="tcp:19647:23"/> it ſheweth that pride hath a fall, by the example of <hi>Haman.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="argument">
                  <head>The Argument of Iob.</head>
                  <p>THis ſtorie ſheweth the religion of <hi>Abrahams</hi> other kinred tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Iſraell, how before the law they held faith and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience, <hi>Abrahams</hi> kinred in the fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of <hi>Nahor,</hi> as <hi>Elihu</hi> was in <hi>Eſaus,</hi> as <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phas</hi> was in his own better line, as <hi>Bildad</hi> of his ſon <hi>Suach</hi> was (whom many latins, and all Greeks, commonly make to be of <hi>Abraham</hi> by <hi>Eſau,</hi> becauſe the land Vz, in <hi>Ier. Lament.</hi> is in Edom) this kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of hic <hi>Abraham,</hi> in theſe families held religion, and had theſe men pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, but prophets alwais had not viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for Gods particular dealings, though for naturall knowledge and rules of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue they be ſinceare. This booke in this argument, is moſt rare, containing a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, of fiue prophets, God in the end comming moderator. The ſhortnes of ſpeech, the deapth of matter, the diſcourſe of <hi>Iob</hi> for his life, of <hi>Elihu</hi> for
<pb facs="tcp:19647:24"/> naturall philoſophie, of the reſt for the common plaguing of the wicked, the thriſe holie concluſion of God makes that booke better than all ophir-gold. The ſtorie fell out about <hi>Moſes</hi> birth, 777 yeres after the deluge. <hi>Iob</hi> I hold to be of <hi>Abraham</hi> by <hi>Kettura,</hi> and the land Vz to be not that of <hi>Eſaus</hi> Vz, but of <hi>Nachors:</hi> whether <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſonnes by <hi>Kettura</hi> went to ſeeke dwelling with their eldeſt coſine of thoſe ſonnes of the eaſt. And thence ſo <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſons by <hi>Kettura</hi> be named. <hi>Moſes</hi> was dead before <hi>Iob,</hi> for he liued but 120 yeares, and <hi>Iob</hi> 140, after his temptation. <hi>Dina</hi> is ſaid to be <hi>Iobs</hi> wife, but by men that in ſadneſſe follow the ieſts of the Iews, who faigne for memorie of ſtorie, fables. <hi>Dina</hi> hath in ſcriptures no husband na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, nor <hi>Iob</hi> a wife with hir proper name, thereupon Iewes (for teaching children readineſſe in ſtorie) mary <hi>Dina</hi> (that might be <hi>Iobs</hi> gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dmother) to him; who followed them in ſadneſſe were decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued. Herein we are aſſured, vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent practiſe, and proofe of Gods eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall
<pb facs="tcp:19647:24"/> fauour, that when al deſolations and hazards whatſoeuer are neareſt, euen then is that man neareſt vnto God, and in the greateſt poſsibilitie of honor and maieſtie. Many great and excellent things are herein contained, therefore I recommend them vnto your chriſtian diligence.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="argument">
                  <head>The Argument of the Pſalms.</head>
                  <p>IT is called in Hebrue <hi>Sepher Tehilim,</hi> by the which the Graecians doe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe muſicall inſtruments. It was ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered by <hi>Eſdra.</hi> The authors were di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe, as the <hi>Pſalmes</hi> doe witneſſe, and ſome are vncertaine, yet the matter is ſound and good; <hi>Dauid</hi> was the chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt,<note place="margin">2. Sam. 23</note> and therefore he was called the ſweet Pſalmiſt of Iſrael: <hi>Moſes</hi> wrote the 90 and 91 as a fourme of praier; <hi>Ethan</hi> and <hi>Theman</hi> wrote the 88, and 89 who were men of great wiſdome;<note place="margin">1 Kin. 4, 30</note> the holy Prieſts and Leuits wrote the 137. <hi>Dauid</hi> ordeined wiſe and skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full men to make <hi>Pſalmes,</hi> and to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie
<pb facs="tcp:19647:25"/> with all ſorts of inſtruments, as <hi>Corah</hi> and his ſonnes, <hi>Aſaph</hi> and his ſonnes, <hi>Ieduthum</hi> and his ſonnes, <hi>Heman</hi> and his ſonnes there were ordained be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Arke of cunning muſitia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">2. Chro. 15, 16.25, 1.2. 2. <hi>Eſd.</hi> 12, 40.</note> 288; the inſtruments were theſe, <hi>Meginath, Mehiloth, Alamoth, Gittith, Ieduthum, Suſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>eduth, Soſainum, Salteries, Harpes, Organes, Trumpets, Cimballes, &amp;c.</hi> and the <hi>Pſalmes</hi> ſerue for diuerſe purpoſes, as you may eaſely ſee, if you marke them; ſome for muſicke, as you may know by then titles; ſome for prayers, ſome for thanksgiuing, ſome for conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, ſome for doctrine, ſome for pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie, and ſome for ſtorie.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="argument">
                  <head>The Argument of the Prouerbs, Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtes, Canticles.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">1. King 4.32.11.</note>
                     <hi>SAlomon</hi> was the writer of theſe three bookes, as appeares by their Titles, and maner of writing, after his conuerſion.</p>
                  <p>In the firſt, he teacheth all people the true <hi>wiſdome</hi> in the vſing of Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall
<pb facs="tcp:19647:25"/> things. In the ſecond he tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth a <hi>contempt</hi> of all earthly glorie, in regard of ioies in the Lord Ieſus. In the third, he ſets out the incomprehenſible fauor of God towards all ſuch, by their marriage in Chriſt, repreſenting a ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall and an inſeperable coniunction, vnder metaphors, ſimilitudes, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſons.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="argument">
                  <head>The Argument of Eſaie.</head>
                  <p>HE was <hi>Amos</hi> ſonne, taken of manie for an Euangeliſt, he ſpake and taught vnder <hi>Vziah, Ioatham, Ahaz, Ezechia,</hi> and <hi>Manaſſes.</hi> This booke was written by him a little before his death: it contains the doctrine of reconciliati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on more clearely than the reſt. It is full of reprehenſions and conſolations; the comming of the Meſsiah is prooued, and the vniting of the Iewes and Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="argument">
                  <pb facs="tcp:19647:26"/>
                  <head>The Argument of Ieremie.</head>
                  <p>HE was ſonne to <hi>Helchia</hi> the Prieſt, he wrot this booke and propheſied vnder <hi>Ioſias Ioiachim,</hi> and <hi>Zedechia,</hi> at that time as Hieruſalem was ranſac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, and the people captiuated, whome <hi>Ieremie</hi> lamenteth. <hi>Baruck</hi> was his ſecre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarie. This booke ſhewes the captiuitie of Hieruſalem and hir people, for hir manifold ſinnes.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="argument">
                  <head>The Argument of Ezechiel.</head>
                  <p>HE was a prieſt in Babylon, fiue yeres of <hi>Ichoiachims</hi> captiuity. This booke doth ſhew the murmuring of the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked againſt the Prophets, becauſe they yeelded to <hi>Nabuchadnezar.</hi> Therefore in the firſt part of this booke he labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth to confirme his former doctrine, that they did well in yeelding, for it was decreed by the mouth of God, that they ſhould be captiuated, then he la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boureth with doctrine to aſſure them
<pb facs="tcp:19647:26"/> of deliuerance againe, from this their ſeruitude and captiuitie.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="argument">
                  <head>The Argument of Daniel.</head>
                  <p>HE was in Babilon with <hi>Ananias, Miſael,</hi> &amp; <hi>Azarius,</hi> in <hi>Iehoiachims</hi> time, and he thus propheſied vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>Nabuchadnezer, Euilmeredec,</hi> &amp; <hi>Baltazar.</hi> In this book is ſhewed what hapned to their king and the people, during the 70 yeares captiuitie; what kings raigned, how the people were v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, what ſhould be happen them after their captiuitie vntill Chriſt.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="argument">
                  <head>The Argument of Hoſea.</head>
                  <p>IN the daies of <hi>Oſiah, Ioathan, Ahas,</hi> &amp; <hi>Ezechias,</hi> kings of Iudah, he wrote and prpheſied. This booke ſhewes the Idolatrie of the people vnder <hi>Iero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boam,</hi> and their ſins by many particulars. This prophet was amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g them 70 yeres, and they deſpiſed him and others.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="argument">
                  <pb facs="tcp:19647:27"/>
                  <head>The Argument of Ioel.</head>
                  <p>HE propheſied in the daies of <hi>Oſia,</hi> and <hi>Ieroboam,</hi> concerning <hi>Samaria,</hi> and wrote the ſame. Herin is ſhewed the famine and extreame miſery that they of Iudah endured, becauſe of their ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrie and obſtinacie.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="argument">
                  <head>The Argument of Amos.</head>
                  <p>IN the daies of <hi>Oſiah</hi> and <hi>Ieroboam,</hi> he wrote this, he was a poore and a ſimple ſhepheard, ſtirred vp of ſpeciall purpoſe to ſet foorth Gods glorie, by calling the people to repent.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="argument">
                  <head>The Argument of Obadiah.</head>
                  <p>HE ſpake againſt Edom, at which time the pallace of the temple and the citie was ſet on fire, this booke ſhewes how the <hi>Idumeans</hi> vexed Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el moſt cruelly, and continually: in the higheſt pitch of their pride, God ſends
<pb facs="tcp:19647:27"/> this <hi>Obadiah</hi> to denounce his vengeance againſt them, and good ſucceſſe vpon his owne inheritance.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="argument">
                  <head>The Argument of Ionah.</head>
                  <p>HE ſpake vnder <hi>Amaziah</hi> and <hi>Ierobo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am,</hi> he controled <hi>Phulbelocus</hi> of Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuie, who ſucceeded <hi>Sardanapalus.</hi> This booke ſheweth how little his preaching auailed in Iſrael; and how much few words preuailed in Niniuie, to the ſhame of all Iſraell: here is the diſtruction firſt of the kingdome of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael, then of Iudah, chiefly becauſe they contemned the prophets.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="argument">
                  <head>The Argument of Nahum.</head>
                  <p>HE propheſied vnder <hi>Ezechia</hi> king of Iudah, <hi>Hoſea</hi> king of Iſrael, and <hi>Salmanazer</hi> king of the Aſsyrians, This booke ſhewes the reuolting of Niniuie, from the true profeſsion which they had taken from <hi>Ionah;</hi> they became per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuters of all that profeſſed godlineſſe,
<pb facs="tcp:19647:28"/> therefore their citie was deſtroied by <hi>Nabucadnezer,</hi> among whom there was ſome godly, whom God remembreth with his comforts, ſent by the prophets.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="argument">
                  <head>The Argument of Abacuk.</head>
                  <p>HE wrote this booke about the ſame time, and he lamenteth the deſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the godly, and the proſperitie of the wicked, who in the end ſhould be captiuated by the Chaldeans.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="argument">
                  <head>The Argument of Sophoniah.</head>
                  <p>HE propheſied in the daies of <hi>Ioſiah,</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Ammon,</hi> king of Iudah, The Moabits, the Aſsirians, and others, who were enemies to Gods people, ſhall come themſelues to confuſion, but the godly by patience ſhall poſſeſſe their ſoules.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="argument">
                  <head>The Argument of Agge.</head>
                  <p>THis prophet, <hi>Zacharie,</hi> and <hi>Malachie,</hi> were eſpecially appointed after the
<pb facs="tcp:19647:28"/> captiuitie to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort the people, &amp; to ſet them forward to the building of the temple at Ieruſalem, which was a ſight of the ſpirituall Ieruſalem. This prophet ſhewes the cauſe of their captiuitie, and exhorteth to repentance.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="argument">
                  <head>The Argument of Zacharie.</head>
                  <p>THis prophet wrote the ſecond yeare of <hi>Darius,</hi> in the eight moneth, the ſame matter.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="argument">
                  <head>The Argument of Malachie.</head>
                  <p>THis prophet was the laſt and the next to <hi>Iohn</hi> Babtiſt. He ſpake of the captiuitie, of the building of <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons</hi> temple, and the ſtorie of <hi>Eſdras,</hi> and <hi>Nehemias;</hi> he reproues diuerſe ſinnes, and ſpeaks as the two former.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="argument">
                  <head>The Argument of Mathew.</head>
                  <p>HE wrote this Goſpell in Hebrue, eight yeares after the aſcention of
<pb facs="tcp:19647:29"/> Chriſt. All the foure Euangeliſts did write in efect one thing, they al entitled their writing <hi>Goſpell,</hi> ſignifiing, Good ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings or newes from heauen; compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hending the incarnation, death, reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and aſcention of Chriſt, being the abſolute ſumme of our redemption, and adoption to eternall glorie. This Title comprehends all the matter ſhadowed in the law, and perfourmed in the goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell: whatſoeuer one writes darkly, the other more largely and plainly. They varie not in any one thing, though their writing be farre in diſtance, for time and place, which greatly argueth and aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menteth the trueth and dignitie there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. They entreat in ſome matters more exactly than in other; <hi>Mathew</hi> laboreth to ſetfoorth an hiſtoricall narration of Chriſts body, to weet, of his incarnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, his kinred, how he was occupied in the time of his life, teaching and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king miracles to confirme the will of his father; he ſpake of his death, and reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, with ſuch circumſtances as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long thereunto.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="argument">
                  <pb facs="tcp:19647:29"/>
                  <head>The Argument of Marke.</head>
                  <p>HE was the diſciple and interpreter of <hi>Peter.</hi> Vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> earneſt requeſt made to him <hi>at Roome,</hi> he wrote this goſpell in Greeke, ten yeares after the Aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Chriſt. He planted the faith at Alexandria, where he died.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="argument">
                  <head>The Argument of Luke.</head>
                  <p>HE was a phiſition at <hi>Antioch,</hi> the follower of S. <hi>Paule,</hi> who did write this goſpell 15 <hi>yeares</hi> after Chriſts aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, he died at Conſtantinople. This book moſt chiefly ſpecifieth of ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies which were performed in Chriſt.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="argument">
                  <head>The Argument of Iohn.</head>
                  <p>HE was ſonne to <hi>Zebedeus</hi> the brother of <hi>Iames,</hi> whom <hi>Herod</hi> be headded, at the requeſt of ſome Biſhops in <hi>Aſia.</hi> He chiefly handleth Chriſts diuinitie, and wonderfull worke of our reconcili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation.
<pb facs="tcp:19647:30"/> He wrote this goſpell 32 yeares after Chriſts aſcention, he died and was buried amongſt the Epheſians.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="argument">
                  <head>The Argument of the Acts.</head>
                  <p>THe ſame was written in Greeke by S <hi>Luke,</hi> at Rome, and dedicated to one <hi>Theophilus.</hi> This booke is an abridgment or a chronicle of all famous &amp; worthy acts of Chriſt, of his diſciples and Apoſtles: herein is annexed the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons of the Apoſtles, touching faith &amp; maners, the open perſecution of the truth, &amp; the victorie thereof in the end.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="argument">
                  <head>The Argument of the Romanes.</head>
                  <p>THe Romanes were Iews and Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, embracing Chriſt in Rome, among whom were many falſe teachers which moued S. <hi>Paule</hi> to write this E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle, by his ſecretarie <hi>Tertius,</hi> exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them to take heed therof, and to encreaſe in the knowledge of Chriſt. The dignitie of works, of faith, of grace,
<pb facs="tcp:19647:30"/> and iuſtification of the law, and the vſe thereof, from Corinth,<note place="margin">Acts 20. Rom. 16.</note> ſome few daies before he went to Ieruſalem.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="argument">
                  <head>The Argument of the firſt to the Corinthians.</head>
                  <p>THe Corinthians had their originall of <hi>Corinthus,</hi> who built that citie; in it was the temple dedicated to the Goddeſſe <hi>Venus.</hi> There was that great notorius whore <hi>Lais,</hi> ſpoken of ouer all the world, and there was many other abhominatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, yet in this city God had his church. S. <hi>Paule</hi> ſtaied there almoſt three yeares, but when he departed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Siria,</hi> manie falſe teachers entred in, who taught that whoredome, riot, drunkenneſſe, &amp;c. was lawfull, they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied marriage, and the reſurrection; vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which occaſion, S. <hi>Paule</hi> wrote this Epiſtle, to withdraw them from all thoſe euils,<note place="margin">Act. 19. 1 Cor. 16.</note> and with exhortations to remaine in the doctrine which he had taught. From Epheſus. 4</p>
               </div>
               <div type="argument">
                  <pb facs="tcp:19647:31"/>
                  <head>The Argument of the ſecond to the Corinthians</head>
                  <p>HEre he excuſeth his long abſence, by diuerſe troubles which hindered him, he willeth to exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municate him that was taken in adulterie; he cleareth himſelfe of all blame towards them,<note place="margin">Acts 20.</note> he ſheweth a difference betwixt one ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite and another, the agreement of the old teſtament with the new. From <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lippi.</hi> 6</p>
               </div>
               <div type="argument">
                  <head>The Argument of the Gallathians.</head>
                  <p>THe Gallathians were a people of <hi>Aſia:</hi> after S. <hi>Paules</hi> departure thence, many falſe teachers entred in and taught, That the ceremonies of the law were to be kept, and they taught e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill things againſt the Apoſtles, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to deface their doctrine; which mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued him to write vnto them, diſchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging himſelfe for the credit of his cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and confirming of his doctrine,
<pb facs="tcp:19647:31"/> with the ouerthrow of the contrarie. From Rome. 13</p>
               </div>
               <div type="argument">
                  <head>The Argument of the Epheſians.</head>
                  <p>THis citie of Epheſus was famous by the ſea ſide of Ionius, where was a temple dedicated to the falſe God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſſe <hi>Diana.</hi> S. <hi>Paule</hi> at his firſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming ſtaied little there, but at the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond time he continued three yeares, perceauing that God had many ſoules there to be ſaued, euen among witches, ſorcerers, &amp;c. whereby the mercie of God appeared more aboundantly: at his departure he left among them elders, and <hi>Timothie</hi> as their Biſhop. This Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument agreeth neerly with the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes and Gallathians. Sent from Rome. 11.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="argument">
                  <head>The Argument of the Philippians.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>PHilip Macedon</hi> was the originall of the citie, they had domeſticall trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, and many loſt for the trueths
<pb facs="tcp:19647:32"/> ſake, and therefore he exhorteth them to patience and watchfulneſſe. Sent from Rome. 8.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="argument">
                  <head>The Argument of the Coloſsians.</head>
                  <p>THe Coloſſians were a people of that great citie <hi>Colloſſa,</hi> S. Paule was neuer with them, they were taught by <hi>Epaphras, Oneſimus,</hi> &amp; <hi>Tychi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus,</hi> S. <hi>Paule</hi> heard that they were troubled with the Iewes, about cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, and with the gentils about ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till queſtions and wordes of philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phie, wherefore he wrote vnto them to confirme them in that they had lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned concerning Chriſt, and to confute the contrarie. Sent from Roome. 9</p>
               </div>
               <div type="argument">
                  <head>The Argument of the firſt to the Theſsalonians.</head>
                  <p>THeſſalonica was a famous citie of Macedonia, whence the people had their names, he was among them, but three Sabaoths, by reaſon of the
<pb facs="tcp:19647:32"/> Iews. He ſent <hi>Timothie</hi> vnto them, by whom he vnderſtood of their conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and that they ſhould conſider well of the reſurrection.<note place="margin">Acts 17,</note> He ſent it from Athens.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="argument">
                  <head>The Argument of the ſecond to the Theſsalonians.</head>
                  <p>HE excuſeth his long abſence, ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them the manner of the reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and the comming of Chriſt, he dehorteth from curious queſtions. Sent from Athens. 2</p>
               </div>
               <div type="argument">
                  <head>The Argument of the firſt to Timothie.</head>
                  <p>HIs father was a Graecian, his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a Iew, which was the cauſe he was not circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ciſed in his infancie, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the law. His mother <hi>Eunice,</hi> and his grandmother <hi>Loida,</hi> were godly, wherein they brought him vp. S. <hi>Paule</hi> his maiſter ſent him on the Lords bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſines, to diuerſe places: in the end he
<pb facs="tcp:19647:33"/> was left at Epheſus as their biſhop, to whom he wrote this Epiſtle, about the choiſe of Paſtours in the church. At Laodicea. 3</p>
               </div>
               <div type="argument">
                  <head>The Argument of the ſecond to Timothie.</head>
                  <p>HE mourned greatly after S. <hi>Paule,</hi> therefore <hi>Paule</hi> did write to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort him, and withall to ſhew him how he was held in priſon, which was the cauſe that he came not to Epheſus according to his promiſe. Sent from Rome. 12</p>
               </div>
               <div type="argument">
                  <head>The Argument of Titus.</head>
                  <p>HE was a Graecian borne, <hi>Paule</hi> was his maiſter, who left him at Creete to conſtitute miniſters in euerie pariſh, and to refourme their manners, <hi>Titus</hi> was a yong man, therefore his maiſter wrote this Epiſtle that he ſhould do no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing raſhlie. What kinde of Paſtours ſhould be allowed and what not, From Nicapolis in Macedonia.<note place="margin">Acts 20.</note> 5</p>
               </div>
               <div type="argument">
                  <pb facs="tcp:19647:33"/>
                  <head>The Argument of Philemon.</head>
                  <p>HE was <hi>Collocentia,</hi> a rich man, and a godly liberall man, he had a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant named <hi>Oneſimus,</hi> who departed from him by ſtealth: when he heard S. <hi>Paule</hi> preach, he beleeued in Ieſus Chriſt and confeſſed his fault, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon S. <hi>Paule</hi> wrote this Epiſtle to his maiſter, exhorting him to forgiue his ſeruant. Sent from Rome. 10</p>
               </div>
               <div type="argument">
                  <head>The Argument of the Hebrues.</head>
                  <p>THe truth is by the opinion of the moſt and beſt learned, that S. <hi>Paule</hi> wrote this Epiſtle, the Grecians did ſo allow of it, and the ſame was confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in the councell of Nicen. <hi>Nicepho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus</hi> ſaith that it was written in Hebrue by S. <hi>Paule,</hi> and tranſlated into Greeke by S. <hi>Luke,</hi> who altered S. <hi>Pauls</hi> ſtile and method of writing. <hi>Iraeneus</hi> who was <hi>Policarpus</hi> ſcholler, ſaid the ſame; the trueth being receiued from S. <hi>Iohn,</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:19647:34"/> who was <hi>Policarpus</hi> maiſter; ſuch was the obſtinacie of the Iewes, reſiſting the doctrine of Chriſt, which gaue oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to S. <hi>Paule</hi> to write, exhorting them from the hardnes of their hearts. Herein he magnifieth Chriſt aboue the prophets, <hi>Moſes,</hi> and <hi>Aaron, Leui,</hi> and all other offices, and officers; who fulfilled the propheſies, accomplſhed the law, and offred a farre more perfect ſacrifice than they all. Sent by <hi>Timothie</hi> from Italie.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="argument">
                  <head>The Argument of Iames.</head>
                  <p>IN the tenth of <hi>Mathew</hi> mention is made of two <hi>Iames,</hi> one the ſonne of <hi>Zebedeus,</hi> the other the ſonne of <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheus,</hi> which <hi>Iames</hi> was the Author of this Epiſtle, he is called <hi>Lebbeus</hi> and <hi>Thaddeus,</hi> and he is called the brother of <hi>Iude,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Gal. 1, 19.</note> and the brother of our Lord. Here he inſtructeth al men to liue wel, and to beleeue well, he ſets out the conuerſation of thoſe that are regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated:
<pb facs="tcp:19647:34"/> the excellencie of faith, of works, of patience, &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="argument">
                  <head>The Argument of the firſt of Peter.</head>
                  <p>THis <hi>Peter</hi> was called <hi>Simeon</hi> the ſon of <hi>Iohn</hi> the fiſher, Chriſt did name him <hi>Caephas,</hi> which is <hi>Peter,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Marke 3.</note> he was one of the Apoſtles, and the chiefeſt for diuerſe cauſes. He ſpake of works after iuſtification, as S. <hi>Iames</hi> doth: he deſcendeth into the dueties of each degree, and to the conuerſation of the Gentils. It was written vpon the occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of <hi>Siluanus,</hi> being long with <hi>S. Paule,</hi> and trauelling to Babilon, met with S. <hi>Peter,</hi> who deliuered him this Epiſtle generall.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="argument">
                  <head>The Argument of the ſecond of Peter.</head>
                  <p>HE exhorteth all men from day to day, and from degree to degree, to increaſe in the works of regeneration, to beware of falſe teachers, the ſtate of the laſt times. He thought his death to
<pb facs="tcp:19647:35"/> be at hand, wherefore he wrote to the glorie of his maiſter Chriſt.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="argument">
                  <head>The Argument of the firſt of Iohn.</head>
                  <p>THis <hi>Iohn</hi> was one of the foure Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſts, he was the ſonne of <hi>Zebedeus</hi> beloued of Chriſt, he wrote the <hi>Reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> he exhorteth to faith &amp; brother<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly loue, to trie and approue the ſpirits, to auoid falſe teachers, hypociſie, and ſmall offences, and to decke them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues with godly liuing.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="argument">
                  <head>The Argument of the ſecond of Iohn.</head>
                  <p>HEre he handleth mutuall loue, the duetie of widowes, to beware of falſe teachers, &amp; a way to know them: he did write eſpecially to a godly wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, who with hir children and hir houſhold laboured after Chriſt.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="argument">
                  <pb facs="tcp:19647:35"/>
                  <head>The Argument of the third of Iohn.</head>
                  <p>HE exhorteth his familiar friends, and his hoſt <hi>Gains</hi> to diuerſe points of doctrine, and to good works, than<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king God for the great comfort recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued at his hands, he commends him for a harberour of Gods people.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="argument">
                  <head>The Argument of Iude.</head>
                  <p>HE was one of the Apoſtles, he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed the Godly to continue in well doing, he ſhewes the iuſtice of God againſt ſinners and reuolters, as the Angels, the Iewes.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="argument">
                  <head>The Argument of the Reuelation.</head>
                  <p>THis booke containeth all the doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine of the prophets, concerning Chriſt, which was to be accompliſhed after his comming, the comfort that comes by his death, the marriage of the church with the ſanctified mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers,
<pb facs="tcp:19647:36"/> the prouidence of God, and the force of his word,</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="introduction">
               <head>The third Introduction.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hat may be ſaid of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther books called <hi>Apocry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pha,</hi> you may eaſely iudge by the conſideration of the authours, and eſpecially by the matter, not conſonant with other ſcriptures. The word <hi>Apocrypha</hi> according to the Aetymologie thereof, ſignifieth a myſterie, a matter hid, ſecreat, or kept cloſe. They are books to be read at home, and not in the congregation.</p>
               <div type="argument">
                  <head>The firſt and ſecond of Eſdras.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">1 <hi>Eſd.</hi> 7, 6. 2 <hi>Eſd.</hi> 8, 4.5.6.</note>THis <hi>Eſdras</hi> was a Scribe and an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounder of the law: when the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple went from Babilon vnder the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment of <hi>Zarobabell,</hi> in the time of <hi>Cirus,</hi> and <hi>Darius, Hiſtaſpis</hi> ſonne, he was in great report, and bare credite a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong all people. Concerning the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie
<pb facs="tcp:19647:36"/> of theſe books, the matter it ſelfe hath no certaine ground, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, That in the firſt of <hi>Eſd.</hi> the third and fourth, of the three yong mens ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences. In the firſt of <hi>Eſdras</hi> the 4, and 1. the Angell reproued <hi>Eſdras</hi> for his curious ſearching, he was purpoſed to ſorow, and faſt him ſelfe to death,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Eſd.</hi> 10, 4.</note> both which things argued an vnper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect ſpirite in him. This and the reſt, proues the books not fit to be matched with the Canonicall, whoſe ſpirite was neuer found guiltie of controlment.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="argument">
                  <head>Tobias.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Tobias</hi> liued in the daies of <hi>Salman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer,</hi> and <hi>Zenacherib</hi> his ſonne, kings of Aſsiria, and was taken captiue at Nini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie. This booke was penned by ſome godly man not perfectly knowne, it was found in the Hebrue, Aſsyrian, and Chaldean tongues, very antient, yet with many blemiſhes, and imperfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions. In the twelfth and fifteenth it is ſaid, That the Angels did preſent the
<pb facs="tcp:19647:37"/> praiers of the ſaints; which none can do but Ieſus Chriſt himſelfe, for he is our Aduocate, and high ſacrificer. In the 4 and 10 old <hi>Tobias</hi> ſaith, that Alms deliuered a man from death; which is a matter contrarie to all holy ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. In the ſeuenteenth he exhorteth to giue bread for the dead; which in deed is a ſhew of Idolatrie, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the man is to be taken for god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and religious, and his booke ſo far to be taken for credit, as it doth agree with the Canonicall.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="argument">
                  <head>Iudith.</head>
                  <p>THis booke ſeemeth toward the laſt part to haue been penned after hir death; by whome, it is vncertaine: the ſtorie is in the Hebrue and Chaldean tongues, yet not ſo receiued as the Canonicall, becauſe of the ſundrie im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfections thereof.<note place="margin">Cap. 11, 6.16 8.1.11, 1.</note> She tooke Gods name in vaine, ſhe denied the power of God and the authoritie of his Saints, yeelding all to <hi>Holophernes. Nabu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cadnezer</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:19647:37"/> was Emperour of Perſia, and his ſeat was at Babilon, but not in Nini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie, as is here laid downe. For theſe and ſuch like, this booke cannot be allowed for ſound, yet many good things are therein, therefore iudge ſoberlie and charitably.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="argument">
                  <head>Heſter.</head>
                  <p>THis booke was written by ſome Graecian not truely knowne, it is very friuolous, &amp; it is annexed vnto the true ſtory of <hi>Heſter,</hi> the variety thereof ſhewes the contrariety.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="argument">
                  <head>Wiſdome.</head>
                  <p>IT is called in Greeke <hi>Panare<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>on,</hi> that is to ſay, The booke of all vertues; <hi>Ierome</hi> writeth that <hi>Philoiudeus</hi> enlar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged it with great wiſdome and learning into Greeke, being left before as a remnant or peece by <hi>Solomon:</hi> this <hi>Philoiudeus</hi> liued in the daies of the Apoſtles, and he embraced chriſtian faith. We muſt graunt that there
<pb facs="tcp:19647:38"/> are many excellent things done and ſpoken herein, the author being elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent and learned, but yet euerie lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and eloquent booke may not be admitted among the ſaints.</p>
                  <p>Read <hi>Aug. de doct. Chriſt. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>De ciuitat. dei, lib.</hi> 17, 20. <hi>Iunius</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face in <hi>Apocrypha.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="argument">
                  <head>Baruck.</head>
                  <p>HE was ſecretarie to <hi>Hieremie.</hi> This booke is not in the Hebrue, but in the Greeke, therefore it was not recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned among the Iſraelits, who were of that language. It is not reckoned in the chronicles of the kings of Iudah, nor yet accounted among the prophets.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="argument">
                  <head>Suſanna.</head>
                  <p>IT is not knowne who did write this booke. Although hir chaſtitie be commended, yet the matter is not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued, northe author canonized.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="argument">
                  <pb facs="tcp:19647:38"/>
                  <head>Bell and the Dragon.</head>
                  <p>THe author is not to be found, and the matter is not likely.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="argument">
                  <head>The praier of Manaſses.</head>
                  <p>HE is the author thereof, as it is gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally receiued. It was in Greeke, which did diſanull the authoritie thereof among the Hebrues.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="argument">
                  <head>The firſt and ſecond of Machabees.</head>
                  <p>THe firſt was written in Hebrue, in the time of <hi>Iohannes Hircanus,</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Simon Machabeus.</hi> It was recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued as a ſtorie: but not of credit, to be with the books of God.</p>
                  <p>The ſecond was in Greeke, very fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uolous and out of order.</p>
                  <p>The third was entituled <hi>Simon</hi> the high prieſt, penned (by all likelihood) by <hi>Philoiudeus,</hi> at Alexandria, in Greek. Mark their authority, <hi>Iudas Machabeus</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:19647:39"/> offered for the dead, and praied for them, that their ſinnes might be par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned; which thing is againſt all ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.<note place="margin">12, 42. &amp;c.</note> The ſin which he praied for, was mortall, and not veniall, (as they ſay who would haue this booke to be cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicall) yet they pray and ſacrifice for them.<note place="margin">2 Mach. 2, 5.</note> It is ſaid that <hi>Ieremie</hi> hid the Arke of the Tabernacle in a caue, and that <hi>Salomon</hi> ſanctified the place;<note place="margin">2 Mach. 8, 9.10.</note> which thing <hi>Salomon</hi> could not doe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it was no part of his office, and he neuer did it: the ſame prophet did euen then reproue the ſeekers after ſuch pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, leaſt there ſhold be any monument or relick of Idolatrie: further, the death of <hi>Antiochus</hi> is not agreed vpon, for in 1 <hi>Mach.</hi> 6, 5.6, 16. it is ſaid, That he di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with ſorrow; in the 2. <hi>Mach.</hi> 9, 6.7. the maner of his death is reckoned to be far otherwiſe. It is ſaid that <hi>Iudas Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chabeus</hi> was ſlaine in <hi>Demetrius</hi> armie, 1 <hi>Mach.</hi> 9, 18. but in the 2 <hi>Mach.</hi> 1, 10.11. he writeth a letter after his death 36 yeares vnto <hi>Ariſtobolus,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2 Mach. 1.10.11.</note> he doubteth of his well doing. Let the feare of God
<pb facs="tcp:19647:39"/> withdraw you from all vnreuerent handling and iudging hereof.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="introduction">
               <head>The fourth Introduction.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Argument or ſum of all the Bible by books and chapters, as they ly, comprehendeth ten hiſtories or generall matters, chaining the ſcriptures to the ſaluation of one people, in the ſeruice of God, and to the deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of an another, wilfullie nelegcting and obſtinatly gainſaying the ſame: whereby you ſhall ſee, as it were it one view, what was moſt notably done and ſpoken in euerie age, what difference and change there was, and vpon what occaſion: you ſhall not light into any one booke or chapter, but hereby you ſhal be able to ſay, This or that matter belongeth to ſuch a ſtorie; This is the effect of euery booke &amp; chapter; Here
<pb facs="tcp:19647:40"/> this or that beginneth, and there it en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth. I haue ſet before the particular matter of euerie ſtorie ſeuerally, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the age and continuance there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, which being once perfectly learned, ſhall euer be remembred, with the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of knowledge, and with an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable change in your ſelfe, to your comfort, and to Gods glorie.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:19647:40"/>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <row>
                        <cell role="label">
                           <hi>Storie.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="label" cols="4">
                           <hi>Bookes and Chapters.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="label">
                           <hi>Contents.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell rows="12">From</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Gen.</hi> 1,</cell>
                        <cell rows="7">To</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Gen.</hi> 7,</cell>
                        <cell> The Flood. 1656. years.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>2</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Gen.</hi> 8,</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Gen.</hi> 12,</cell>
                        <cell> The renouation of the creation. 424. yea.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Gen.</hi> 12,</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Exod.</hi> 19,</cell>
                        <cell> The election in Abram and his ſeed. 430. yea.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>4</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Exod.</hi> 12.</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Ioſ.</hi> 1,</cell>
                        <cell> Their going out of Aegypt to Canaan. 40. yea.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>5</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Ioſ.</hi> 1,</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Iudg.</hi> 1.</cell>
                        <cell> Their quiet poſſeſſion in the ſame. 7. yea.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>6</cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Iudg.</hi> 1,</cell>
                        <cell>1. <hi>Samuel.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell> Of Saul their firſt king. 450. yea.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>7</cell>
                        <cell>1. <hi>Sam.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Nehem.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell> Their captiuitie in Babylon. 490. yea.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell rows="3">8</cell>
                        <cell cols="3">
                           <hi>Nehem.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell rows="3"> Their reſtoring to libertie. 70. yea.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell cols="3">
                           <hi>Ezra.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell cols="3">
                           <hi>Hester.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>9</cell>
                        <cell cols="3">
                           <hi>Danie.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell> Their perpetuall libertie in Chriſt. 490. ye.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>10</cell>
                        <cell cols="3">
                           <hi>Reuel.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell> The birth of Chriſt, to the worlds end, by the computation of <hi>Elias,</hi> 2000. ye.</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:19647:41"/>
               <p>NOw you muſt learne what euerie ſtorie doth generally containe, what is the ſum or whole drift of the holy Ghoſt in the ſame, which I haue ſet downe by particulars. You muſt marke where and in what booke or chapter the ſubſtance of euerie ſtorie lieth, and how it is diſpearſed in the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; moſt principally note two things, to weet, what good men was in euerie age, or in euerie ſuch ſtorie, and what wicked men.</p>
               <div type="exegesis">
                  <head>The particulars of the firſt ſtorie.</head>
                  <p>
                     <table>
                        <row>
                           <cell rows="10">Fathers. <note place="margin">Gen. 5.</note>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Adam.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell rows="10">Signifieth</cell>
                           <cell>Earthly.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Seth.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>Setled.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Enos.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>Sorrowfull.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Kenan.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>Godly repentance.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Mahalalel.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>Praiſe God.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Jared.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>The lowly.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Henoch.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>The Sabaoth keeper.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Methuſelah.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>Long life.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Lamech.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>Heart wounded.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Noah.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>The Comforter.</cell>
                        </row>
                     </table>
                  </p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19647:41"/>
                  <p>Theſe were the tenne holy fathers before the floud, which the holy ghoſt reckoneth, in whom the religion and ſeruice of God was grounded; theſe publiſhed ouer the world, that the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was, all ſuch effectuall matters tending to religion, as was deliuered afterward to <hi>Moſes</hi> in two tables of ſtone, to be continued and enlarged by ſacraments and ſacrifices, by ceremonies, and ſuch like ordinances, euen vnto the death of Chriſt: there was nothing done in the time of <hi>Moſes,</hi> which might not wel be deriued from the law and profeſsion of theſe men, if you compare them by their ſpecial inſtances; &amp; by them you ſhal finde true religion maintained, and the falſe detected, moreouer by them hard places are made plaine. And if you reckon how long euerie of them liued, the whole doth perfectly mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure the age of that world, from <hi>Adam</hi> to the floud, 1656. And for theſe ſpecial cauſes I haue laid downe brief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly their ſtories.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19647:42"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>ADam</hi> was a paſsing and a moſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect creature, diſagreeing from all other creatures, both in the magnani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie of his ſoule, and in the excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of his bodie; in ſoule he was like to God himſelfe, for wiſdome, for inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cencie, and clearenes; in bodie he did beare the fourme and faſhion of the goodlieſt male and female kinde that was to be in the world. He comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, by the light of Gods ſpirite, that the ſeede of the woman ſhould reſtore him and all beleeuers into the fauor of God, and therefore he called his wife <hi>Heua,</hi> that is to ſay, Life; and he called his ſonne <hi>Seth,</hi> that is to ſay, Setled, and perſuaded in the faith of Chriſt. In the commemoration of which ſeed, <hi>Adam</hi> offered continuall ſacrifice, the which in the allowance thereof was or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarilie conſumed by fire, as was the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice of <hi>Abraham</hi> in the time of the law. By this he may well be called a king, a prophet, a prieſt or ſacrificer. As the original whence he came being earth, had relation to what he ſhould
<pb facs="tcp:19647:42"/> returne; ſo the place where he was created, being mount Moriah, had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to that place where Chriſt the high ſacrificer ſhould be crucified, to the ioy of the world; as by many other particulars afterwards, was made plaine to be Ieruſalem,<note place="margin">Gen. 22, 2.</note> where <hi>Iſaac</hi> was offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red as a figure of Chriſt; where <hi>Sem</hi> or <hi>Melchiſedech</hi> dwelt, being the king of peace and iuſtice;<note place="margin">14, 18.</note> where <hi>Noahs</hi> arke re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted;<note place="margin">Gen. 8.</note> where <hi>Salomon</hi> was commanded to build the temple in the honour of his name.<note place="margin">2 Cron. 3, 1.</note> When God had chaſtned the woman, and curſed the ſerpent, he ſaid vnto <hi>Adam,</hi> The ſeed of the woman ſhall bruſe the ſerpents head.<note place="margin">Gen 3, 15.</note> He liued to inſtruct <hi>Mathuſelah</hi> in this promiſe concerning Chriſt, 243 yeares;<note place="margin">Gen. 5, 25.10, 11.</note> the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, becauſe <hi>Methuſelah</hi> was appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of God to liue long and manie yeares after, of purpoſe to teach o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</p>
                  <p>That <hi>Adam</hi> fell the day of his cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation, all muſt hold, that loue not groſſe ignorance, our Lord telleth that Satan ſtood not in the truth. Now his falling
<pb facs="tcp:19647:43" rendition="simple:additions"/> could not be knowne to vs, to iudge of that ſpeech, but by the ſtorie of the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, which <hi>Moſes</hi> ioined with the creation: and it were irreligious bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to thruſt a practiſe of life betwixt, in another kinde. Moreouer, our Lord telleth that ſatan was a murtherer from the beginning, ſpeaking vnto Hebrues. They now his enemies not onelie graunt, but proue by the teſtimony vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſall of all their learned, that the ſixt day the ſerpent deceiued <hi>Eue.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>If <hi>Adam</hi> fell not ſame the day of his creation, what did he then on the next ſeuenth day? how beſtowed he the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baoth? if he were idle, then he gaue an ill preſident to his poſteritie; if he wrought, then he did worſe; and if it be ſaid that he was religiouſly occupied in the ſeruice of God, then it followeth that he fell the day before, whereupon Chriſt was promiſed, and to be adored the next ſabaoth.</p>
                  <p>Againe, if <hi>Adam</hi> fel not the ſame day of his creation, then <hi>Cain</hi> was begotten in innocencie; for it muſt needs be gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb facs="tcp:19647:43"/> acording to the inſtitution and qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of nature, that day or the next night <hi>Adam</hi> knew <hi>Eue</hi> his wife, in which he was conceiued.</p>
                  <p>The euening ſacrifice in the law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> had perfect relation to the coole of the day, or euening in which <hi>Adam</hi> tranſgreſſed.</p>
                  <p>The ſixt day in which Chriſt was crucified, and about the euening-tide, pointed plainly to the day, and to the verie time in the which <hi>Adam</hi> fel; the courſe of ſtorie, the words of our Lord, and the graunt and proofe of his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, inforceth men of modeſtie to beleeue it, and to thinke their humours ſtrange that dare croſſe the old and new Greeks, proteſtants, and Romiſts, to this day; the differing runne into more abſurditie than a large volume wold containe; and they who yeeld not to the moſt auntient and vniuerſall, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe they bring a reaſon that all muſt embrace, ſhew neither skill in learning, nor any reuerence to Chriſtianitie.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19647:44"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Seth</hi> Was the third ſonne of <hi>Adam,</hi> begotten in the likeneſſe of his father, when he was 130 yeare old, all the world is bound to take inſtruction of him, thereby to be ſetled in Chriſt the rocke.</p>
                  <p>All places of ſcripture that do<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>th import faith and conſtancie may be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced vnto this.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Enos</hi> Was verie zealous, and therfore ſorrowfull, when he ſaw the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption of religion and good maners, which was like to enſue vpon the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage of the ſonnes of God, with the daughters of men, who regard beautie and worldly preferment rather than the promiſes of life euerlaſting, by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuing in true religion.</p>
                  <p>To this you may referre the zeale of <hi>Moſes, Elias, Paule, Iohn,</hi> &amp;c. who wept for the ſinnes of the people, and deſired rather to be raſed out of the booke of life euerlaſting, than that ſo many thouſands ſhould periſh.</p>
                  <p>To this you may referre all vnordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate
<pb facs="tcp:19647:44"/> and vnequall marriages.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Kenan</hi> Had ſorrowfulneſſe, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, godly repentance, furniſhed with a godly care of amendment.</p>
                  <p>To this you may reduce all ſorrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and penitent ſinners.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Mahalaleell.</hi> Had a name very anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable to that acceptable ſacrifice which the creator impoſed vpon his creation, according to the ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nification of his owne name.</p>
                  <p>To this you may reduce all places of thanksgiuing and prayſing God.</p>
                  <p>So <hi>Leah</hi> named hir fourth ſonne <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah,</hi> ſignifying, Praiſe the Lord; this ought to be imitated of all men throughout the courſe of religion, and trade of life, the reaſon why, is ſhewed <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19, 47, 105, 120.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Iared</hi> Had the vertues of his fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers, which induced him to great humilitie and lowlineſſe.</p>
                  <p>To this you may reduce al ſuch pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
<pb facs="tcp:19647:45"/> how God exalteth the lowly and meeke.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Henoch</hi> Walked with God in holines, he was a man dedicated to the Lord by his name and trade of life, and therefore taken vp into heauen; he is the ſeuenth from <hi>Adam:</hi> his yeares are agreeable with the number of the ſaba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oth, putting all men in mind of the ſix daies creation, &amp; the ſeuenth daies redemption. Seuen is an holy and an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite number, importing grace and peace, by Ieſus Chriſt. The number of Seuen is taken many times for a time certaine and ceaſing, but in euill part, as <hi>Nabucadnezer</hi> was a beaſt Seuen yeres, and no longer. The tabernacle was a building Seuen moneths and no longer.</p>
                  <p>Seuen ſomtimes is taken in good part, and for a certaine time ceaſing, as the land of Canaan was Seuen yeres in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quering. Al notable actions were done in equall number of Seuen, as from <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> to Chriſts death by ſeuen ſeuens; Seuen fifties for the glorie of <hi>Ioſephs</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:19647:45"/> houſe; ſeuen ſeuenties for the houſe of Iudah; ſeuen tennes for the captiui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie; ſeuen ſeuenties to Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>The holy ſeruants of God, as a rare marke to behold, were borne in the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall number of ſeuen, as
<table>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Henoch.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell rows="6">The 7. from</cell>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Adam.</hi>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Heber.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Henoch.</hi>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Iſaac.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Heber.</hi>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Moſes.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Abraham.</hi>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Ioſua.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Ephraim.</hi>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Ioram.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Dauid.</hi>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                     </table>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Methuſelah</hi> Hauing all the vertues and bleſſedneſſe of his forefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, after his death ſhal haue life aeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, which his name did teach him by the ſignification therof. As <hi>Adam</hi> liued 743 yeares to inſtruct him, ſo he liued with <hi>Sem</hi> 98. yeares.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19647:46"/>
                  <p>Apply this to the faithful, as a reward of their labours in Chriſt, to which all ſuch like places may be reduced.</p>
                  <p>His age was an exact number or rule of the floud. The waters could not drowne the world while he liued.</p>
                  <p>The like may be ſaid of Lot, that fire could not fall vpon Sodome and Gomorah vntill he was in Zoar.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Lamech</hi> He was outwardly afflicted by men, and inwardly afflicted in conſcience, by the Deuill; he was a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, for he ſpake of things many hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred yeares paſt, and of the comfort to come by <hi>Noah.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>To this you may reduce the tribula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, afflictions, and ſorrowes of the church.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Noah</hi> Found grace and fauour with God, to whom almightie God vouchſafed to ſpeake, next vnto <hi>Adam,</hi> and to eſtabliſh the couenant with him; his houſhold as a ſmall remnant left in the Arke, is an aequall proportion of
<pb facs="tcp:19647:46"/> the ſmalneſſe of the church, in reſpect of the wicked multitude.</p>
                  <p>The Doue bringing an oliue leafe, ſignifieth peace and plentie: you may reduce it to the holy Ghoſt, bringing glad tidings and eternall ioy to the church. He was the tenth from <hi>Adam.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The ſignification of their names be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing well linked together, makes vp a chriſtian ſacrifice, the whole ſumme of religion, or the liuely image and portra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of Chriſt. Goe backeward or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward with their names, by the ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation or Aetymologie thereof; he that hath one vertue hath all, he that miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth of one vertue, miſſeth of all, they cannot be ſeperated.</p>
                  <p>Forward thus; He that is ſetled in Chriſt, as was <hi>Seth,</hi> is ſorrowfull for ſin as <hi>Enos.</hi> He that is ſorrowfull for ſinne hath godly repentance, with <hi>Kenan.</hi> He that hath godly repentance, praiſeth God in pouertie and in plentie, with <hi>Mahalaleel.</hi> He that praiſeth God is lowly in all eſtates, as was <hi>Iared.</hi> He that is lowly ſanctifieth the ſabaoth, as did
<pb facs="tcp:19647:47"/> 
                     <hi>Henoch.</hi> He that ſanctifieth the ſaba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oth, hath long life with <hi>Methuſelah.</hi> He that hath theſe former vertues ſhal be heartely wounded in this world, as was <hi>Lamech,</hi> but in the world to come he ſhall haue ioy and comfort with <hi>Noah.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Backward thus; He that hath not ioy and comfort in Chriſt with <hi>Noah,</hi> is not heartily wounded with the affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of this life as was <hi>Lamech.</hi> He that is not heartily wounded, hath no hope of long life with <hi>Methuſelah.</hi> He that hopeth not for long life kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth not the ſabaoth with <hi>Henoch.</hi> He that keepeth not the ſabaoth, is not lowly with <hi>Iared.</hi> He that is not lowly, praiſeth not God with <hi>Mahalaell.</hi> He that praiſeth not God, hath not godly repentance with <hi>Kenan.</hi> He that hath not godly repentance, is not ſorrowfull for ſinne with <hi>Enos.</hi> He that is not ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowfull for ſinne, is not ſetled in Chriſt. He that is not ſetled in Chriſt, is earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, miſerable, and periſheth.</p>
                  <p>I pray you labour well for the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of this ſtorie, let nothing paſſe,
<pb facs="tcp:19647:47"/> for all is profitable.</p>
                  <p>In them the law is thundered, in them the Goſpell is preached, and in them the ſacraments are adminiſtred.</p>
                  <p>All the world were enimies to theſe few, as appeared by Gods iudgement vpon them by a floud.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="exegesis">
                  <head>The particulars of the Second ſtorie.</head>
                  <p>
                     <table>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Sem.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell rows="10">Signifieth</cell>
                           <cell>Renowned.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Arphaxad.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>Healing.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Sale.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>Peace.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Heber.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>Pilgrime.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Peleg.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>Deuided.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Regue.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>Breaking.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Sarug.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>Palme trees.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Nahor.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>Angrie or drie.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Terah.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>A wretch.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Abram</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>High father.<note place="margin">Gen. 11,</note>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                     </table>
                  </p>
                  <p>Here the great and mightie creator, in the number of other ten holie fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, beginneth to multiplie a new ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety or ſanctified people, and to ſet vp his owne glorie in open ſhew to all that ſhould come after, according to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion in the former age.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19647:48"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Sem</hi> Was <hi>Noahs</hi> ſonne who afterwards was called <hi>Melchiſedech,</hi> becauſe he was to beare a perfect demonſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or figure of Chriſt; he was ſaid to be the king of peace, of iuſtice, and of righteouſneſſe, and to be without fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and without mother,<note place="margin">Gen. 14, 18. Heb. 7, 1.</note> without be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of daies and end of life. So long liued he after the floud, that his kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red was vnknowne, for in <hi>Abrahams</hi> time he was a great grandfather of eight degrees. <hi>Melchiſedech</hi> muſt be <hi>Sem,</hi> for none of <hi>Chams</hi> houſe, nor any of <hi>Iaphets</hi> houſe, could reſemble the ſonne of God, whoſe religion was to come from <hi>Salem. Noah</hi> hauing found fauour with God, and perceiuing by a ſpirite of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie, that his ſonne <hi>Sem</hi> ſhould be bleſſed, and of great fame with God and man, he named him, Renowmed; which in the Hebrue is according to the Aetymologie of his name. Thus of the other nine.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19647:48"/>
                  <p>
                     <table>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Elam.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell rows="4">Their iſſue</cell>
                           <cell>Elamits.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Aſhur.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>Aſsyrians.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Iud.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>Lidians.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Aram.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>Aramits, or Aſsyrians.</cell>
                        </row>
                     </table>
                  </p>
                  <p>Theſe were the wicked off-ſpring of <hi>Sem,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Gen. 10, 12,</note> who became ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> enemies to him and to other of that ſacred line, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce Chriſt ſhould come.</p>
                  <p>
                     <table>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Gomer.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell rows="3">Their iſſue.</cell>
                           <cell>Tartarians.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Magog.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>Turkes, and Scythians.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Madai.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>Medes.</cell>
                        </row>
                     </table>
                     <table>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Iauan.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell rows="4">Their iſſue</cell>
                           <cell rows="2">People of Aſia and Gracia.<note place="margin">Ezec 27, 1.2.38, 1.2.</note>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Tuball.</hi>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Meſech.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell rows="2">Theſe were the ſonnes of <hi>Iaphet,</hi>
                              <note place="margin">Gen. 10, 2.3.4.5.</note> of whom were the Gentils.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Tiras.</hi>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                     </table>
                  </p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19647:49"/>
                  <p>
                     <table>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Cuſh.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell rows="4">The iſſue</cell>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Ninnod</hi> a mightie hunter, the builder of Babel. <hi>Gen.</hi> 10, 8.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Miſraim.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>Aegyptians, in Hebrue Miſraims.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Pute.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>Blacke moores.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Canaan</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>Canaanites and Pereſits, <hi>Gen.</hi> 10.</cell>
                        </row>
                     </table>
                  </p>
                  <p>Theſe were the ſonnes of <hi>Cham,</hi> who became profeſſed and ſworne ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies in this age.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="exegesis">
                  <head>The particulars of the third ſtorie.</head>
                  <p>
                     <table>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Ruben.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell rows="12">Signi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth</cell>
                           <cell>Water.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Simeon.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>A ſword.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Leui.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>A booke.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Iudah.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>A lion.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Dan.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>An adder.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Nepthali.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>A Hind.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Gad.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>A banner.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Aſher.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>Bread.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Iſachar.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>An aſſe.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Zabulon.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>A ſhip.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Ioſeph.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>A fuictful bow.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <note place="margin">Gen. 29.</note>
                              <hi>Beniamin.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>A wolfe.</cell>
                        </row>
                     </table>
                  </p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19647:49"/>
                  <p>In this age almightie God maketh his ſeruice &amp; religion more open and appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent than before, by diuerſe ordinances, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtitutions &amp; lawes, which he impoſed vpon theſe twelue holie fathers, to be vnrepealed vntill the paſsion of Ieſus Chriſt: in the meane time God dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted them and guided them as it were by hand, and fead them in due ſeaſon, with al things miraculouſly: out of theſe as out of one man, (euen <hi>Abram</hi> their father, to whom the promiſe was made) there came a mightie nation, fierce and terrible, againſt whom the kings of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan could not preuaile, no, not the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill in hell; whoſe kingdome is a king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of power. Our of theſe twelue came all thoſe of whom God had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard, vntil Chriſt. They are diſpearſed in the ſcripture to great vſe, therefore learne their ſtories, ſo you ſhal be able to ſay ſomething of euerie one. In the creation God did foreſee this royal na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, deriued from the twelue tribes; for in their iourney to Canaan, they came to <hi>Elim,</hi> where was twelue fountaines.
<pb facs="tcp:19647:50"/> He deuided the yeare according to their number; the twelue ſtones in <hi>Aarons</hi> breſt, the twelue ſtones out of Iordan, and diuerſe other notable things of that number, hath relation to this people. You muſt be perfit in their par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular ſtories, for example thus:</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Iudah</hi> Was the fourth ſonne of <hi>Iacob,</hi> whom <hi>Rachel</hi> bare vnto him,<note place="margin">Gen. 29, 31.32.</note> ſhe called his name <hi>Iudah,</hi> which is by interpretation, Praiſe the Lord; wherein ſhe ſhewed a perpetuall me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie of Gods mercie, not onely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſhe being deſpiſed and reproched for hir barrenneſſe, had now the fourth ſonne, but alſo becauſe that of his ſeed the Meſsias ſhould come, in whom all the world might ſing and praiſe the Lord. <hi>Iacob</hi> by a ſpirite of diuination did foreſee the ſame, and therefore among the reſt of his brethren, at his death he gaue him a name or a cogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſance of great magnanimitie and cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, ſpeaking after this manner; <hi>Iudah,</hi> as a lions whelpe thou ſhalt come vpon
<pb facs="tcp:19647:50"/> the ſpoile, my ſonne; he ſhall lie downe and couch as a lion, and as a lioneſſe, who ſhall ſtirre him vp? Here is a plaine narration of Chriſt, compared to a lion, for his kinglie properties, no man daring to withſtand him; of whom S. <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Reuel. 5, 5.</note> Behold the lion out of the tribe of <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah,</hi> hath obtained to open the booke, and to vnlooſe the ſeales thereof; mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Chriſt Ieſus is he that ſhutteth and no man openeth, and he that openeth and no man ſhutteth. <hi>Moſes</hi> that king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly prophet, at his death bleſſed theſe twelue tribes in another ſort, and yet ratefying the former, wherein he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membreth <hi>Iudah</hi> aboue the reſt.</p>
                  <p>Theſe were enemies in this age, with their iſſue.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Iſmael.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Eſau.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </div>
               <div type="exegesis">
                  <pb facs="tcp:19647:51"/>
                  <head>The particulars of the <hi>4.</hi> Storie.</head>
                  <p>
                     <table>
                        <row>
                           <cell rows="12">12 princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall ſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, or ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of Iſraell.</cell>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Ramaſes.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Ex.</hi> 12</cell>
                           <cell>Wormes meat.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Succoth.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>13</cell>
                           <cell>Poore cottages.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Ethan.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>13</cell>
                           <cell>Hard ground.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Maarah.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>15</cell>
                           <cell>Bitterneſſe.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Elim.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>15</cell>
                           <cell>Strong hearts.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Sin.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>16</cell>
                           <cell>Thornie.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Rephedim.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>17</cell>
                           <cell>Temptation.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Sinai.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>19</cell>
                           <cell>Euerlaſting te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptation</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Jothathae.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                              </hi> 1,</cell>
                           <cell>Turning away.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Hor.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>20</cell>
                           <cell>Declaring, or ſhewing.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Zalinonah.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>21</cell>
                           <cell>Shadow of a portion.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Moab.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>27.</cell>
                           <cell>Of the father.</cell>
                        </row>
                     </table>
                  </p>
                  <p>The ſaid twelue tribes were fortie yeares trauelling from Aegypt, vnder the conduct of <hi>Moſes,</hi> towards Cana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an. They pitched their tents and reſted
<pb facs="tcp:19647:51"/> in two and fortie places, whereof ſome were pleaſant, and ſome were vnplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant, of which I haue reckoned vp theſe twelue. Read the chapters oppoſit, and you ſhall direct your memorie to all that was done in this age.</p>
                  <p>Enemies in this time.
<list>
                        <item>King <hi>Pharao.</hi> Exod. 1, 5, 14,</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Amalakits.</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15,</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="exegesis">
                  <head>The particulars of the fift ſtorie.</head>
                  <p>Wherein conſider:
<list>
                        <item>1 The ſtrength of Canaan; hauing relation to Sathans force.</item>
                        <item>2 The weakeneſſe of the conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours; hauing relation to the poore church of Chriſt.</item>
                        <item>3 The time of the conqueſt, which was ſeuen yeares; hauing relation to Ieſus Chriſt the conquerour of conquerours, written and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſed in the aequall number of Seuen, as many other great and famous acts are.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19647:52"/>
                  <p>The black Moores, the Canaanites, the Pereſites, being the progenie of <hi>Chant, Noahs</hi> curſed ſonne, banded themſelues, and became an huge ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie againſt the hoſt of Iſrael.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="exegesis">
                  <head>The particulars of the ſixt Storie.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Acts 13, 20.</note>THeſe 13 Iudges or gouernors con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued<note n="*" place="margin">But in proprietie of Chron. 339.</note> 450 years, accounting the years of the oppreſſors. Their ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie ſerues very well to ſhew the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God againſt obſtinat ſinners, and his mercies to the penitent. There are many waightie things therein, and well worth the perfecting.</p>
                  <p>
                     <table>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Othoniell.</cell>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Iudg</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell rows="14">Of the Tribe of</cell>
                           <cell>Iudah.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Ehud.</cell>
                           <cell>3</cell>
                           <cell>Beniamin.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Deborah, &amp; Barack.</cell>
                           <cell>6</cell>
                           <cell>Nepthali.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Gedeon.</cell>
                           <cell>6</cell>
                           <cell>Ephraim.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Ahimelech,</cell>
                           <cell>8</cell>
                           <cell>Ephraim,</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Tola.</cell>
                           <cell>10</cell>
                           <cell>Iſachar.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Iair.</cell>
                           <cell>10</cell>
                           <cell>Manaſſes.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Iepthe.</cell>
                           <cell>11</cell>
                           <cell>Ephraim.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Abelane.</cell>
                           <cell>12</cell>
                           <cell>Iudah.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Eglon.</cell>
                           <cell>12</cell>
                           <cell>Zabulon.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Abden.</cell>
                           <cell>12</cell>
                           <cell>Manaſſes.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Sampſon.</cell>
                           <cell>13</cell>
                           <cell>Dan.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Holy.</cell>
                           <cell>1. <hi>Sa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> 1</cell>
                           <cell>Leui.</cell>
                        </row>
                     </table>
                  </p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19647:52"/>
                  <p>Oppreſſours or enemies, after the death of <hi>Ioſhua,</hi> when the people be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came ſecure and careleſſe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <table>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Philiſtims.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell rows="5">
                              <hi>Iud.</hi> 3,</cell>
                           <cell rows="5">Theſe were ſtirred vp as rods &amp; as ſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges for the people, when they neglected the holy worſhip and ſeruice of the higheſt.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Canaanites.</hi>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Sidonians.</hi>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Heuits.</hi>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Chuſan.</hi>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Eglon.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Iudg.</hi> 3.</cell>
                           <cell rows="7"> </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Iabin.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>4,</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Madianites</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>6,</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Amalakites</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>6,</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Philistims.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>10</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Amonites.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell rows="2">13</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Philiſtimes</hi>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                     </table>
                  </p>
                  <p>Here you may proue ar large the aſſurance of Gods loue and fauour, where good men doe beare rule, and are obaied; and on the contrarie his iuſtice, where wicked men doe beare rule, and the people rebellious in his ſeruice. I haue diſtinguiſhed the good from the bad, as they ſucceeded, ſo are you to learne them perfectly. Read the booke.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="exegesis">
                  <pb facs="tcp:19647:53"/>
                  <head>The particulars of the ſeuenth ſtorie.</head>
                  <p>Wherein conſider well three kings, before the kingdome of Iſraell was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Saule.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Dauid.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Salomon.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Saul</hi> Signifieth, Deſired of the people; He was of the tribe of <hi>Beniamin,</hi> which thing was a great prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatine to that tribe, being the leaſt, and the laſt. Becauſe the people diſpaired in the mercies of God, and diſtruſted his power, hauing giuen them manifeſt aſſurance of the ſame, he gaue them ſuch a one as they deſerued, to weet, an Hipocrite, and an open enemie to all truth and ſinceritie, who ſlew all that did weare an Ephod,<note place="margin">1. Sam. 10, 13, 18.19.20.17</note> and tooke an oth of the people to betray harmeleſſe and guiltleſſe <hi>Dauid,</hi> and the reſt.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19647:53"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Dauid</hi> Beleeued God, and his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome was reckoned when the Ark was recouered to <hi>Iudah</hi> at Eaſter; ſo Chriſt at Eaſter was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed king. He was of the tribe of <hi>Iudah,</hi> of the roote of <hi>Ieſſe,</hi> he killed a Beare, and a great outragious Phili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine, that defied Iſraell; wherein he was a figure of Chriſt. He had many e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, and infinite diſtreſſes; therein he was a figure of the church.<note place="margin">1 Sam. 16, 17,</note> 
                     <hi>Dauid</hi> was vpright exept in this, 1. <hi>King.</hi> 15, 5.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Salomon</hi> Signifieth peace; ſo was his kingdome. For his wiſdome and order in religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, he might wel be a figure of Chriſt.<note place="margin">Kin. 11, 4.5. 2 Sam. 13, 14, 2 Chro. 3, 1. 1 King. 12, 1 Kin. 11, 1, Ezech, 37, 16.17.18.</note> He fell to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treame ſinnes, yet he was ſaued. He laid the foundation of the temple, in Moriah. His kingdome was diuided into two parts, according to the words of the Lord vnto him, but after 490 yeares were expired, it was throwne together againe.</p>
                  <p>Immediatly after the death of <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:19647:54"/> the great and entire kingdome of Iſrael was deuided into two parts, whereof one was called the kingdome of Iudah, whoſe ſeat was at Ieruſalem, the other was called the kingdome of Iſrael, whoſe ſeat was at Samaria. The kings of Iſrael were open and profeſſed enemies to the kings of Iudah, Iſrael was ſtronger than Iudah, for the one had tenne tribes, the other onely two, that held and tooke part.</p>
                  <p>When you read the booke of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel</hi> or the booke of the Kings, marke diligentlie theſe ſix neceſſarie que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1 Whether the king of Iudah, or of Iſrael?</item>
                     <item>2 Whether he were good or e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill?</item>
                     <item>3 What prophet, one or more?</item>
                     <item>4 The religion of the people?</item>
                     <item>5 Their manners and conuerſation?</item>
                     <item>6 Their proſperitie or aduerſitie?</item>
                  </list>
               </div>
               <div type="exegesis">
                  <pb facs="tcp:19647:54"/>
                  <head>The particulars of the eight ſtorie. Daniel.</head>
                  <p>In this booke is ſet forth a true pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion of Antechriſts earthly glorie, which for a time reached vnto heauen, and mounted ouer all nations; the end was as a tree cut downe by the roots, with an axe. And who ſees not here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the prouidence of God, in the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of time, ſhining vpon his ſanctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arie, which ſo long had laine waſte? To make this plaine, and to direct your memorie ſure, I canne deuiſe no better inſtruction ſhort and plaine, than that which is in my former booke of method.</p>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Two things muſt be well marked.</head>
                     <p>The one, what kings raigned in Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilon during the captiuitie.</p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:19647:55"/>
                     <p>The other, what kings raigned and ruled after the captiuitie, vntill Chriſt.</p>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <note place="margin">Three kings during the captiuitie.</note>
                           <hi>Nabucadnezer</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Euilmeredech.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Baltaſher.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Dan. 12, 3.4.</item>
                        <item>2. King. 25, 27.</item>
                        <item>Dan. 5, 8.</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <p>What is to be ſaid of them.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Nabucadnezer</hi> Saw a viſion; A great Image,<note place="margin">Dan. 2, 31.</note> whoſe glorie was excellent, and very terrible, bearing theſe 5 parts and proportions:</p>
                     <p>His
<list>
                           <item>Head was as fine gold,</item>
                           <item>Breaſts and armes of ſiluer.</item>
                           <item>Bellie and thighs of Braſſe.</item>
                           <item>Legges of yron.</item>
                           <item>Feet part of yron and part of clay.</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <p>The true expoſition of this image, according to the parts thereof, as the holy Ghoſt ſets it downe, ſignifieth <hi>Nabucadnezer;</hi> who for his greatneſſe is compared to a tree, reaching to the
<pb facs="tcp:19647:55"/> heauens: that which <hi>he</hi> ſaw as a moſt goodly and glorious image,<note place="margin">Dan. 4.16,</note> 
                        <hi>Daniel</hi> ſaw <hi>it</hi> in a viſion, verie fierce and terrible, as a lion with Eagles wings chopt off. It was lifted vp and ſet vpon his feet, as a man, and a mans heart was giuen vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him.</p>
                     <p>The other two kings, to weet, <hi>Euil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meredech,</hi> and <hi>Baltaſhar,</hi> are referred in compariſon to the firſt, who raigned iuſt 45 yeares as appeareth thus.</p>
                     <p>He tooke <hi>Iehoiachim</hi> king of Iudah, in the eight yeare of his raigne.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Euilmeredech</hi> his ſonne who ſuccee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded him, lifted vp <hi>Iehoiachim</hi> out of pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon where he had lain, ſeuen and thirty yeares, in which <hi>Iehoiachim</hi> was raiſed vp, that makes iuſt fiue and forty yeres, being the whole raigne of this firſt king.</p>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Euilmeredech</hi> raigned 22 yeares.</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Baltaſhar</hi> raigned 3 yeares.</item>
                     </list>
                     <p>Thus you may ſee plainly the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenty
<pb facs="tcp:19647:56"/> yeares were fully ended in the particular raigne of theſe three kings,<note place="margin">Iere. 25, 12.</note> according to a propheſie.</p>
                     <p>Now the head of gold is gon off, and quite taken away, the kings of Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel are extinquiſhed, and the ſeuentie yeares expired. In this age the church was exiled, vnder rulers of cruell and beaſtly affections.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="exegesis">
                  <head>The particulars of the ninth ſtorie.</head>
                  <p>WHen the ſeuentie years were ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pliſhed,<note place="margin">Leui. 26, 40. 1. Kin. 8, 46.</note> which were foretold, <hi>Daniel</hi> praied vnto the Lord for the reſtoring of the deſolation of Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, which ſo long had beene exiled, and in diſgrace; whiles he yet ſpake and praied, the Angell of the Lord came in haſt about the euening ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, who vttered theſe words:</p>
                  <p>Seuenty yeares are determined vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thy people, and vpon thy holy ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,<note place="margin">Dan. 9, 24,</note> to bring in euerlaſting righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
                  <p>Here is an euen reckoning and a iuſt
<pb facs="tcp:19647:56"/> account caſt out of all the times from <hi>Daniels</hi> viſion, at the Edict,<note place="margin">9, 21.</note> vnto the death of Chriſt the prince of peace.</p>
                  <p>Euerie weeke hath ſeuen daies; the Angel means for euerie day in a weeke a yeare; ſeuen daies, ſeuen yeares,<note place="margin">Leuit. 29, 8.9.10</note> after the reckoning of the Iubile yeare, the whole is 490 yeares.</p>
                  <p>The ſame Angel for plainneſſe, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uides the ſame ſeuen weekes,<note place="margin">Dan. 9, 25.</note> into three parts, after this manner.</p>
                  <p>The firſt part ſhall be ſeuen weeks, that is to ſay, forty and nine yeares, from the going forth of the commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that the people of Iſrael ſhould be freed in the firſt yeare of <hi>Darius,</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the building and finiſhing of the temple at Ieruſalem, the proofe wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is thus.</p>
                  <p>The Iewes confeſſe fortie and ſix yeares,<note place="margin">Ioh. 2, 20. Ezra.. 4, Nehc. 4, Ezra 6, Neh. 7, 8.9.10, 13. Dan. 10, 1.2.</note> in which the temple was a buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding: in the other three yeares they were hindered from their worke, in which three yeares of trouble <hi>Sirus</hi> raigned; yet according to the Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties former reckoning it was finiſhed.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19647:57"/>
                  <p>The kings and rulers that were in this age or deuiſion of time appeareth thus:</p>
                  <p>Armes and breaſts of ſiluer, being part of the image which <hi>Nabucadnezer</hi> ſaw,<note place="margin">Dan. 2, 39.</note> ſignifieth ten kings of the Medes and Perſians, who continued one hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and thirtie yeares, who are theſe.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1 <hi>Cirus</hi> or <hi>Darius.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2 <hi>Artaxerxes</hi> or <hi>Cambiſes.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>3 <hi>Aſſuerus</hi> or <hi>Darius.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>4 <hi>Hiſtaſpes.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>5 <hi>Xerxes.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <p>Theſe raigned twentie and nine yeares, in the twentith yeare of <hi>Artax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erxes</hi> or <hi>Darius</hi> the Temple was built, being full fortie and nine yeare.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19647:57"/>
                  <p>Theſe other kings were after the building, who made vp the hundred and thirtie yeares.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>6 <hi>Ochus.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>7 <hi>Artaxerxes.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>8 <hi>Ochus.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>9 <hi>Arſes.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>10 <hi>Darius</hi> the Perſian.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>Theſe kings which ſeemed to the world to be glorious, as the armes and breaſts of ſiluer, <hi>Daniel</hi> ſees them like a ſauage and a cruel beare, with iij. ribs in his mouth, ſaying; Ariſe, let vs de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoure much fleſh, ſo did they macerate the ſaints of God, but at their death the armes and breaſts of ſiluer is ſaid to be cut off, being kings of Madai and Paras.</p>
                  <p>The ſecond part of the Angels de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſion of time.<note place="margin">Dan 2, 16.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>Sixtie and two yeares ſhall be a trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſome time for Gods people, after the which the prince of peace, the king of glorie ſhal be ſlaine, euen he
<pb facs="tcp:19647:58"/> ſhall deſtroy the citie and the ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuarie.</p>
                  <p>The bellie and thighs of braſſe doth ſignifie king <hi>Alexanders</hi> power.</p>
                  <p>To this belongeth the viſion of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">8, 3.4.</note> a Goat buck with a horne, which being broken off, comes out in ſteed thereof foure heads, ſignifying <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anders</hi> foure captaines fighting two and two, which two firſt is alſo the legges of yron and clay and their ſucceſſours, and the 4 beaſt with 10 hornes. <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander</hi> continued ſix yeares.</p>
                  <p>His legges of iron.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Dan. 7, 7.</note>Is the beaſt which <hi>Daniel</hi> ſaw verie fearefull and ſtrong, with yron teeth burſt in pieces, and ſtamped the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidue vnder his feet, who was the fourth kingdome in the earth, ſubdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all to himſelfe.<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>3.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>The tenne hornes are tenne king ſtronger than the Iewes, that ſhall riſe out of Siria and Aegypt, whereof one is ſaid to be a little horne boaſting againſt the moſt higheſt.<note place="margin">8, 7.11.</note>
                  </p>
                  <list>
                     <pb facs="tcp:19647:58"/>
                     <head>Iron like.</head>
                     <item>1 <hi>Solennicus Nicator.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2 <hi>Antiochus Soter.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>3 <hi>Antiochus Theos.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>4 <hi>Solenicus Callicus.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>5 <hi>Solenicus Serauius.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>6 <hi>Antiochus Megas.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>7 <hi>Solenicus Philopater.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>8 <hi>Antiochus Epimanes.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Iauan</hi> kings of Aegypt, yron like, to make vp the ten horns.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>9 <hi>Ptolomeus Lagi.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>10 <hi>Ptolomeus Philodelphus.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19647:59"/>
                  <p>His feet part of yron and part of clay, were <hi>Iauan</hi> kings of Babell clay like in number twelue.</p>
                  <p>Theſe kings as beaſts ruled moſt beaſtly and vnnaturally, verie ſtrong 294. yeares to <hi>Cleopatras</hi> death, who preſumptuouſly confirmed <hi>Herod</hi> king ouer Iudah.</p>
                  <p>The third part of the Angels deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of time, conſiſting in theſe wordes.</p>
                  <p>He ſhall confirme the couenant with many for one weeke, and in the midſt of the weeke he ſhall cauſe the ſacrifice to ceaſe.<note place="margin">Dan. 9, 27.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>Theſe wordes hath plaine relation to Ieſus Chriſt, his death, reſurrection, &amp;c. for one weeke in the account of the Iubile yeare aforeſaid, ſtandeth for ſeuen yeares, a yeare for a day.</p>
                  <p>In the midſt of the ſame weeke, that is to ſay, in the midſt of this laſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen yeares, Chriſt was baptized, and did preach this laſt halfe ſeuen yeares, confirming his authority with miracles, ſignes, and wonders, vntill the ſame three yeres and halfe, the end of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niels</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:19647:59"/> weeke, was ended.</p>
                  <p>In which he ſuffered his paſsion ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as it was before determined manie thouſand years in the councell of the euerlaſting Trinitie.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:19647:60"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19647:60"/>
                  <head>
                     <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> To the elect Lady <hi>Florence Herberd,</hi> late the wife of a worthie knight, Sir <hi>William Herberd,</hi> of S. <hi>Iulians,</hi> in the Countie of Munmoth, diſceaſed.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S a pretious<note n="*" place="margin">Cant. 1, 2, 1. Ioh. 2, 20.27.</note> ointment being poured foorth caſteth out, and ſprea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth abroad a ſweet, a fragrant, and an odiferous ſmell farre and near: euen ſo (good Chriſtian Lady) the name and fame of ſuch as are annointed with the holy Ghoſt, doth caſt out and ſpread it ſelfe farre and near, verie ſweet to the noſthrils of the Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,
<pb facs="tcp:19647:61"/> and verie delightfull to the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of Chriſt. Though the diſtance of place, and the conueniencie of time, hath not miniſtred vnto me any ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance with you, nor occaſions to ſee you, yet your<note n="b" place="margin">Act. 10, 2.</note> deuout behauiour, your fulneſſe of almes, and your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall praying, with other your mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt and chaſt conuerſations, being caſt out and ſpread abroad farre and near, makes me bold to write vnto you, as to one perfectly knowne, and wel acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and that with no leſse than three ſpeciall and waightie occaſions, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing and vrging me. The firſt is, to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure you and to proteſt vnto you that I haue truely, ſincerely, and faithfully, publiſhed this your husbands labour, annexed with my owne, as he deſired (by the fauour of a worſhipfull gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man who hath vndertaken to patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nize the ſame with the reſt.) The ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d is, to deſire pardon of your Ladi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip
<pb facs="tcp:19647:61"/> for the long delaing thereof, ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thence my importunities are iuſt, and my excuſes reaſonable. The third is, in the mercifulneſse of Chriſt Ieſu to exhort you, and to comfort you on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in the good way and right courſe which your Chriſtian husband hath left you. He hath broken the yſe to his pains, you may ſee the cleare water at your pleaſure: he hath crazed the ſhell to his verie death, you may take the kernell all your life: and he hath ſauo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of the ſauce that was ſoure, now you may aſſay and eate of the ſweete. His pains hath brought him at the laſt to drinke of Chriſt, the water of life: his continuall hungring after righteouſneſſe, hath brought him to eate of ſpirituall Manna, the food of his ſoule: and his bitter annoy is chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged into heauenly and eternall ioy.<note n="c" place="margin">1. Cor. 15, 49.</note> He that bare in the earth the image of the earthy, now beares the image of the
<pb facs="tcp:19647:62"/> heauenly. He once was ſubiect to ſinne becauſe he was ſubiect to the law, and being ſubiect to the law, he was ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to death, but thanks be to God, who hath giuen him victorie in Ieſus Christ. Death is now dead, death is ſwallowed vp, his death is dead, and how?<note place="margin">1. Cor. 15, 57. Hoſ. 13, 14. Eſa. 25, 8.9. 1. Cor. 15, 54.55.56.</note> Sinne is the ſting or the life of death, the life of ſinne is the law; now, take away the law, take away ſin; take away ſinne, then death is dead, death is gon and vtterly deſtroyed:<note n="d" place="margin">Luke. 7,</note> and to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, your husband (ſweete Lady) is aliue, he is not dead but liueth, he was a knight on earth, he is now a<note n="e" place="margin">Gal. 5, Re. 1, 6. Cant. 5, 1.</note> king in heauen. And ſince his chance was to make ſuch an exchange, good Madame be merrie, though his companie was your comfort, yet be not againſt his preferment, and know this to be a common and a commendable ſaying, Paſt cure, paſt care. Out of remedie, out of reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brance.<note n="f" place="margin">1. Sam. 12, 20.21.22.23.</note> 
                     <hi>Dauid</hi> whilſt his
<pb facs="tcp:19647:62"/> ſonne was aliue, faſted and wept bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly, but when he was dead, he was merrie and reioyſed greatly. As it is ſure whilſt your husband was aliue, you did the one, ſo now ſeing he is dead let it be ſurely ſeene for good example that you doe the other. As <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaid of his ſonne I ſhall goe to him, but he ſhall not come to me: ſo ſay you, (good worſhipfull Lady) I ſhall goe to my husband, my husband ſhal not returne to me. Beare you the croſse valiantly, which you haue taken vp zealouſly, no manner of diſco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tentment is ioyous for the preſent time, but grieuous, neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe afterwards it bringeth quiet reſt. As fine Gold is wrought in flaming fire, and white ſiluer in blacke pitch, euen ſo glorie is to be gotten with the depth of danger, and pleaſure with the price of paine. As the roots of a tree are bitter and the fruits ſweete, euen ſo of bitter annoy comes pleaſant ioy,
<pb facs="tcp:19647:63"/> and of an heauie ſute, happy ſucceſſe. That it may be a parcell of your ioy in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ſee him which was your ioy in earth, reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber the inſtruction he gaue you whilſt he was liuing, reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber the councell he gaue you whilſt he was dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, &amp; remember to keepe in practiſe ſeriouſly, and ſinceerely, among your houſhold, the ſtudie and the excerciſe of true religion, according to the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Ieſus Chriſt. To whoſe holy tuition and mercifull prouidence I leaue your Ladiſhip, with ſo many good deſires for your godly deſerts, as miles hath ſeuered S. <hi>Iulian</hi> and S. <hi>Leonard.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Yours in the Lord,</hi> Edw: Vaughan.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="exegesis">
                  <pb facs="tcp:19647:63"/>
                  <head>Sir <hi>William Herberd</hi> knight his particulars vpon the tenth ſtory, to weet, from the birth of Chriſt to the worlds end.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Onſider the times from the birth of Chriſt to the end of the world, which by the doctrin of <hi>Elias</hi> amounteth to 2000 yeares, the whole time may be deuided into ſeuen ſucceſsiue ages, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the
<table>
                        <row>
                           <cell rows="3">
                              <hi>Seuen</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Churches.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell>Reuel. 1, 4.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Seales.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell> 5, 1.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>
                              <hi>Trumpets.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell> 8, 6.</cell>
                        </row>
                     </table>
                  </p>
                  <p>The two firſt are aſcribed to the church of Epheſus and Smyrma, which accompliſhed the firſt 300 yeares, for
<pb facs="tcp:19647:64"/> it is manifeſt that the things ſpoken to thoſe churches concerne the firſt 300 yeares after Chriſt, that is to ſay, The examination of falſe Apoſtles, the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the Nicolaitans hereſies, the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>during of the extreame malice of the Iews,<note place="margin">Reu. 2, 10.</note> and of the ten perſecutions, with patience and conſtancie, is called the tribulation of ten daies.</p>
                  <p>The third deuiſion belongeth to the church of Pergamus, to which, as to each that follow, we attribute 340 yeares, which reacheth from the yeare of our Lord till the 640. That age is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended for conſtancie in the truth, and becauſe there were then ſome that doted vpon images, and had ordained dedication to the Idols temple, to the martyrs and vigils, in their honour, which was a ſpirituall fornication, pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed of the Nicolaitans, this age was therefore thus reprooued: <hi>I haue a few things to ſay to thee, becauſe thou haſt maintained the doctrine of</hi> Balaam, <hi>which taught</hi> Balac <hi>to put a ſtumbling blocke be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the children of Iſrael, and that they
<pb facs="tcp:19647:64"/> ſhould eat things ſacrificed to Idols, and to commit fornication.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Reu. 2, 14.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>The fourth deuiſion or age is appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priated to the church of Thiatira, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending from the yeare 640, to the yeare 980. The church in this age is commended for hir great deuotion, but becauſe it permitted the church of Rome to vſurpe authoritie, and to be another <hi>Ieſabel</hi> in Samaria, drawing people to Idolatrie, it is therefore re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued, the plagues that God would bring vpon the church of Rome, are declared, and the children of the true church exhorted to continue in the antient faith which they haue already receiued.</p>
                  <p>The fift deuiſion or age is the church of Sardic, which beginneth at the yere 980, continued till the yeare 1332. In this age the ſpirit of <hi>Ieſabel</hi> was growne ſo ſtrong, and hir <hi>Achab</hi> ſo wicked, that the viſible church bare onely the name of a church, the doctrine generally cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted, and things reduced, touching the publicke worſhipping of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie,
<pb facs="tcp:19647:65"/> vnto that miſerable eſtare, that they reſembled the raigne of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chab</hi> and <hi>Ieſabel,</hi> wherein <hi>Elias</hi> had ſo greatly complained, yet God had then his ſecreat elect expreſſed in theſe wordes, <hi>I know thy workes and where thou dwelleſt,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Reu. 2, 13.</note> 
                     <hi>euen where Sathans throne is, thou keepeſt my name, and haſt not deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the faith.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The ſixt deuiſion appertaineth to the church of Philodelphia, which containes the times that we liue, and all the yeares from 1320, till the yeare of our Lord 1660. In this age of the church the truth of the doctrine is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleniſhed, and the truth of the Goſpell floriſhed, notwithſtanding all inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours againſt it, the faithfull are endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with ſpirituall ſtrength, thus; <hi>I haue ſet before thee an open doore, and no man can ſhut it, for thou hast a little ſtrength, and hast kept my works,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Reu. 3, 8.</note> 
                     <hi>and haſt not deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed my name.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The ſeuenth deuiſion or age, is attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted to the yeare 2000, this age for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getting the mercie of God wil proue to
<pb facs="tcp:19647:65"/> be careleſſe of heauenly things, being neither hote nor cold. Therefore God will loath and abhorre this age, mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt in theſe wordes; <hi>I know thy workes, and tribulation, and pouertie, but thou art ritch, and I know the blaſphemie of thoſe which ſay they are Iews, and are not,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Reu. 2.8.9.</note> 
                     <hi>but are the ſynagogue of Sathan.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Beſides theſe myſteries of the ſeuen churches, let vs receiue farther inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in the opening of the ſeuen ſeales, concerning thoſe things from the birth of our ſauiour, vnto the end of the world.</p>
                  <p>THe firſt ſeale being opened, is diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered the preaching of the Goſpell, and the victories of Chriſt, in ſubduing multitudes to his truth. <hi>I beheld, and loe there was a while horſe, and he that ſate on him had a bow, and a crowne was giuen vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Reu. 6, 1.2.</note> 
                     <hi>and he went out conquering that he might ouercome.</hi> Hereof ſpeakes that princely prophet <hi>Dauid,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 45.</note> Good lucke haue thou with thine honour, ride on, becauſe of the word of truth, of meeke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,
<pb facs="tcp:19647:66"/> and righteouſneſſe, thine arrowes are verie ſharpe, and the people ſhal be ſubdued vnto thee euen in the middeſt among the kings enemies, thy ſeal (O God) endureth for euer, the ſcepter of thy kingdome is a right ſcepter.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">1.</note>The ſecond ſeale being opened; the bloudie perſecutions of the Idolaters, Romane Emperors, and in Gods iuſtice, theſe cruell warres, and bloudie deaths are prefigured in theſe words; <hi>And there went out another horſe that was red, and power was giuen vnto him that ſate there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to take peace from the earth,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">3.</note> 
                     <hi>and there was giuen vnto him a great ſword.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The third ſeale being opened, the darkeneſſe, ignorance and hereſies, the famine both ſpirituall and temporall was diſcouered, that horrible perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and warres ſhould bring into the world, in theſe wordes; <hi>I beheld, and loe a blacke horſe, and he that ſate thereon had a balance in his hand, ſaying, A mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of wheat for a penny, and a meaſure of barlie for a penny, and oyle and wine thou ſhalt not hurt.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">5.6.</note>
                  </p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19647:66"/>
                  <p>Notwithſtanding all the perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, hereſies and ſcarſitie both of true teachers and of true doctrine in the church, yet the ſpirituall wine and oyle, being the old and new teſtament, (the law and the Goſpell) were preſerued and vncorrupt as you heare, this is the wine and oyle that the good Samari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tane poured into the wound, which he thereby both clenſed and cured: this wine of the law ſearcheth our infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and this oyle of the goſpell is the oyle of gladneſſe, wherewith we be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed that be the true members of Chriſt. It is the oyle that in the lamp of our ſoules kindleth and continueth the light of our faith. This oyle the fiue wiſe virgins were furniſhed with, and the fiue fooliſh wanted; and it is the oile and the vnction that ſupplies our vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding.<note place="margin">1. Ioh. 2.20, 27.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>The fourth ſeale manifeſted the Romiſh <hi>Ieſabel,</hi> and the perſecuting church of Rome, by paleneſſe preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding whiteneſſe, by hypocriſie preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding pietie, ſpreading his authoritie
<pb facs="tcp:19647:67"/> ouer the earth, and deſtroying many, ſome with the ſword, others with ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall hunger, others with ſpirituall death, &amp;c. expreſſed by theſe wordes; <hi>And behold, a pale horſe, and his name that ſate thereon was death, and hell followed after him, and power was giuen vnto him ouer the fourth part of the earth, to kill with the ſword,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Reu. 6, 8.</note> 
                     <hi>with hunger, and with death.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The fift ſeale being opened, appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the ſoules of them that were killed for the teſtimonie of the truth, requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring iuſtice at the hands of God for their bloud, but it was ſaid vnto them, that they ſhould reſt a little while, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till their fellow ſeruantes were alſo killed.</p>
                  <p>The ſixt ſeale being opened, the iudgement of God vpon the perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of his chuch, the horror of their conſcience, and the anguiſh of their mindes, was declared in theſe wordes; <hi>And the kings of the earth, and the great men hid themſelues in dens and among the rocks, ſaying, Rocks fal on vs, and hide vs
<pb facs="tcp:19647:67"/> from the preſence of him that ſitteth vpon the throne.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">12.13.14.15.16.17.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>The ſeuenth ſeale being opened, prefigured the beginning of aeternall reſt.</p>
                  <p>Now marke what the holy Ghoſt diſcouereth vpon the ſound of the ſeuen trumpets,<note place="margin">Reu. 8,</note> it makes plaine all that was betweene the birth of Chriſt, and the end of the world.</p>
                  <p>THe firſt and ſecond trumpet hath relation and ſit cohaerence to the church of Epheſus, and the church of Smirma, and to the opening of the firſt and ſecond ſeale, that is to ſay, to the firſt 300 yeares after Chriſt. The euent demonſtrated is firſt the perſecution of the church, by the Romane Emperours, whoſe cruelties were ſo ſharpe &amp; blou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, that they are repreſented by the tearmes of haile and fire mingled with bloud: this ſtorme of perſecution fell vpon Chriſts husbandrie, ſo that the third part of the trees, that is to ſay, the third part of the people, and all the
<pb facs="tcp:19647:68"/> greene graſſe, meaning the miniſters bedued with ſpirituall grace, yeelding plentie of food vnto their flocke, were burnt vp and conſumed. The iuſtice of God vpon theſe perſecutors, in affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting them with horrible warres, which like a great mountaine burning like fire, was caſt into the turbulent ſea of their tumultuous eſtate, ſo that the third part of their dominions was repleniſhed with bloud-ſhead, the third part of their ſubiects ſlaine, and the third part of their prouinces, cities, and gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, which are reſembled to ſhippes ſayling vpon the ſea of that Empire, was deſtroyed.</p>
                  <p>The third Trumpet is anſwerable to the church of Pergamus, and to the opening of the third ſeale, repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the time from 300 yeares after Chriſt, till the yeares 640. Superſtition and idolatrie, the doctrine of <hi>Balaam,</hi> and ſcandalous endeuours of <hi>Balac,</hi> the blacke horſe of darkeneſſe, ignorance and famine of Gods word, began then to take roote. And before the end of
<pb facs="tcp:19647:68"/> thoſe yeares, as this trumpet declareth, a great ſtarre no leſſe than the Biſhop of Rome, fel from heauen burning like a torch, and it fell into the third part of the riuers, that is, into the third part of the doctrine of the church, and into the fountaine of waters, that is, into the principall points of religion. And the name of the ſtarre is called Worme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood, or Corruption; and the third part of the waters became as worme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood, that is, corrupt and falſe do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine</p>
                  <p>The fourth trumpet, according to the times of the church of Thiatira, and the opening of the fourth ſeale, that is, from the yeare of our Lord 640, to the yeare 980. In this time the Romiſh <hi>Ieſabel</hi> had taken heart and deceiued the children of God, and made them commit ſpirituall fornication. In theſe times the pale horſe of the hypocritical church of Rome was farre onward on his race, carrying Death vpon his back, and haling hell after him, hauing power ouer the fourth part of the earth, and
<pb facs="tcp:19647:69"/> killing with the ſword, with famine, and with death, no maruell then if this trumpet telleth vs, In thoſe daies the third part of the ſun, that is, the Euange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licall light; and the third part of the moone, that is, of the church, which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiueth all her light of Gods word; and the third part of the ſtarres, that is, of the paſtours and miniſters, were dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned; and the day was ſmitten, that is, the doctrine both of the goſpel, and of the law, was ſo darkened and ſo corrupted, that they wanted the light wherewith they ſhould haue illuminated their mindes.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Reu. 9, 1.2.3.</note>The fift trumpet agreeth with the times and ſtate of the church of Sardie, and with the opening of the fift ſeale. In the ending of the period of yeares of the church of Sardie, at the which An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techriſt was growne to his full great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and had ſet vp by publicke order the adoration of the ſacrament, and thereby brought in an idoll to be wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped as God, which was decreed at the councell of <hi>Laterane,</hi> the yeare
<pb facs="tcp:19647:69"/> of our Lord 1315, and within ſeuen or eight yeares after, no doubt gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally receiued in the churches of Chriſtendome, we ſee the wordes of <hi>Daniell</hi> perfourmed taking his daies for yeares, and from the time that the dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſacrifice ſhalbe taken away (which was aboliſhed at Chriſts paſsion) the idoll or deſolation ſet vp, there ſhall be 1290 daies, which pointeth to the yeare 1323. The next verſe hath relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the beginning of the times of the church of Philodelphia, when as the truth began to be taught, bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed is he that waiteth and commeth to 1335 dayes. That extreame pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution of the ſpirituall temple was ſuch as it hath an alogie with the vtter de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of the temple at Ieruſalem, by <hi>Vaſpatian</hi> and <hi>Titus.</hi> It was prefigured in the yeare and halfe, and odde daies of <hi>Antiochus</hi> horrible tiranny in Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, from the fourth yeare and ſome moneths more of his raigne, whereas he cauſed the law of <hi>Moſes</hi> to be abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed, the ſacrifices to ceaſe, the temple
<pb facs="tcp:19647:70"/> to be defiled, the abhominable idol of <hi>Iupiter Olimpius,</hi> to be worſhipped for the ſpace of 1290 daies, till the eight yeare that <hi>Iudas Machabeus</hi> clenſed the temple, and decked it with crownes and ſhields of Gold, a figure of Chriſt Ieſus. The time of extreame darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and tyranny of Antechriſt, by <hi>Achab</hi> and <hi>Ieſabell,</hi> had <hi>Elias</hi> been of this age, he would haue ſo cried out as he did then; but God would haue an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, I haue a few names in Sardie that haue not defiled their garments. The ſeale opened openeth vnto vs, that in this age the ſoules of the Martirs cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth for vengance at the hands of God, who loſt their liues for the truths ſake, and for that they would not embrace falſhood. But it was told them that they ſhould reſt till the number of their bretheren were fulfilled, who ſhould alſo be ſlaine by Antechriſt. This trumpet telleth vs, He had gotten the key of the bottomeleſſe pit and opened the gulfe of hell, and hence produced an innumerable companie of Locuſts,
<pb facs="tcp:19647:70"/> that is to ſay, of friers, monkes, and ſuch like, the ſmoke of whoſe errors darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the bright ſunne of the Goſpell, and the aire of mens minds, but theſe haue not power ouer Gods elect.</p>
                  <p>The ſixt trumpet comprehendeth the times of the church of Philodel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phia, and the opening of the ſixt ſeale,<note place="margin">Reu. 9, 8.</note> in theſe the goſpell is preached, the Babylonians fallen, the ſynagogue of ſathan ſhalbe ſubdued, the elect of God are ſealed, Antechriſt with his kings &amp; confederates ſhalbe aſtoniſhed. At the iudgement of God, they ſhall crie, Mountaines fall vpon vs. This trumpet ſheweth, that not onely the ſpirituall temple ſhall be re-edified by the true <hi>Zorobabel,</hi> Ieſus Chriſt, and the goſpel preached generally, but alſo many par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars touching the ſame, which (to auoid tediouſneſſe) I muſt leaue.</p>
                  <p>The ſeuenth trumpet is agreeable to the euent of the church of Laodicia,<note place="margin">Reu. 5, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> whom the Lord (as ſoone as he ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth) will ſpew out of his mouth. It hath reſemblance to the opening of the
<pb facs="tcp:19647:71"/> ſeuenth ſeale, which doth intimate vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs the euerlaſting ſabaoth and reſt, for a mightie angell lifted vp his hand to heauen, and ſware by him that li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth for euermore, which created all things, that Time ſhould be no more, but in the daies of the voice of the ſeuenth angell, when he ſhall begin to blow the tru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pet. And there were great voices in heauen ſaying, The kingdome of this world are our Lords, and his Chriſt, and he ſhall raigne for euer. Then the 24 elders which ſate before God, fell vpon their faces, and worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped God ſaying, We giue thee thanks O Lord God almightie, &amp;c.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="introduction">
               <pb facs="tcp:19647:71"/>
               <head>The fift Introduction.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Ou ſhall doe well to obſerue this order, and thereby you may be able to vnfold hard and intricate places, and to expound all ſuch parts or parcell of the ſcripture, as doe come in queſtion doubtfully.</p>
               <p>The fiue books of <hi>Moſes</hi> and the foure Euangeliſts doe comprehend ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally and moſt principally the rules of iuſtice, diſcerning betwixt good and euill, which was in the beginning graf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the ſoules of our firſt parents, and afterwards in writing, that we might the better know our creator, and our ſelues, with threats reſtraining vs from euill, and with promiſes perſuading vs to vertue; which bookes in my method were called Laegall.</p>
               <p>The twelue next books that are in the old, and the acts in the new, doth comprehend all thoſe things that were either famouſly done or famouſly ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
<pb facs="tcp:19647:72"/> in good or euil, called hiſtorical. For the reading and ſpeedy vnderſtanding thereof, you muſt learne by heart theſe three particulars.</p>
               <list>
                  <head>Principall,</head>
                  <item>1 Times.</item>
                  <item>2 Places.</item>
                  <item>3 Perſons.</item>
               </list>
               <p>If Time,
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Whether</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>Paſt.</item>
                           <item>Preſent.</item>
                           <item>To come.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>If place,
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Whether</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>For warre.</item>
                           <item>For religion.</item>
                           <item>For worldly affaires.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>If perſons,
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>VVhether</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>Politicke.</item>
                           <item>Religious.</item>
                           <item>Publique.</item>
                           <item>Priuate.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="introduction">
               <pb facs="tcp:19647:72"/>
               <head>The ſixt Jntroduction.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Heſe books following next in order, to weet <hi>Iob, Pſal. Pro. Eccleſiaſtes, Cant.</hi> 14 Epiſtles of S. <hi>Paule,</hi> and ſeuen other being catholicall Epiſtles, doe compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend the wiſdome of God for the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of euerie member of Chriſt, particularly, as occaſion by time and place is offred. They are called Sapien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall, which are thus to be vnderſtood.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1 Conſider the chapter or verſes going before or following after any ſuch matter taken in hand, you ſhall finde that it helpeth much.</item>
                  <item>2 By ſome quotation oppoſite in the margent.</item>
                  <item>3 By ſome notes after this ſort mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked as a ſtarre * at the beginning of ſome verſes, and ſometimes at the end, the one expounds the
<pb facs="tcp:19647:73"/> other, if you compare them.</item>
                  <item>4 By theſe notes ¶ ſhewing the end of one matter, and the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of an other.</item>
                  <item>5 Theſe notes ‖ at the end, in the middle, or in the beginning, poin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth you to the margent for ſome ſhort definition of wordes, deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of places, or aetymolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie of names.</item>
                  <item>6 To what Parable, miracle, or hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorie, that doe pertaine which you haue in hand.</item>
                  <item>7 The time, whether houres, daies, weekes, moneths, or yeares, night, or day, ſunday, or holyday. Confer it with the like els where, by marking what was done.</item>
                  <item>8 If there be any thing ſpoken of God the creator, as of his head, his arme, his hand, or any part of his body, &amp;c. By the head you muſt vnderſtand his principalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, or gouernment; by the arme, his ſtrength; by the hand, his gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing and helping, and ſo through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb facs="tcp:19647:73"/> the reſt of his members, na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in ſcripture.</item>
                  <item>The like is to be conſidered of all other creatures bearing life, which are vſed in ſcriptures, for the better explaining of hard pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. You are verie carefullie to conſider the nature and proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of euerie ſuch thing, and then make your compariſon by a ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall application.</item>
                  <item>9 If there be a ſpeech of the quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titie, length, breadth, height, depth, &amp;c. or of the qualitie, as hard, ſoft, bitter, ſweet, gentle, curriſh.</item>
                  <item>10 If there be any thing ſpoken in one place that is not to be leueld and made plaine in another, then take it not literally, you muſt ſeeke for ſome other ſence.</item>
                  <item>11 If it be ſpoken by ſimilitude, phraſe, compariſon, figure, para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, &amp;c. then goe no further, the interpretation thereof is eaſie,
<pb facs="tcp:19647:74"/> marking well their manners, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties and kinde.</item>
                  <item>12 If there bemention made of theſe numbers 3, 4, 6, 7, 10, 12, the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter adioyning will ſhew you whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be good or euill; then com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare euerie ſuch mumber with the like.</item>
                  <item>If there be any thing of faith, of religion, of life and conuerſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, then compare it with the like els where.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="introduction">
               <head>The ſeuenth Introduction.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He ſixteene Prophets, and the Reuelation, compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hendeth great and nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble things, paſt, preſent, and to come; in reading whereof marke well theſe that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, called Propheticall.</p>
               <p n="1">1 Vnder what king in Iſrael or in Iudah, any ſuch prophet did liue, one
<pb facs="tcp:19647:74"/> or more, good, or euil.</p>
               <p n="2">2 What were the manners of the people and their religion, vnder ſuch and ſuch a king; compare it with the doctrine of that Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet.</p>
               <p n="3">3 Whether ſuch a propheſie were before the captiuitie, or after.</p>
               <p n="4">4 Whether it were before the incarnation of Chriſt, or after.</p>
               <p>Compare the books of the kings with the obſeruation or the former in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tion, with the books of the prophets, and you ſhall thereby make plaine the one by the other, for you ſhall find that the prophets did apply their doctrine according to their manners, where they had to doe.</p>
               <p>The firſt and ſecond of <hi>Chro.</hi> will ſerue verie well for the interpretation of the prophets, becauſe it doth enlarge many things ſpoken in the books of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muell</hi> and Kings.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="introduction">
               <pb facs="tcp:19647:75"/>
               <head>The eight Introduction.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hus I haue aduiſedly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered and briefly diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed few principall places, how you ſhall after ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſort make interpretation of holy ſcripture, particularly by applying or comparing the old Teſtament with the new, or the new with the old: you muſt be very perfect in them, and then make diligent examination which of them ſhall happen to be in any one place that you haue to vſe for the time.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:19647:75"/>
               <p>Conſider whether the ſcripture that you haue in hand be ſet foorth by
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Commaundement.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Promiſe.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Ceremonie.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Type or figure.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Propheſie.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Similitude.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Example.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Phraſe.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Contradiction.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Parrable.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Miracle.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Allegorie.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Sacrifice.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Sacrament.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Leaſt you ſhould miſſe by taking one for another, I haue verie briefly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed and laid you downe their plaine definition, with examples.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:19647:76"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Commaundement</hi> Is an impoſition, a charging, willing, or requiring of a man fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his owne wil, ſeeme it neuer ſo good, to the accompliſhment and doing of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mans wil. And the Lord comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the man ſaying;<note place="margin">Gen. 2, 16.</note> Thou ſhalt eat freely, but of the tree of knowledge of good and euill thou ſhalt not eat.<note place="margin">17.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Promiſe</hi> Is to aſſume, to vndertake, to couenant, to indent, bargaine, and agree, is all one thing, and to one ſence.</p>
               <p>If thou wilt obay diligently the voice of the Lord, then the Lord wil ſet thee on high, aboue all nations, and theſe bleſsings ſhall fall on thee,<note place="margin">Deut. 28, 1.2.3.4.</note> Bleſſed in the citie, and bleſſed in the field. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ceremonie</hi> Is an order, a conſtitution, diſpoſition, rite, an element, or tradition. It is an out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward repreſenting vnder a materiall and earthly thing, an infallible matter
<pb facs="tcp:19647:76"/> tending to religion and the ſeruice of God, vrged and commaunded by the greateſt of power, as time, place, or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon doth require, hauing an end, as</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Circumciſion</hi> Being the outward cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the foreskin of the fleſh, repreſenteth the mortification of carnall and earthly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections and luſts, and the quickning of the ſpirit. This had an end by Baptiſme, which is alſo a ceremonie, and hath an end at the ſecond comming of Chriſt.<note place="margin">Gen. 7, 10.11.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tipe, or figure</hi> Is that which can be referred neither to religion, to man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, nor to truth. If it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand any wicked thing, or doe forbid any good thing, then it is a type or a figure. When it may be taken two manner of waies, one way to good,<note place="margin">Gen. 9, 26, 14, 8. Haeb. 7, 1. to 15. Gen. 12, 1. to 18.22, to 19. 2. Cor. 12, 4.</note> and another way to euill, then is it a type or figure.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sem</hi> or <hi>Melchiſedech</hi> was a perfect fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure or type of Chriſt Ieſus, both con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning his kingdome and prieſthood.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:19647:77"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Propheſie</hi> Is a diuining, foretelling, an interpreting, an exorting, or aedifying.<note place="margin">Exod. 7, 1.2. 1. Cor. 14.3.4 1. Theſſ. 5, 20. Eze. 13, 1.39, 1.2.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Sonne of man propheſie againſt the prophets of Iſrael, and ſay vnto them, that propheſie out of their owne hearts thus ſaith the Lord.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Similitude</hi> Is that which beares a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblance, proportion, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion, likeneſſe, ſhew, diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, or more plaine manifeſtation of another matter. A ſimilitude is not the ſame in euerie particular as that which was likened vnto it, but it is ſufficient if it be like in one. Similitudes are neuer ſet out to confirme or confute, but to adorne or to make a matter more plain; and it is euermore inferiour to the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in hand, as for example:</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 144.</note>Man is like a thing of nought, things of nought worth are ſtill throwne out, caſt away, not ſit for any good purpoſe, therefore to be caſt out, reiected, and
<pb facs="tcp:19647:77"/> troden vnder feet; ſo is man as a thing of nought.</p>
               <p>My beloued is like a Roe or a yoong Hart.<note place="margin">Cant. 2, 9.</note> Here you muſt conſider the qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie of a Roe or a yoong Hart, then you ſhall ſee what the beloued of Chriſt is.</p>
               <p>Like the lillie among the thornes,<note place="margin">Cant. 2, 2. Luk. 13.19.21. Math. 20, 1.2.</note> ſo is my loue among the children of men.</p>
               <p>Like the graine of muſtard ſeed; to leuen; to vineyard; ſo is the church.</p>
               <p>Marke well the particulars or the ſundrie propertie, qualitie, condition, or effect of euerie ſimilitude, then apply it to this or that thing, or to that mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and you ſhall be greatly delighted, and enlightned.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Example</hi> Is a matter like in effect, though not in ſubſtance. It is the confirmation of another matter whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it hath the ſelfe ſame ſence, although not the ſelfe ſame wordes. It is well ſaid to be a fit example, when a like matter being generall doth proue a particular. An example is a matter done and extant in print and in writing.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:19647:78"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Enſample</hi> Is that which we ſee with our eyes daily in the worke of God, or conuerſations of men, which is not printed or written. It is an enſample when we ourſelues can witneſſe the ſeeing of it, and the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of it. An Example is that which hath an end or purpoſe either to exhort, or to dehort from ſome thing, and ſo is an Enſample.</p>
               <p>The drowning of <hi>Pharao</hi> in the ſea, was an example of Gods iuſtice againſt obſtinate ſinners,<note place="margin">Exo. 14.21.</note> perſecuting the godly, and reſiſting the will of God.</p>
               <p>The falling of the tower of Siloh, was an example that others ſhould take heed.<note place="margin">Luke 13, 4.</note>
               </p>
               <p>The deſtruction of the cities of So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and Gomorrah,<note place="margin">Gen. 19, 23.</note> was an example that we ſhould not delight in ſinne.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Phraſes</hi> The holy Ghoſt for our bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter capacitie and vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, vſeth to ſpeake and to deliuer great and waightie matters af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a phraſe or common ſpeech, vſed in
<pb facs="tcp:19647:78"/> the world among ordinary men, as thus;</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nathan</hi> ſaid to <hi>Saule,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Sam. 15.</note> The Lord hath caſt thee away: meaning thereby, as men doe caſt away things of nought, things good for nothing, ſo God hath reiected and caſt him off, he hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen him ouer as a thing nought worth. Men ſay of baſe and ſimple things, We will caſt it away.</p>
               <p>Let not ſinne raigne in your mortall bodies; meaning by kings gouernement,<note place="margin">Rom. 6, 12.</note> that ſinne ſhould not gouerne nor haue dominio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ouer vs. To raigne, to rule, and to haue dominion, is a common ſpeech or phraſe that is vſed for them that haue gotten the vpper hand, the maſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, and the authoritie, to commaund others.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Difficultie</hi> or <hi>Contradiction</hi> Is when one place croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth another, by a contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie letter or ſence, thus:</p>
               <p>The male in whome the fore-skin is not circumciſed ſhall be cut off from the people.<note place="margin">Gen. 17.</note>
               </p>
               <p>If you be circumciſed, Chriſt ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:19647:79"/> not profite you to ſaluation.<note place="margin">Gal. 5.</note> This is a contrarie to the former in letter, one place croſſeth or gainſayeth another.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Exod. 20,</note>Honor thy father and thy mother.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Luke. 14,</note>If a man will come vnto me, he muſt forſake father and mother. This is a contrarie in ſence.</p>
               <p>God is not contrarie to himſelfe, which ſeems here by the letter, nor ſo abhorring the lawes of nature, as to commaund a man to forſake his father and mother that nouriſhed him vp. &amp;c. But by way of companion, forſake fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and mother, yea, life and all, rather than God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Parable</hi> Is a wiſe, a hidden, a ſecreat, and a darke ſaying, vnder earthly things to ſet forth hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly.<note place="margin">Pro. 1, 6.</note> Parrable hath many things in it to be conſidered of neceſsitie. Chriſt ſpeaks to the wicked by parables, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe in hearing they ſhould not heare, and in reading they ſhould not vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand;<note place="margin">Mar. 4, 31.</note> he makes al plaine to his diſciples.</p>
               <p>Chriſt ſpake in a parrable of a Sower,
<pb facs="tcp:19647:79"/> 
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 13, 3. another 24.25. another 31. another 33. <hi>Mar.</hi> 23. to 28. A certaine man had a figge tree planted in his vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard. <hi>Luke</hi> 13, 6.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Miracles</hi> Is a wonder, a ſtrange action, things applyed and turned cleane contrarie to their courſe and nature, as water turned to wine. Things onely perfourmed by the power of God.</p>
               <p>Miracles perfourmed by <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> at Gods commaundement.<note place="margin">Iohn 2, 1. Exo. 4, 1.2.</note>
               </p>
               <p>The Lord did theſe great miracles,<note place="margin">Ioſ. 24.17.18.</note> in the ſight of the people.</p>
               <p>Chriſt healeth incurable diſeaſes,<note place="margin">Ioh. 5. Mat. 8.9, 11.</note> he fedde many with little.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Allegorie</hi> Is one thing pretending in <hi>wordes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioh. 6.1.</note> another in <hi>ſence,</hi> ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the old, or in the new Teſtament.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Allegorie in wordes.</label>Now is the axe laid to the roote of the tree, euerie tree that bringeth not foorth good fruite, &amp;c.<note place="margin">Mat. 3, 10.</note>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:19647:80"/>
               <p>
                  <label>Allegorie in ſence.</label>The ſence and meaning is, that they ſhould vſe the time and take the oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunitie of repentance, and faith in Chriſt, leaſt ſuddenly they ſhould be deſtroyed.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Words.</label>The harueſt is great, and the labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers are but few,</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Sence and meaning.</label>There are few good magiſtrates in the church.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sacrifice</hi> is an oblation, and offering, or a giuing of praiſe, powring of praiers vnto God.<note place="margin">Exo. 8, 25.</note> It is a men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, a relation or prognoſtication of great and holy things to come.</p>
               <p>Sacrifices are of diuers ſorts, and of the beſt and fineſt creatures, repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting holineſſe.<note place="margin">Leuit. 1, 2, 3, 4, 5.6, 7, Pſal. 4, 51. 2. Pet. 2, 1.2.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sacrament</hi> Is a mention and plaine de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration of holy things alreadie come and in hand. It is a manifeſt aſſurance of Sanctificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb facs="tcp:19647:80"/> and redemption in Chriſt, ſo farre as by any earthly creature may be repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented, or related, which may not be vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on policie, or kingly ordinance, but vpon the ordinance and commaundement of the hieſt, and that without adding or di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſhing. Wherof there were but two in the time of the law of <hi>Moſes;</hi> and other two aboliſhing them now in the time of the Goſpell, which are theſe.</p>
               <p>And as they did eat, Ieſus tooke bread, and when he had giuen thanks,<note place="margin">Mat. 26.26</note> he brake it and ſaid, Take eat, this is my bodie.</p>
               <p>Alſo he tooke the cup,<note place="margin">27. Mar 14, 22. Luk. 22, 19. 1. Cor. 11.24.</note> and when he had giuen thankes, he gaue it them ſaying, Drinke yee all of this, for this is the blood of the new Teſtament. &amp;c.</p>
               <p>And Ieſus when he was baptized, came ſtraight way out of the water, and the heauens were opened, and <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaw the ſpirit of God deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb facs="tcp:19647:81"/> like a Doue, and lighting vpon him.<note place="margin">Mat. 3, 16.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Goe ye into the world, and preach the Goſpell, baptizing them in the name of the Father,<note place="margin">Mat. 28, 19.</note> the Sonne, and the holy Ghoſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="introduction">
               <head>The ninth Introduction.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat you may the better make good and perfect vſe of the former inuention, and places of ſpeciall ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, conſider well and learne by heart theſe that follow, in manner and forme as I haue ſet them downe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:19647:81"/>
               <list>
                  <head>If a Commaundement.</head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>1 Who commaunds,</hi> Whether God or man.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>2 Who is commanded,</hi> All or ſome, publike, or priuat.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>3 What is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded,</hi> Things pertaniing to God, or man.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>4 To what end.</hi> To Gods glorie, or to mans commoditie.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>If a Promiſe,</head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>1 Who promiſeth,</hi> Whether God, or men of power.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>2 What is promiſed,</hi> Temporall things, or ſpirituall.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>3 To whom it is made,</hi> To ſuch as are in authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, or to all generall.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>If Allegorie,</head>
                  <item>Then ſee</item>
                  <item>
                     <list>
                        <item>1 What is pretended in words.</item>
                        <item>2 What is intended in Sence.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <pb facs="tcp:19647:82"/>
               <list>
                  <head>If Propheſie,</head>
                  <item>Then conſider</item>
                  <item>
                     <list>
                        <item>1 What Prophet.</item>
                        <item>2 What propheſie.</item>
                        <item>3 Vnder what king.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>If Similitude,</head>
                  <item>1 The nature and qualitie of that earthly thing which beares the ſimilitude particularly.</item>
                  <item>2 To what it is likened, to God, or to good men; to the Deuill, or to wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked men.</item>
                  <item>3 To what part of the ſimilitude the thing likened doth agree.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>If Example,</head>
                  <item>1 Whether the matter be good or euill.</item>
                  <item>2 For what cauſe it was ſo done.</item>
                  <item>3 For whoſe ſake and Example it was</item>
               </list>
               <pb facs="tcp:19647:82"/>
               <list>
                  <head>If Phraſe.</head>
                  <item>1 Whence the phraſe is deriued.</item>
                  <item>2 The meaning of the holy Ghoſt.</item>
                  <item>3 Whether in the law, or in the goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell.</item>
                  <item>4 Whether for good or for euill.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>If difficultie or contradiction.</head>
                  <item>1 Whether contrarie in letter or in ſence.</item>
                  <item>2 The words before and after.</item>
                  <item>3 The manner of doing or ſpeaking.</item>
                  <item>4 The time when it was.</item>
                  <item>5 The place where it was.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>If Parable.</head>
                  <item>1 What the matter or ſubiect is, in the nature and qualitie thereof.</item>
                  <item>2 What the ſpirituall matter is.</item>
                  <item>3 Why it was ſpoken in Parables.</item>
                  <item>4 When it was ſpoken.</item>
               </list>
               <pb facs="tcp:19647:83"/>
               <list>
                  <head>If Miracle,</head>
                  <item>1 The perſon who wrought it.</item>
                  <item>2 For whoſe ſake.</item>
                  <item>3 Before whom.</item>
                  <item>4 To what end.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>If Allegorie,</head>
                  <item>1 What the words are.</item>
                  <item>2 What the ſence is.</item>
                  <item>3 Whether in the old or in the new.</item>
                  <item>4 Who ſpeaks it.</item>
                  <item>5 To whom it was.</item>
               </list>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <head>If a Sacrifice,</head>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell rows="4">Whether it be</cell>
                        <cell>Praiſe, or of prayer.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>2</cell>
                        <cell>Of earthly things commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the law.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell>Of ſpirituall, commended in the Goſpell.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>4</cell>
                        <cell>The manner of it.</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:19647:83"/>
               <list>
                  <head>If a Sacrament.</head>
                  <item>1 Looke for a commandement.</item>
                  <item>2 The nature of the outward Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</item>
                  <item>3 The inward graces repreſented by it.</item>
                  <item>4 The promiſe of ſaluation.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Thus you ſhall examine and finde out a true ſacrament, from that which is imagined, for theſe foure muſt needs be in euerie perfect ſacrament.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="introduction">
               <pb facs="tcp:19647:84"/>
               <head>The tenth Introduction.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He concluſion of all arts and ſtudies doe conſiſt of three parts; to weer, Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, Noting, and Exerciſe.</p>
               <p>To the end you may make perfect vſe of your Reading, I haue thought good to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>poſe this order for your No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting; then (Gods ſpirit aſsiſting) your Exerciſe will be eaſie. The names or aetymologies of the twentie holy fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, of the twelue Patriarchs, of the twelue ſtandings or habitations where <hi>Iſrael</hi> pitched in their iourney from Aegypt to Canaan. You muſt digeſt in a writing booke of two quires, after the maner of common places: one of the ſame places or titles muſt be at the vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per end of euerie ſecond leafe in Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to; and be ſure to place nothing vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath but ſuch matter as the place and title requireth. And when you haue ſo gone ouer and written all your booke, then caſt it aſide, and take another after
<pb facs="tcp:19647:84"/> the ſame order, which being alſo fini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, compare it with the firſt, and you ſhall ſee your ſelfe much amended in skill. Thus doe once more in another booke, and then you ſhall be able rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily and roundly, to ſpeake artificial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and diuinely of all things neceſſarie to ſaluation, forgetting not the vſe and helpes of the introductions aforeſaid, one quarter of a yeare will profit you more than forty yeares reading, after the common and generall order.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1 You ſhall not read any parcell of ſcripture, but you may reduce them to ſome one of theſe.</item>
                  <item>2 It will ſharpen your conceipt and iudgement.</item>
                  <item>3 It will ſhew you what place is moſt principall and neceſſarie in euerie booke and chapter.</item>
                  <item>4 You ſhall know what matter be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs to Exhortatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Reprehenſion, Confirmation, Confutation, and Conſolation.</item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19647:85"/>
                  <item>5 You ſhall know what matter be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs to the firſt Table, and what to the ſecond.</item>
                  <item>6 Your memorie will be ſtaid, as in one ſight or view, wherby you ſhal haue in a readineſſe all things.</item>
               </list>
               <p>
                  <hi>You ſhall haue a briefe definition, or interpretation of euerie one oppoſite, leaſt you take one for another, or miſſe of the ſence.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <pb facs="tcp:19647:85"/>
                     <head>The names or aetymologies of the firſt ten Fathers.</head>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Earthly,</cell>
                        <cell> 
                           <hi>Vaniſhing, deſcending, ſubiect to decay, corruption.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Setled,</cell>
                        <cell> 
                           <hi>Conſtant, vnremoueable, perſuaded, reſolute, beleeuing, determined.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Sorrowfull,</cell>
                        <cell> 
                           <hi>Perplexed, vexed, greeued, hating, loathing, deteſting.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Godly repentance,</cell>
                        <cell> 
                           <hi>Sorie for ſinnes paſt, greeued for diſpleaſing of God, and not for any worldly loſſe or diſcontentment whatſoeuer.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Praiſe God,</cell>
                        <cell> 
                           <hi>That is to be content in all eſtates, to bleſſe God, to praiſe him, and to thanke him.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>The lowly,</cell>
                        <cell> 
                           <hi>Not to be puffed vp with worldly conceipts, nor to ſtand vpon our own me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, but in humilitie and lowlineſſe to expect after Chriſt.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>The Sabaoth keeper,</cell>
                        <cell> 
                           <hi>Is he that dedicateth his body and ſoule to ſpirituall contempla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion, and to the ſauing of needfull things.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Long life</cell>
                        <cell> 
                           <hi>All gifts temporall and ſpirituall is ſignified.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Heart wounded,</cell>
                        <cell> 
                           <hi>Moleſted with the tribulations and miſeries of the life.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>The Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</cell>
                        <cell> 
                           <hi>When all worldly helps faileth to the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, then there is helpe and comfort to the Godly in Chriſt.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <pb facs="tcp:19647:86"/>
                     <head>The names or aetymologies of the ſecond ten Fathers.</head>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Renowned,</cell>
                        <cell> 
                           <hi>Famous, excellent, in good credit with good men, and with God.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Healing,</cell>
                        <cell> 
                           <hi>This is a cloſe narration of our clenſing, Healing, and reſtauration.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Peace,</cell>
                        <cell> 
                           <hi>Tranquillitie, reſt, ioy and Peace, quietneſſe and eaſe.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Pilgrime,</cell>
                        <cell> 
                           <hi>When we aſcend to God, we deſcend from our ſelues, and from all the pleaſures of this life: whence we are pilgrimes.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Deuided,</cell>
                        <cell> 
                           <hi>In the heat of our iournie to God, we are deuided, ſeparated, and ſequestred from father and friends &amp;c. to ſerue God.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Breaking</cell>
                        <cell> 
                           <hi>This ſhewes the parting, the cutting off and diſloialtie of the wicked, for want of faith and patience.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Palm-trees,</cell>
                        <cell> 
                           <hi>As the Palm-tree the more it is preſſed, the more it ſpringeth, euen ſo the godly, &amp;c.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Angrie, or drie,</cell>
                        <cell> 
                           <hi>The wicked is ſoon moued to wrath, &amp; ſo drie &amp; vnfruitfull.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Wretch,</cell>
                        <cell> 
                           <hi>The ſonne of ſuch a father hardly proueth valiant, euer he is wretched.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>High father,</cell>
                        <cell> 
                           <hi>That is, by a new begetting, new regeneration to be godly, and ſo in fauour.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <pb facs="tcp:19647:86"/>
                     <head>The names or aetymologies of the twelue Patriarches.</head>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Water,</cell>
                        <cell> 
                           <hi>Conſider the nature of Water is to waſh, to mollifie, to fructifie, to drowne or deſtroie, &amp;c. all is to one effect, and must be vnder one Title.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Sword,</cell>
                        <cell> 
                           <hi>Conſider the vſe thereof. Alſo it is to be taken for Crueltie, Jrefull.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Booke,</cell>
                        <cell> 
                           <hi>Jt hath relation to Learning, to Knowledge, Skill, Offices, &amp;c.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Lion,</cell>
                        <cell> 
                           <hi>Vnderſtand Courage, Valeant, Mightie, Kingly, Victorious, &amp;c.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Adder,</cell>
                        <cell> 
                           <hi>The qualitie: as to ſting, to hurt, to defile, to vex, &amp;c.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Hinde,</cell>
                        <cell> 
                           <hi>Swift, ſpeedie, flying, poaſting, and ſuch like beaſt.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Banner,</cell>
                        <cell> 
                           <hi>Warriors, fighters, weapons, armour.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Bread,</cell>
                        <cell> 
                           <hi>Food, apparell, and all ſuch things as belong to the backe, and to the bellie.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Aſſe,</cell>
                        <cell> 
                           <hi>Slouthfull, ſluggiſh, and ſuch like beasts.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Ship,</cell>
                        <cell> 
                           <hi>Seas-ſailing, ventring, fiſhes, Marchants.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Fruitful bough,</cell>
                        <cell> 
                           <hi>Proſperous, powerfull, encreaſing, ſpreading abroad.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Wolfe,</cell>
                        <cell> 
                           <hi>Extirping, rooting, and other beaſts of that nature.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <pb facs="tcp:19647:87"/>
                     <head>The names or aetymologies of the twelue Standings.</head>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Worms meat,</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell> Such are we in nature, and in bodily ſubſtance.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Poore Cottages,</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell> So are our habitations and continuance in this world.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Hard ground,</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell> So are our worldly commodities, hard and vnprofitable.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Bitterneſſe,</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell> After a little eaſe and reſt, we fall into diuers trials.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Strong harts,</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell> So God encourageth the weake and wearied, ſeeking him.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Thornie,</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell> The cares and pleaſures of this life and lets and hinderances.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Temptation,</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell> Riches and pleaſures are prouocations to ſinne.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Euerlaſting temptation,</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell> Hath the godly, and prouocations to ſinne.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Turning away,</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell> As Cerah and the reſt rebelled.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Declaring or ſhewing,</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell> This hath relation to Mountains.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Shadow of a portion,</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell> Riches, and ſuch like, are Portions.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>
                           <hi>Of the Father,</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell> To this you may refer Genealogies, kinred, or progenies.</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="sample_dialogue">
               <pb facs="tcp:19647:87"/>
               <head>An entrance to the anſwering of the three queſtions recited in the beginning of this booke.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Haue heard many men of diuers trades, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, and profeſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and ſome in the pariſh where I haue cure and charge, vſing ſpeeches deroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie to the credite, good eſtate, and proſperous continuance of Lawyers, Phiſitions, and of the Preachers of the word of God: the ple<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tie of which three ſortes of learned and honeſt profeſſors, are the manifeſt arguments of Gods moſt ſpeciall fauor towards his church: yet notwithſtanding, I perceiue they are neither liked nor loued of the ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant and enuious multitude; wherein they do ſo much as in them lieth, abuſe the means of their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort, &amp; reiect the graces of God which they daily pray for; yet whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they, by reaſon of their vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly
<pb facs="tcp:19647:88"/> or diſtemperate behauior, are brought to the hazard of their liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, their liuings, or their liues; then ſome of them maiſter and worſhip the Lawyer. Others being but a little ſicke, poſt and haſt their meſſengers to the Phiſitions, then they intreat them and entertaine them with diuers paiments &amp; promiſes. And ſome of them, though the ſmaller number, when their wils be made, and their ſoules bequeathed, ſend for the miniſter, vnto whom they then ſpeake faire, and crie God mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, I haue beene a ſinner, Maſter Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon pray forme: or words to like effect, I doubt me to ſmall purpoſe. Wherfore theſe things conſidered, I thinke it not amiſſe (good chriſtian Reader) to contriue their queſtions and my an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers Dialogue wiſe, as betweene the Paſtor and Pariſhioner, after this maner.</p>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19647:88"/>
                  <speaker>Pariſhioner.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hat is your opinion and iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Lawyers? They are men generally hated and ill reported, and as I thinke very iuſtly: for they doe by delaies and ſhifts in law, hinder and vndoe many.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Paſtor.</speaker>
                  <p>The lawes of this realme, made and ordained by policie and wiſdome, and maintained by authoritie, are ſaid to conſiſt of perfect reaſon, auntient cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome, yea and of the law of God; very perfectly pointing to euerie man his owne, as God hath limited out of the creation, leauing nothing common or vndeſpoſed, but the fiſhes of the ſea, the fowls of the ayre, and the beaſts of the wilderneſſe. And it hath his denomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <hi>Lex à Ligando,</hi> becauſe as a bond doth knit and hold many things toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and as of many links is made one
<pb facs="tcp:19647:89"/> chaine,<note place="margin">Eph. 4, 1.2.3. Exo. 28, 1.2.3.4.5.6.</note> and as by the ſinewes, our ioynts and parts of our naturall bodies are tied and bound together; euen ſo by law, the politicke body of a common weale, is vnited &amp; knit together as one, for the preſeruation of peace, in the profeſsion of one true euerliuing &amp; ouer-ruling Lord. It requireth in it ſelfe the captiuating of our owne wils, and obedience to the wil of the maker thereof, vpon pains and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalties enforcing the ſame. The lawes ſo conſidered, make difference betwixt right and wrong, betwixt good and euill men: the lawes of this Land, if they be duely and truely handled, haue that end and purpoſe as the law of Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie God, which is, to reduce men from ſauageneſſe to ciuilneſſe, from igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance to knowledge, and from vice to vertue;<note place="margin">Rom. 13, 3.4.</note> therefore S. <hi>Paule</hi> ſaid, Princes are nor fearefull, by their lawes, to them that doe good, but to them that doe euill. Wilt thou be without feare? doe well then: ſo ſhalt thou be praiſed, then is he the miniſter of God, for thy wealth: but he is the miniſter of God, to take
<pb facs="tcp:19647:89"/> vengeance on them that doe euill. Theſe our lawes are laudable, and very neere (for excellencie and ſinceritie) to the lawes of God, as doth partly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare by the definition thereof, <hi>Lex est ſanctio ſancta iubens honeſta &amp; prohibens contraria.</hi> The law is a holy ordinance commaunding good things, and forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the contrarie. Why then is it diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>praiſed? nay rather why is it not moſt highly commended, liked, and allowed?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pariſhioner.</speaker>
                  <p>All this that you haue ſaid of the law it ſelfe, I partly graunt, but what maketh this for the calling of Lawyers, and their practiſe, as Councellors, Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors, Attorneis, Proctors, Sollicitors, Petty-foggers, and ſuch like? there were no ſuch men allowed in the iudici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all lawes of God, euerie man was heard of the iudge to ſay what he could for hmſelfe, and why ſhould not our lawes haue that proceeding? Is there any matter ſo hard and intricate that the
<pb facs="tcp:19647:90"/> partie grieued cannot vtter it himſelfe, and where a cauſe being neuer ſo hard and tedious, might be ended within ten daies after the defendants aunſwere, it is now drawne to three or foure yeares handling, by the deceit, and for the lucre of Lawyers, vpon whom all the world crieth out with open mouth.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Paſtor.</speaker>
                  <p>It ſhould ſeeme you ſpeake of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, as wiſhing all things well, or of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treame malice being ſome way grieued by them: the beſt of both pleads you guiltie, in accuſing all for ſome. It was not ſo hard a matter for <hi>Moſes</hi> to iudge all Iſraell at the firſt by himſelfe, as it was afterwards to iudge them by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe and others, when <hi>Iethro</hi> councel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led him for his eaſe to chooſe many more helpers. And more tedious it is to determine all the cauſes moued by the ſubiects here in England, than it was for <hi>Moſes</hi> when he had moſt to doe in Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el for complaints,<note place="margin">Exod. 18, 13. to 23.</note> iniuries, and wrongs,
<pb facs="tcp:19647:90"/> are encreaſed, ſo that many hundreth iudges could not deliberatly heare and conſideratly determine all the cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes ariſing here, although the plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tife and defendant were ſuffered to ſpeake but tenne words a piece; where indeed, if they ſhould haue their allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, 2000 would not ſerue. Againe, ignorant and vnlearned men are not able to ſet forth or report to the iudge the points and truth of their owne cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. Beſides if they were, yet is not any iudge ſo exquiſite &amp; perfect in the laws, or any mans wit ſo pregnant, or memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie ſo ready, as vpon ſuch ſodaine, to mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter iuſtice to euerie man as his cauſe requireth: therefore learned lawyers, as Councellors, Doctors, Attorneis, and Proctors, are neceſſarie and fit men, to open, argue, and debate cauſes, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the iudge may ſee more clearely, who hath wrong, and who hath right, and be called to minde by their moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, what ſentence or iudgement is fit to be giuen betwixt them. And further, if the parties ſhould plead their owne
<pb facs="tcp:19647:91"/> cauſe, ſuch might be the skill and ſubtil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the wrong-doer, and the ſimpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie of him that deſireth redreſſe or recompence, the iudge being ignorant <hi>De veritate facti,</hi> for want of information might approue the wicked, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne the innocent: wherefore I ſay againe and againe, that Councellors, Doctors, Attorneis, Proctors, yea, and Sollicitors, and the officers vſed in and about the execution of law and iuſtice, are fit men, neceſſarie, and profitable in a Chriſtian common weale. But for a Petti-fogger, it is a word of diſdaine, I know no ſuch calling allowed in the law.</p>
                  <p>And whereas you ſpeake of delaies and ſhiftes vſed by lawyers, whereby they hinder and vndoe many; you muſt vnderſtand, that ſeeing the cauſes and ſutes in this land are many, as is aforſaid, and ſeeing there is a prioritie of one ſute before another, in regard of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mencement thereof, and therefore alſo muſt needs be a prioritie in the procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding therein, and likewiſe alſo in the hearing and determining of the ſame,
<pb facs="tcp:19647:91"/> euerie one being heard in his courſe, ſome competent and reaſonable time muſt therefore be allowed vnto euerie cauſe, for the continuance thereof. But if there be any that profeſſe the law, that are either ſo vnskilfull and vnlear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned that they cannot councell their clients for their beſt expedition, or ſo couetouſly bent, and ſo addicted to gaine and lucre, that they will for their owne benefite, protract and delay any mans cauſe, (as amongſt many, of what degree or calling ſoeuer, there are ſome bad) ſeeing there are others (God be thanked) a great many, that are conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onable and honeſt, and againe learned and wiſe; if any fall into the hands of the former vnlearned or vngodly law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yer, it is to be accounted his owne folly, for that he, when it was his owne ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to retaine whom he liſt, would make choice of ſuch a one, when he might as eaſily and with as ſmall coſt, haue had him that had bin learned and godly. But in deed commonly the fault is in the clients themſelues, who are ſo
<pb facs="tcp:19647:92"/> cruelly and ſpitefully bent, that what lawyer ſoeuer they haue, they will themſelues ſeeke infinite waies and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſes to delaie their ſutes, and to detaine their aduerſaries a long time in trouble and expence of law: inſomuch as I haue credibly heard of ſome, who knowing their cauſe to be vniuſt, and yet alſo knowing themſelues of wealth and abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie to exceed thoſe againſt whom they haue delt, and therefore meaning by reaſon of their wealth to ſuppreſſe the truth, and by long delaies ſo to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poueriſh their aduerſary, as they ſhould neuer be able to bring the cauſe to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, haue in the bitterneſſe of their heart, and in the heat of their furie, vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered theſe words; <hi>I will not leaue him worth a great. I will make him daunce the beggers galliard before I haue done with him,</hi> with ſuch other cruell and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian ſpeeches. And theſe and ſuch like minded men, for the better effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting of this their wicked intention, la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor and endeuour to ſeeke vnto them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues ſuch lawyers as will ſit their hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors:
<pb facs="tcp:19647:92"/> wherevpon if God for the harde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of their hearts, doe ſend them vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to to ſuch a one, then they haue their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire: if otherwiſe they light vpon ſuch a lawyer that will not fauour nor further that their extreame bitterneſſe and cruelty, then they themſelues partly by wrong informations giuen to their law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yer, and partly by other ſubtill and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret practiſes, find out the means to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay &amp; lengthen their ſuits, and to hold, detaine, and keepe both themſelues, and their aduerſaries, in long and tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous actions, to the poore mens great de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay and impoueriſhment, if not to their vtter vndoing. By means whereof, the law is euill ſpoken of, and the lawyers are ſlaundered, whereas indeed the law it ſelfe is good and holy, and may be well vſed, and ſo is by a great many of the profeſſours thereof; and when it is otherwiſe adminiſtred, the fault is not in the law, but in the practiſers thereof, that are defectiue either in learning or conſcience, but moſt commonly in the clients themſelues.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19647:93"/>
                  <speaker>Pariſhioner.</speaker>
                  <p>As you thought me to ſpeake ill of Lawyers vpon ſpleene onely, by reaſon of ſome grieuance receiued by or from ſome of them, ſo I thinke that you ſpeake well of Lawyers, by reaſon of ſome fauour or good done vnto you by ſome Lawyer, as partly it appears by the dedication of your booke. There were many better men, and greater in account, more likely to gratifie you than a Lawyer.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Paſtor.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Eſa. 15, 20.21.</note>As he that iuſtifieth the wicked, is ſubiect to woe, ſo he that condemneth the godly, is ſubiect to woe: as it is a ſinne to arrogate for him that deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth ill, ſo it is a ſinne to derogate from him that deſerueth well: you can not denie but all that I haue ſaid con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the law, and the profeſſours, generally is true. And whereas you
<pb facs="tcp:19647:93"/> ſeeme to charge me with ſome benefit paſt which makes me partiall, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe that euen he was the pleader, and that by his learning and paines (yea, without fee) he deliuered me from a greedy Informer, who through his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiltie and my ſimplicitie, had condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned me in a hundred marks more than I was worth: to which worſhipful Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yer I dedicate this my labour, think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it a ſufficient gratification, in that it pleaſeth him to patronize the ſame, and me alſo, who as a poore Doue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong Kites &amp; Crowes, am throwne in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the world into many dangers, and hard aduentures; whoſe loue and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full friendſhip towards me, I aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure my ſelfe, is ſealed and deliuered; whoſe readineſſe likewiſe to helpe all ſuch as are helpleſſe, if it be deſired, and whoſe vprightneſſe in his profeſsion to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards all, hath many yeares appeared. And ſhall I ſuffer this man to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure? no, no, I will not; no, he is not; no, if I, you, and 1000 more with vs, both tooke in hand to dimme that
<pb facs="tcp:19647:94"/> he hath done, the ſaincts in earth would praiſe him, and the angels in heauen would pray for him, that God might regard and reward him.</p>
                  <p>
                     <q>
                        <hi>Carpturum alios immaculatum eſſe oportet.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pariſhioner.</speaker>
                  <p>For my queſtion I reſt ſatisfied. Now therefore I pray you what is your opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion and iudgement of Phiſitions? they robbe men of their liuings, and ſpoile men of their liues; vnder the pretence of doing good, they heale few and kil many.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19647:94"/>
                  <speaker>Paſtor.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Hiſicke is a preſeruer of health,<note place="margin">Hipocrates De arte.</note> and the repulſer of ſickneſſes. Phiſicke is a put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting too, and a taking from; that is to ſay, It doth adde, encreaſe, ſtrengthen, and augment good blood; where it is decaied, by age, by imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of nature, by ſurfait, or by any other means howſoeuer: and it doth take away, cut off, kill, deſtroy, purge, or by ſome ſuch way, it doth diſcharge the body of that which is ouer &amp; aboue nature, as of chollor, rheume, corrupt blood, impoſtumes, &amp;c. The body of man is ſubiect to infinite diſeaſes, and therefore through the corruption therof, it is likened by the holy Ghoſt,<note place="margin">Eſa. 6, 4.</note> to a filthie clout, or the cloath of a menſtruous woman.<note place="margin">Exo 9.9.17, 2. King. 1, 2. 2. Cron. 11, 14.</note> It is ſubiect to the leproſie, to the plureſie, to the dropſie, to the frenſie, to the palſie, to the botch, to the canker, and to other infinit diſeaſes, which will ſoone infect, ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runne,
<pb facs="tcp:19647:95"/> and deſtroy the body, if it be not aided, maintained, ſupported, and defended by Phiſicke: whence our ſauiour Chriſt ſaid, The whole haue no need of the Phiſition; as well to confound the opinion of thoſe that truſted in their owne righteouſnes, as alſo to ſhew that it was a matter ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie &amp; requiſite,<note place="margin">Mat. 9, 22.</note> that he which was ſicke ſhould ſeeke to the Phiſition. Anſwerable to this,<note place="margin">Eccle. 38, 1. &amp;c.</note> 
                     <hi>Ieſus</hi> the grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>father, and <hi>Ieſus</hi> the nephew, gaue in commaundement highly to eſteeme, and reuerently to account of the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, with this great word, Honor, which indeed is a word of great digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and commonly yeelded to Lords of nobilitie. Honor (ſaith he) the Phiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, with that honor which is due vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, which is as much to ſay, He de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerueth to be honored, it doth pertaine vnto him; it is his right and his duetie to be had in aeſtimation, and to be reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renced, not becauſe it doth any way good vnto him, not that he hath any vſe of thy honour, reuerence, or ſeruice,
<pb facs="tcp:19647:95"/> but in reſpect of thy owne neceſsitie, for thine owne need; thou ſhalt haue continuall occaſion to vſe him, Honor therefore the Phiſition, becauſe of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsitie. And for another reaſon he is to be honored, becauſe the Lord hath cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated him, the Lord hath ordained and conſtituted him forthy ſake, and for thy good: as thou wilt not be found to neglect the good gifts, the good ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances of almightie God, Honor the Phiſition. A third reaſon enforceth this honor, to weet, his ſtudie, his cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and his profeſsion, which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth of God, his maieſtie hath crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted it, he it is that hath inſtituted and ordained it. If Phiſicke be not the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of Almightie God, I would faine know what vſe haue we of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe roots, hearbs, flowers, trees, plants, licours, and many other things, in beaſts, in foules, in fiſh, and creeping creatures, whoſe effects are verie ſtrange and wonderfull, all working the health and preſeruation of mans bodie? or were they created in vaine?
<pb facs="tcp:19647:96"/> we haue in our knowledge no other vſe of the Roſe, than the ſight, the ſappe, and the ſauour, yet it hath many other excellent vſes and effects, ſimple, or compounded. What ſhalbe done with the Toad, the Ant, the Adder, and ſuch ſmall things? all the creatures of God are good,<note place="margin">Gen. 1, 31.</note> as he himſelfe vereſieth, and as the proofe thereof plainely ſheweth. They are to be vſed in their ſeaſon, and to be taken in their kinde, ſo ſhall we haue vſe and comfort by them. <hi>Luke</hi> the Euangeliſt, was a Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition in Antioch, whom Chriſt would not haue accounted, much leſſe appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for an Apoſtle, if his profeſsion had not beene lawfull and neceſſarie. And why ſhal I ſtand colouring of pure Corrall? or preſeruing of pure Ciuet, that will neuer leeſe his ſauour? as the one will not receiue to it, and the other will not leeſe from it; euen ſo Phiſicke is ſo exquiſitely excellent, that it need not haue any counterfait helpe: and the other haue their commiſsion ſo lawfull, that they cannot be condemned, nor
<pb facs="tcp:19647:96"/> iuſtly diſdained. Nature and Neceſsitie are two handmaids that attend vpon Phiſitions, the one enforced to ſeeke their helpe, the other inforced to yeeld the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their guerdon &amp; reward. As it is to be proued by Gods word, damnable ſin for a man to kill himſelfe with fire, wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, ſword, or with ſuch like; ſo is it ſinne for a man to deſtroy himſelfe in not ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king after Phiſitions and Chirurgions, when time and opportunitie is offred for recouery. As men may be too care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in ſeeking after Phiſitions to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moue the diſeaſes of their bodies: ſo may they be too too careleſſe in ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king after Chriſt, to remoue the ſinnes of their ſoules. Whence comes all ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of infirmities and diſeaſes of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die? comes it not from the ſinnes of the ſoule? All the inconueniences, dangers,<note place="margin">Pro. 18, 7. Iere. 26, 19. Eze. 18, 4. Mat. 17, 26.</note> miſeries, troubles, and wretchedneſſe whatſoeuer vpon the body, comes as a puniſhment for the ſinne of the ſoule. Thence comes the originall, thence comes the cauſe. A good Phiſition or Surgion will firſt remoue the cauſe, ere
<pb facs="tcp:19647:97"/> he begin to heale, euen ſo he that en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpriſeth his health, muſt firſt of all goe vnto Ieſus Chriſt, the Phiſition of the ſoule, that the cauſe may be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moued, then Phiſicke hath vertue and power to heale, and not before. All power of healing and doing good, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds from him. As the vertue attra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiue, to draw <hi>Eliſha</hi> from his worke, was not in <hi>Elias</hi> cloake,<note place="margin">1. King. 19, 19.20.</note> but in the power of the word: euen ſo the vertue of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling is not in the Phiſitions, nor any thing they take in hand, but in the Lord of life. From the moſt high com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth healing;<note place="margin">Eccles. 38, 2.3.4.</note> the Lord hath created medicins, God hath giuen men know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, that he might be glorified in his wonderfull workes. Men may not ſeeke to Phiſitions, (nor blame them if they be not healed) when they muſt ſeeke to God; neither may they ſeeke to God, when they ſhould ſeeke to Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions. The beſt Phiſition ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not heale, where God ſets not to his hand,<note place="margin">Luke 8, 43.</note> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore blame them not. As for their liues and conuerſations, to ſpeake truely, and
<pb facs="tcp:19647:97"/> in the feare of God indifferently, I take them for the moſt part to be men moſt ciuill in their behauiour, chaſt in their bodies, moderate in their diet, and moſt religious in the ſeruice of almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie God. And ſo I end for the Phiſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, deſiring God to increaſe his graces in them, and to bleſſe their labours in others. Their cauſe is good.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>Vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>um hoc geſtit veritas,</l>
                     <l>ne ignoranta damnetur.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Men doe hurt and endamage themſelues, by committing their bodies into the hands of ſuch as are not warranted by the degrees of learning to be Phiſitions indeed. If you adhibit any credit to my councell, be ſure to know the knowledge and the conſcience of the Phiſition, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you commit your life into his hands; euerie one cannot heale a ſore, that can make a ſalue: ſo euerie one is not a Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, that makes the profeſsion.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19647:98"/>
                  <speaker>Pariſhioner.</speaker>
                  <p>You haue ſaid well for the Lawyer &amp; the Phiſition, now I pray you what is your iudgement concerning preachers and miniſters? for all the world ſaith, they feed themſelues with the ſweat of other mens browes. Whilſt they are buſied with the cares of their wiues and their children, they ſtarue the ſoules of Gods people: and their ill life marres all.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Paſtor.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Ou blame the miniſters for neglecting their charge, and for their ill life and conuerſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; you make no ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception, you conclude all and euerie one within the compaſſe of your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation, as the Pope doth com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend all England within the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe of his curſe. The Elder that is
<pb facs="tcp:19647:98"/> fulleſt of pith, is ſmalleſt of ſtrength; the emptie Caske will giue a great ſound; and the bird Taurus hath a great voice, but a little body; euen ſo you, and ſuch like, haue great will, you haue ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny great words, but God be thanked, no power to hurt. And againe, that which you allow, is ill; that which you miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, is good; becauſe you haue no knowledge to iudge according to truth, you haue no conſcience to iudge accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to charitie, and you haue no place of office publickly to iudge according to iuſtice. Your accuſing of others, is but the excuſing of your ſelfe; your med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling with the miniſters, ſhewes that you cannot away to be reproued; you hate to be reformed, as the holy Ghoſt wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſeth ſaying,<note place="margin">Ioh. 12, 35. 1. Cor. 3, 1.2 2. Theſſ. 3. 2. Pet. 2, 1. Iohn. 2, 1.</note> He that walketh in darkeneſſe, hateth the light; meaning that ſuch as liue lewdly &amp; laſciuiouſly doe hate them that liue godly and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly. A matter very ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge to be ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and hard to be beleeued, that vice ſhould hate vertue, or that the ſheepe ſhuld controle the ſhepheard: therfore
<pb facs="tcp:19647:99"/> Chriſt foreſeeing it, anſwereth by way of interrogation,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 6, 14.15.16.</note> What fellowſhip hath righteouſneſſe with vnrighteouſneſſe? what communion hath light with darkeneſſe? and what concord hath Chriſt with <hi>Beliall?</hi> wherein his diuine maieſtie doth ſhew the ods, the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, the contrarietie, the debate, and the inequality that is between the right and the vnright; betweene the ignorant and the learned; between Atheiſts, Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cures, &amp; ſuch like, &amp; the true followers of Chriſt. The vnrighteous, the open &amp; the obſtinate ſinner, cannot away with the godly and ſinceere man; the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant can not away with the learned; the baſe-borne cannot like with the noble, and it is too true, that the careleſſe and vnconſcionable liuers, will ſhun and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoid the company of the members of Chriſt. You, and the reſt of your fellow bretheren, and partners, haue no other quarrell to the miniſters of God, but that they alſo doe diſdaine, ſhun, and auoid your companies; there is ſuch inequalitie betwixt you and them, that
<pb facs="tcp:19647:99"/> they admit not of your fauour, neither doe they at any time feare you. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I need not ſtudie to anſwere your friuolous queſtions particularly, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in few words to reproue, and with plain tearms to reprehend your baiard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly boldneſſe, in medling with ſuch as are ſo farre aboue your ſelfe, as you are herein beyond the meaſure of mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, and chriſtian duety. Euery baſe and beggerly fellow, euerie lewd and wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton miſtres, euerie prophane and ruſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fianly ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tleman, euerie ſwearing ſwaſh-buckler, and many ſuch as make ſhew of honeſty, and conſcience of religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, in their feaſting, in their gaming, in their riding, in their going, yea, in all their affaires, they will be medling and ſenſuring of miniſters. Some will blame them becauſe of their conuerſation, ſome will deſpiſe them becauſe of their wiues, &amp; ſome will ſlander the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> becauſe of their apparel ſome wil diſdaine them becauſe they be poore, ſome will ſcorne them becauſe they be ritch, and ſome will condemne them becauſe they be
<pb facs="tcp:19647:100"/> couetous; ſome cannot like them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they preach often, ſome will diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mend them becauſe they preach ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome; and ſome will not fauor them becauſe they preach too plaine and ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, and ſome will not loue them if they preach too proſound and deepe; ſome will not loue them if they pray for Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, ſome will not loue them if they pray not for Biſhops; ſome cannot away with Latine, Greeke, and Hebrue, ſome cannot away without it; and ſome can not away with neither. Alas poore ſilly ſouls, of all ſortes the greateſt, ſome miſlikes you, ſcornes you, diſdains you, hates you, and condemnes you. O how few are there that likes you, and loues you? But be of good cheere, (ſaith Chriſt) I haue ouercommed the world,<note place="margin">Ioh. 15, 20.</note> The ſeruant is not greater than his maſter, if they perſecuted me, they will alſo perſecute you, all theſe things will they doe vnto you for my names ſake.<note place="margin">1. Cor 15 14. to 21.</note> Bleſſed are yee, &amp;c. reioice and be glad, for great is your reward in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. If our reward were not with
<pb facs="tcp:19647:100"/> God, then were we of all men moſt mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pariſhioner.</speaker>
                  <p>You are beholding to your ſelfe, and the reſt of your bretheren haue cauſe to praiſe you, and to pray for you. You haue condemned me as a man of no knowledge, of no conſcience, and of no charitie, and you haue made others my partners and aſſotiats, that ſaid nothing at all to you, to iuſtifie your ſelfe and all ſorts of miniſters good and bad, and yet neuertheleſſe you aſſure your ſelues of Gods bleſsing in earth, and of aeternall fauour in heauen.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Paſtor.</speaker>
                  <p>Good Sir, I haue ſaid nothing of my ſelfe, nor for my bretheren but that the Lord hath ſaid and warranted out of his holy word. He it is that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnes all ſuch as you are for medling with other mens matters,<note place="margin">1. Theſſ. 3.11.</note> the holy Ghoſt councelleth you to be quiet, to
<pb facs="tcp:19647:101"/> meddle with your owne buſineſſe, and to worke with your owne hands. <hi>Vziah</hi> was ſtrucken dead when he did but ſet his hand to ſtay the Lords Arke from falling;<note place="margin">2. Sam. 6, 6.7.8.</note> and ſhal you remaine aliue, yea and vnhurt, that put your hands, not to helpe, but to hinder the Lords procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings?<note place="margin">Mat. 18, 1.2.3.</note> Chriſt did promiſe a woe and a heauie iudgement againſt him that of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendeth a little one in the church, or in the ſociety of the faithfull; and ſhall you eſcape this woe and heauie iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that maliciouſly, wilfully, and ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannouſly, doe intreat and handle ſuch as are great, ſuch as are the miniſters, the diſpoſers of Gods ſecreats, and his heauenly Embaſſadours? no, no. I ſpeake not in the commendation of any ſuch as deſerue condemnation, much leſſe did I warrant their iuſtification or bleſsing from the Lord. If their conuerſation be euill, and their doctrine good; take the one, leaue the other: their doctrine doth belong vnto you, their life &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation to themſelues. You ſhall an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer for their doctrine, &amp; not for their
<pb facs="tcp:19647:101"/> doing. The Scribes and Phariſies were counted hipocrites, painted Sepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, and deuourers;<note place="margin">Ma. 23, 1.2.</note> yet Chriſt wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the people to heare them, ſo long as they ſate in <hi>Moſes</hi> chaire, meaning ſo long as they preached truely, and taught the lawe of <hi>Moſes.</hi> And I pray you is the goſpell of Ieſus Chriſt more defiled, and of leſſe force by the ill de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meanors of the miniſters, than the law was through the vileneſſe and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hominations of the Phariſies? no, no, ſo great a maieſtie, and ſo great might the preaching of Gods word hath, as it cannot be diminiſhed by the vileneſſe of the vileſt, nor augme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted by the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of the moſt holieſt: and therefore it is a queſtion generally co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cluded, That a vicious miniſter, preaching the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell truely and continually, doth more good and leſſe harme in the church of God, than an honeſt miniſter and good houſe-keeper, that cannot or will not feed the ſoules of his people, with the continuall preaching of the word. As a ſeale of copper, or of wood, if it be well
<pb facs="tcp:19647:102"/> graued doth make as good an impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion in wax, as a ſeale of ſiluer or of gold: ſo the holy word of God being well de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided and deliuered by an vngodly man, doth make as good an impreſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the ſouls of the ſaints, as if it were deuided and deliuered by a moſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt and an vpright man. God forbid, yea, let it be farre from any man to thinke, much leſſe to teach, that the vileneſſe of the miniſter ſhould dero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate any working, or withhold any force or effect from ſo great a maieſtie as the word of Reconciliation, for then Lord what good ſhall it doe? all men are ſinners, we haue all ſinned, we haue done amiſſe and delt wickedly. We can not exclude the miniſters out of this number. S. <hi>Paule</hi> ſpeaking of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Chriſts death,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 11, 29.</note> ſaith; Who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer eateth and drinketh thereof vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthilie, eateth and drinketh his owne damnation. Is he accounted an vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie receiuer in reſpect of the miniſter? or in reſpect of himſelfe? if it be in reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect of the miniſter, becauſe he is vile,
<pb facs="tcp:19647:102"/> &amp;c. then muſt you make God contrary to himſelfe, who ſaith,<note place="margin">Deut. 24, 18. 2. King. 14, 6. 2. Chro. 2.25, 4.</note> The ſoule that ſinneth ſhall die, and ſhall nor beare the iniquitie of another: and then you muſt alſo grant, that faith in the recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer hath no effect; which is contrarie to S. <hi>Paule,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1. Cor. 13.5.</note> who willeth all men to ſearch and to proue themſelues for the ſame, thereby to make them worthie. If the receiuer be counted vnworthie, in reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect of himſelfe, then it followeth that the receiuer either good or euill, doth not helpe nor hurt in the adminiſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the ſacrament. As the vertue at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractiue to draw iron, is not in the iron, but in the A damant, euen ſo the vertue and power of ſaluation lieth not in the miniſter, but in the power of the word, wrought by the ſpirit. As the raine and the ſnow commeth downe from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, and returneth not thither againe, but watereth the earth and makes it fruictfull: euen ſo (ſaith the Lord) my word ſhall not returne vnto me void,<note place="margin">Eſa. 55.10.11.</note> but it ſhall accompliſh that which I will, and it ſhall proſper in the thing
<pb facs="tcp:19647:103"/> whereto I ſent it. Thus much briefly concerning the truth and dignitie of the word preached. Wherein I haue ſaid nothing to excuſe, much leſſe to iuſtifie the vnlawfull and diſſolute liues of ſome miniſters, and leaſt of all to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce them a bleſsing, as you obie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted vnto me. I muſt leaue them as the builders of an Arke for <hi>Noahs</hi> ſafegard,<note place="margin">Gen. 7, 1.</note> who notwithſtanding were drowned themſelues.<note place="margin">Exo. 25, 8.10.11.</note> I muſt leaue them as the curious workers of the ſanctuarie for the Lord to dwell in, and were ſhut out themſelues. I muſt leaue them as the makers of the Arke,<note place="margin">Nehe. 3.1. &amp;c.</note> the Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle, and the mercie ſeat vpon it, to ſhadow and to defend others and not themſelues. And I muſt leaue them as the ſeuerall builders of <hi>Salomons</hi> tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and were not of the temple of God themſelues. They are like to the Iews, who cried, The Temple of the Lord,<note place="margin">Iere. 7.4.5.</note> The temple of the Lord, this is the Temple of the Lord; when they moſt of all prophaned and defiled the Temple of the Lord. They are like vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb facs="tcp:19647:103"/> the great and learned Philoſophers, who with the effects of Gods ſpirit, taught al men the right way; who wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the graces of the ſame ſpirit, could not find the good and perfect way for themſelues to be ſaued. And they are like to them of whom S. <hi>Paule</hi> ſpeaks,<note place="margin">Rom. 2, 17.18. to 24.</note> that were teachers, inſtructers, &amp; prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers to others, for the auoiding of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulterie, ſtealth, and ſuch other ſinnes, when indeed they were the ſame them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, and ſo by the iudgement of God, Caſtawaies.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 9, 27.</note>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pariſhioner.</speaker>
                  <p>I pray you tell me how are thoſe mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters to be excuſed in this? If any of their pariſh offend them, they will preach it in the pulpit. They wil rather than faile take a place of ſcripture fit for ſuch a purpoſe, and one thing often. This is a verie foule fault, and I aſſure you it is miſliked of many, and beſides forſooth they take ſo much vpon them, as no man in the pariſh can be their
<pb facs="tcp:19647:104"/> betters, and vnleſſe he be a iudge or a iuſtice at the leaſt, not ſo good as they.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Paſtor.</speaker>
                  <p>Here you offer me occaſion to ſpeake infinitly, and world without end, of two things eſpecially which you miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like in the miniſters; one is their vnor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derlie preaching, the other is their ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogancie and pride. Neuertheleſſe I wil be briefe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">2. Tim. 3, 6.</note>All ſcripture is giuen by inſpiration of God, and it is profitable to teach, to improue, to correct, and to inſtuct in righteouſneſſe.</p>
                  <p>Here you ſee that the ſcripture hath ſoure profitable vſes, and therefore it may be deuided into foure parts, which are diſperſed here and there. The firſt for doctrine, neceſſarie to confirme a man in that good he hath begunne. The ſecond is to confute falſe opinions and hereſies. The third to rebuke the vile and filthy conuerſations of men. And the fourth is to comfort the weake, the
<pb facs="tcp:19647:104"/> wearied, and troubled conſcience. It remaineth in the diſcretion of the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſer hereof, to take ſuch a place, one or more of theſe, as the ſtate and condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his people requireth. As he is ſaid to be an vnskilfull Phiſition, that miniſtreth a purgation to clenſe idle humors, when he ſhould miniſter a po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or ointment to ſtrengthen and comfort them: euen ſo is he ſaid to be an vnskilfull and an vndiſcreet Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher, that takes in hand to comfort and to ſtrengthen his auditorie, when they ſhould be ſharpely reproued and corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted. The true deriuation of an Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, and right vſe of a Preacher, is to make choiſe of ſuch matter for the congregation, as is eaſie, profitable, and neceſſarie. All the books of God haue their particular vſes, as the people mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtreth occaſion, and ſpecially the Epiſtles of S. <hi>Paule,</hi> and the Sermons of the Apoſtles. There is no one in the congregation among many thouſands, but ſhall heare himſelfe as it were di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly pointed at, and ſpoken vnto. But
<pb facs="tcp:19647:105"/> now the guiltie conſciences of many, will apply it to the malice or vndiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creetneſſe of the Preacher, as if the Preacher ſpeake againſt drunkenneſſe, then the adulteror will blame him; if he ſpeake of vſurie, then the couetous man will blame him; and if he ſpeake of counterfait and diſſembling mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, then he that wears a mourning cloake or gowne wil blame him. There is ſuch affinity &amp; alliance betwixt theſe and ſuch like ſins, as was betwixt <hi>Hipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates</hi> Twins, when the one wept, the other wept, when the one laughed, the other laughed, and when the one was touched, the other was touched, ones ioy was anothers ioy, &amp; ones griefe was an others grieſe. Euen ſo is it with the wicked and reprobate impes of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uil, ſpeake againſt one, ſpeake againſt all; touch one, touch all, ſo wiſe they are in their generation, as they will not ſay, The Preacher or the Prieſt ſpake againſt me, but he ſpake againſt ſuch a one. Wherin they take away from the word, the maieſty due vnto it; which is
<pb facs="tcp:19647:105"/> to reproue all men; wherein they doe diſanull to themſelues the graces that they ſhould receiue by it, which is to comfort all men: and wherein they do arrogate to themſelues a more ſpeciall intereſt to the word, than indeed is due vnto them. As there is no law by the which a Preacher for his doctrine may be puniſhed, if he ſpeake not againſt the Prince, ſo there is no diuinitie by the which a Preacher is particularly pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed, or generally ordered, if he ſpeake not againſt God, the mightie Prince of peace.</p>
                  <p>I will turne my ſelfe to the cenſures and iudgement of the learned in this point.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>D pudorem cogendus eſt qui ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lefacit, hoc fit, quando male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factum apertè ac diſertis ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis obiſcitur delinquenti. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lioqui vt est apud</hi> Iſocratem, <hi>in oratione ad</hi> Philippum <hi>Macedoniae Regem.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Quod omnibus dicitur, nemeni dicitur.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19647:106"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Vnde fit vt generales iſtae caſtigationes vitiorum tam parum promonent hodie in Eccleſia.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Muſc.</hi> in Mat. 14, pag. 4, 18,</note> 
                     <hi>Nam nemo pudore afficitur, prop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terea quod nemo nominatim corripitur.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Baptiſta Herodem reprehendit.
<list>
                        <item>1 <hi>Su<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Tira<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>num.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>2 <hi>In faciem.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>3 <hi>Aperte in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lico.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>4 <hi>Diſerte non li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cebit tibi.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Si quis vel potator eſt, vel auare agit, vel durius cum vxore aut familia verſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, aut etiam aliquod aliud, quod non de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cet chriſtianum, ſectatur ſtudium: talis ſi venerit ad Paſtorem, non debet recipi à Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore, priuſquam paſtor viderit emendati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onem. Non hic habebit rationem perſonae, ſed miniſterij ſui, non timebit inimicitiam, non odium, non amiſsionem facultatum, non exilium,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Hem.</hi> de Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore pag. 166.</note> 
                     <hi>non mortem, ſed Deum time<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit, cuius vicem gerit, &amp; Chriſtum, pro quo legatione fungitur.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Ambroſius <hi>excommunicauit</hi> Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doſium
<pb facs="tcp:19647:106"/> 
                     <hi>Imperatorem, cum in Theſſaloni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſes tam grauem tyrannidem exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuiſſet. Pet. Mart. in loc. commu. de Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtratu</hi> 10. <hi>In Iudic.</hi> 19. <hi>ad finem. Lege</hi> Necephorum <hi>eccl. hiſt. lib.</hi> 12, <hi>cap.</hi> 41. <hi>Lege lib.</hi> 13, <hi>cap.</hi> 34. <hi>&amp; lib.</hi> 5, <hi>cap.</hi> 41.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Magnum diſcrimen est Dei ſermones tacere, ob triplicem cauſam:</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Vel propter
<list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Timorem.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Pigritiam.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Adulationem.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>Hier. <hi>ſuper illud, ſi dicente me ad impium.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ars artium regimen animarum.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Greg. <hi>in Paſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In Arca erant
<list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Tabulae.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Virga.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Manna.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Sit diſcretio virgae quae ſeriat,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Greg. 3.</note> 
                     <hi>Sit &amp; conſolatio baculi, quae ſuſtentet.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19647:107"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Multo conſilio &amp; prudentia opus eſt Pastori, &amp; mille vt dicitur occulis ad ſpeculandum vndi<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> hebitudinem earum, quas gubernat animarum Chriſoſt. in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alog. lib.</hi> 2.</p>
                  <q>Eadem ſepius inculcanda.</q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Non eſt fidelis miniſtri, prurietibus audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torum ſuorum auribus ſeruire, &amp; ſingulis conſcionibus noui aliquid adferre in medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um: ſed diligenter obſeruare quid illis immineat mali quod vigilantur ſit preca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uendum; deque illo fideliter iterum at<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> iterum praemonere, etiamſi non omnibus ſaepe iterata admonitio arrideat.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Decies repetita placebunt.</hi> Horat. <hi>ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem ſcribere vobis,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Phil. 3.1.</note> 
                     <hi>me quidem non grauat, vos autem tutos, vel cautos reddit.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Eadem ſcribere, mihi quidem non pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grum, vobis autem neceſſarium; eadem ſcribere vobis, me quidem haud piget, vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis autem tutum eſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19647:107"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Quapropter haud negligam vos ſemper commonere de his, tam etſi ſciatis, &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmati ſitis in praeſenti veritate, etſi pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riti.</hi> Hem.<note place="margin">2. Pet. 1, 12.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Bis, ter, gloria,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Dimoſth.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Bis, ter, idem.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Cicero in oratione.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Non vnum hodie, cras aliud,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Chriſoſt.</hi> in Ioh. 13.</note> 
                     <hi>ſed ſemper idem.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>NOw concerning the pride and ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogancie of Preachers.</p>
                  <p>I would not willingly leaue you in any thing vnanſwered, if happely it pleaſe God by your repulſe &amp; ſhame o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers may walke more warely &amp; wiſely in their owne profeſsion, and not to bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie themſelues in other mens callings.</p>
                  <p>Let there be an inquiſition had, and a proclamation made. If there be any miniſter that is a gentleman, either in regard of his birth, or in reſpect of his degrees in learning, or els in conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of his publicke place in the
<pb facs="tcp:19647:108"/> common-weale, that doth ſeeke his owne profit, and not the Lords praiſe; that doth deſire his owne gaine and not the Lords glorie; or that doth ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alt himſelfe aboue the loweſt of the poore members of Chriſt, by vertue thereof, when they ſhould be humble; or that of enuie or malice doth for his reuenge draw the ſword of Gods word againſt any man by priuat or publique adminiſtration, then let him be bound faithfully to doe the ſeruice of Chriſt,<note place="margin">Phil. 1, 1.2. 2. Tim. 2, 1 Ki n. 19, 19. Mat. 9.9.</note> as S. <hi>Paule</hi> was. Let him be preſently commaunded to ſerue the Lord as <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſha</hi> was; and then let him be enforced to forſake his accounts, as <hi>Mathew</hi> was; and if he be not content to doe this, and withall to be a Iew,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 9, 19.20.21.</note> to win the Iewes; to be meeke, to winne them that are meeke; and to vſe all means to winne ſome vnto Chriſt:<note place="margin">1. Sam. 15, 8.9. to 26.</note> then let Gods ſpirit depart from him as it did from <hi>Saul;</hi> and then let his place be giuen to another,<note place="margin">Mat. 28, 3.4.5.6. Acts 1.15. to 26.</note> as it was from <hi>Iudas;</hi> let him be cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked and ſtrangled to death, as a theefe and a murtherer; and let his bowels be
<pb facs="tcp:19647:108"/> drawne, and his body be quartered for the fouls of the aire, as a traitor &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rator.<note place="margin">2. Tim. 3, 1.2 3. Phil. 2.5.6.</note> Chriſt made himſelfe of no repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, although worthy to be taken and eſteemed among the worthieſt, yet he abaſed himſelfe, &amp;c. as he ſaid;<note place="margin">Mat 20 28.</note> I came not to be ſerued, but to ſerue. He waſhed his diſciples feet, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they ſhould haue waſhed his. He paied tribute to <hi>Caeſar,</hi> when <hi>Caeſar</hi> ſhould haue paied him tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute. Chriſt did it not to be praiſed of men, his praiſe was of God; &amp; he did it not to augment his owne glorie, for he had alreadie the fulneſſe of the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head, but to throw down the pride of al men, &amp; eſpecially of the miniſters. He cared not what he did ſo he might win a ſoule. He thought his time wel ſpent, and his life well beſtowed, if at the leaſt he might winne ſome.</p>
                  <p>Let there another proclamation be made, and an inquiſition had:</p>
                  <p>If there be any lawfull Preacher, how poore ſoeuer, that doth derogate from the worthineſſe of his calling, the reuerence, the duety, the aeſtimation,
<pb facs="tcp:19647:109"/> the fauor, the loue, and the honor that is due vnto him, for feare of men, or for loue of mony, or doth ſubmit himſelfe to my Lord or to my Lady, in any ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice that is not beſeeming and meet for ſo great and ſo ſtately a profeſſor; then after the firſt and ſecond admonition let him be ſhut out from the ſociety of the Saints.<note place="margin">Mat. 18 15. to 19.</note> Let him haue no vſe of the word and ſacrament. Let his goods be confiſcated to the vſe of the poore, and let his body be buried amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the beaſts of the field.</p>
                  <p>A miniſter is not a man baſely to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mean himſelfe: ſo great is the maieſty of his meſſage. A miniſter is not meet for the company of mean men, ſo great is his calling: and a miniſter is not to be ſeruant to a king, that will make him ſeruile. As the words of a lord Chancel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor are ſaid to be great becauſe it comes from the King: ſo the words of a mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter are ſaid to be great,<note place="margin">Exod. 4,</note> becauſe it coms from God. Thence the Preachers are ſaid to be the mouth of God, and their wordes a two edged ſword.<note place="margin">Reu. 19.</note> As fire and
<pb facs="tcp:19647:109"/> ſmoke comes out of the mouths of Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſts: ſo Gods iudgements doe come from the mouths of miniſters, by the preaching of the word.<note place="margin">Ioſhua 1.</note> As God ſaid to <hi>Ioſhua;</hi> Whoſoeuer will not obay the wordes of thy mouth, ſhall die: euen ſo he that obayeth not the words of Gods holy miniſters, ſhall ſurely die. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God hath conſtituted and ordained the ſaluation of all men to be receiued by the miniſterie of the word, therefore he hath ſanctified it, he hath beautified and adorned it with the vſe of excellent creatures, with the adoration of Kings, with the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice of all angels, and with the conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall preſence of his owne maieſtie. <hi>Cornelius</hi> was an excellent man, a man full of morall vertues, yet the angell told him that he wanted one thing; the angell might haue told him that one thing,<note place="margin">Acts 10, 1. to 48</note> had not Chriſt determined his perfectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, his inſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; ſaluation to be receiued by the preaching of the word. The Eunuch was faine to admit of <hi>Philip</hi> to preach vnto him, &amp; to baptize
<pb facs="tcp:19647:110"/> him.<note place="margin">Acts 8, 28, to 40.</note> O the might and maieſty royall of Gods moſt holy word! How may the diſpoſers thereof be lightly regarded? nay, by what reaſon, conſcience, or law, may they be abuſed? Will any man that hath a ſonne or a ſeruant that is profitable vnto him in great matters, will he caſt him off, deface him, and euilly intreat him? no, no; but theſe men are profitable vnto you in all things, both for this life and for the life to come, much more then ought they to be accounted, by how much the more they doe profite you and preferre you. <hi>Naaman</hi> though a great lord of king <hi>Arams</hi> court, with his horſes and chariots and all his traine waited at the doore for poore <hi>Eliſeus. Obadiah</hi> a Lord of <hi>Achabs</hi> court,<note place="margin">2 King. 5, 15.</note> fell at <hi>Elias</hi> feet and ſaid; Art thou my Lord <hi>Elias?</hi> The noble Shunamite fell at <hi>Eliſhaes</hi> feet; and the great Lord of the Queene of Candaces court,<note place="margin">1. King. 18, 7 King. 4, 37,</note> thought poore <hi>Philip</hi> a fit &amp; a meet man to ride in his chariot. This makes plaine the authoritie and the great worthineſſe of the miniſters.<note place="margin">Reu 25 8,</note>
                     <pb facs="tcp:19647:110"/> If the Prophets had this aeſtimation and honor, who were ſpeakers of the law and of Chriſt to come, much more now the miniſters who are ſpeakers of the Goſpell, and warranters that Chriſt Ieſus is alreadie come. As the Goſpell is to be preferred before the law, for the worthineſſe of it: ſo the miniſters are to be preferred before the Prophets for their worthineſſe. Kings ſcorning the reproofe of the Prophets, haue bin de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faced to the face of the world.<note place="margin">1. Chro. 18, 19.</note> The mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters haue names of greater Empha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis, of greater accent and authoritie, than <hi>Moſes, Aaron,</hi> and the Prophets.</p>
                  <p>Here now (my good Pariſhioner) I make an end, with my harty praier to Almightie God for you, and for all ſuch as wander out of the way, that hencefoorth you may walke worthie in your owne calling, and grounding your owne foundation ſure, leaſt being troubled with other mens faults, your ſelfe be ſound guilty of ſlaundering Gods moſt holy word, being the inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of your ſaluation, by ſlandering
<pb facs="tcp:19647:111"/> the miniſters of the ſame; to whoſe moſt mercifull direction, I humbly recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend you now and hencefoorth.</p>
               </sp>
               <q>Qui pergit, que volt dicere, que non volt, audiet.</q>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:19647:111"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
